sorry about all the delays hello okay
you hear me okay very good so so we have
talked about approximations in general
then approximation architectures
remember the two main issues that we
have is how to select the architecture
we have discussed this a little bit and
now how do you train an architecture
after you have selected it so that's
what we're going to talk about now
approximate policy evaluation methods
given a certain policy how do you
approximate the cost of that policy the
cost vector one possibility is to select
this cost vector by projection what we
have here is this cost vector sitting in
a very high dimensional space and we
have an approximation subspace defined
by a linear architecture so think of J
nu has been a gigantic vector in a
gigantic space and this subspace being a
lower dimensional one and we want to
find an approximation within the lower
dimensional space the most the the idea
that immediately comes to mind is
projection define some kind of
projection matrix some norm and project
this down from J mu to PI sub J mu okay
now solving this pi is a Euclidean norm
where condition assuming the Euclidean
norm and Euclidean norms lead to
quadratic least squares cost functions
you minimize the sum of the square
errors between J nu and its projection
it's a quadratic problem that you may
try to solve using data using some data
associated with obtain but with policy
mu so this is a sort of a but this comes
to mind immediately and let's see how
this can be done how can it be done by
simulation
we can't have the if we're trying to
evaluate the cost of a policy we'll try
to evaluate the optimal cost is very
difficult to obtain because that's what
we're looking for
however and we can't evaluate the entire
vector J nu what we can do is
selectively look at some states and
obtain the course starting from that
state how can we do that we have a
system and suppose we have a simulator
for this system we simulate on the
computer and we have a certain policy
that again we can simulate we start at a
certain state i and run a lot of
trajectories with it of course the
system is stochastic and we'll have a
lot of generate a lot of different
different trajectories but we can
average the corresponding costs and
obtain an approximation to the expected
cost starting from the given state and
using that policy in other words ideally
to evaluate the projection of J nu we
need to solve this least squares problem
okay our star just associate with the
optimal projector it minimizes the
Euclidean norm error between J nu and
the approximation psy is a weight that
corresponds to the different components
if sy is a vector of all ones then
you've equally weigh the various
components more generally you can
introduce our weighted awake vector Chi
which gives you the which ways the
different errors with the corresponding
values so that's what ideally what the
exact projection is obtained by
minimizing this dysfunction here with
respect to R now the minimization can be
done by setting the gradient with
respect to R to 0 right
it is a it is a standard problem and
it's solution can be written in closed
form so this is the solution the exact
solution of this projection problem okay
you said here we certainly you create a
matrix of derivatives and you invert
that matrix and this is the exact
expression for V for the for the weight
of the projector R star okay now this
seems very simple but it has two major
problems associated with it the first
one is that you don't know the exact
values of all the JMU's remember that
this J news of Pi has many many
components so you can't calculate all of
them the second is that n could be very
very large so this involves a very large
sum of of numbers and also a very large
sum of matrices to embroil
so how are you going to calculate this
remember what I was saying earlier
simulation comes in handy when you want
to calculate approximations to large
sums and if you look at these because
psy is a probability vector this is an
expected value okay it's expected value
of this with the probabilities of
various components are given by the disk
size
this is also an expected value of a
matrix so simulation can be used to
approximate these expected values and do
low dimensional calculations in
particular we select some states we
sample the state space we select states
I 1 up to I K and we calculate the cost
corresponding to these states by using
simulation now you can do this exactly
or you can do it approximately for
example if you are to run an infinite
number of simulations starting from I 1
then you would get the exact value of K
nu at I 1 this should be 1 here however
you may approximate
this J news of i1 using only a few
simulation samples maybe a hundred maybe
ten okay so you generate all these cross
samples you go here you run the system
get a cost value then you run some go to
another state run some cost the
simulation get another cost value and so
on and you collect all of these samples
and you put them together in an
approximation of the expected values
that go into here so in place of this
expected value we use a Monte Carlo
average and instead of this expected
value we use a Monte Carlo average and
that gives you an evaluation an
approximate evaluation of the projection
where the solution using the simulation
based solution can be viewed as an
approximation of the weighting
corresponding to the projection it's a
typical example of how you use
simulation in this field now this is for
the problem oh by the way let me also
mention something else instead of it's
also possible to show that that this
this simulation answer can be obtained
by solving a least squares problem
whereby the cost samples the model for
the core samples is compared with the
sample values that you get and the error
is weighted in a least squares objective
this formulation is the is equivalent to
this so the original the exact problem
of projection is a least squares problem
like that the simulation based version
is one whereby you replace exact values
by sampled values
okay so this is the first method direct
projection of something of interest like
the cost of a policy it's perfectly
viable simple but it's not the best
method it is direct projection but there
also have indirect approximation methods
that are better suited for our context
and one of them is so-called the lurking
approximation galerkin approximation is
an old method that's used very widely in
numerical analysis for solving high
dimensional equations like partial
differential equations using lower
dimensional approximations
it's designed for this context
approximating high dimensional solutions
solutions of of high dimensional
equations now in indirect about pulse
evaluation in gallery approximation
particular instead of projecting the
object that you want to approximate you
project the equation that the object
solves and you solve the projected
equation so here the equation is X this
J mu equals to T mu J nu you project
this equation and using Phi R in place
of of J nu and you solve this equation
in place of the original policy of the
bellman equation the projected form of
belmonts equation pi comes in here on
the right hand side and to interpret
what this does
we're ears here you want to find a Phi R
onto which J mu projects here you want
to find a Phi R such that T mu of I R
projects is exactly on the Phi R
because by the projection involves
least-squares again this is a
least-squares type of equation but it's
not the same as the one that I had
before there are several methods the
most the most famous methods within this
field for solving for policy evaluation
out of this type are Garner in type and
there's a method called TD lambda which
is a stochastic iterative algorithm for
solving this projected equation there's
another method called LS D D lambda the
lambda parameter let me not discuss what
this is LTV and LS D D they it's also a
simulation based approximation of this
equation I'll say a few things about
what LS D really does this is a
projected equation if you make a
simulation based approximation to that
and solve the this approximation then
you get the LS DD method
LSP methods call this response
evaluation the simulation based form of
projecting value iteration instead of
solving this equation what it does it it
conceives an iteration involving this
equation and then solves this
iteratively by by with some form some
simulation involved okay so these are
major names of methods in the field and
it's not my intention now to discuss
them but just to give you the thumbnails
of where things fall this galerkin
approximation is a major type of
approximation methodologies based on
simulation okay now let's go back to the
bellman equation error method where you
minimize the the square of the error in
satisfying Bellman's equation so within
the approximation architecture you want
to find one element that makes this
error in satisfying the government
equation may
minimum the the quadratic objective with
a weight with a vector side with a
weighted by a distribution X I which
weighs differently the different states
now this bellman equation method is
actually a gal dirty method it's just
that it uses a different projection norm
than the Euclidean than the standard
Euclidean norm there's a way that norm
of a different kind that makes this a
guy lurking method so everything you can
say about the alerting methods you can
also say about bellman equation error
methods and that's that's that's an
interesting thing okay so now how do we
implement this indirect method this
projected equation and or bellman error
methods using simulation again the idea
is to cut to generate many random
samples of states using the distribution
some distributions I either of this norm
of the orthonormal projection calculate
many samples of transitions using the
poles that you are evaluating then form
some kind of simulation based
approximation of the optimality
condition for the projection problem or
this problem here and you use sample
averages in place of inner products and
then solve this Monte Carlo
approximation of the optimality
condition to obtain a vector R so let me
summarize all this again in direct
methods ideally solve this equation for
that equation and there are
simulation based approximation to these
where you pick States ok how you pick
them is something that we may discuss
next week you pick States and you
generate random transitions from the
states and you obtain you can obtain
various terms for this error term here
okay and and and then you weigh them
appropriately you sum them up and then
you you form the corresponding in and
then the corresponding simulation
simulated equation involves Monte Carlo
averages and you solve that and you
obtain a solution I guess I'm used too
many words to explain something's very
simple there's something exact we make a
simulation based approximation to it and
we saw yes your comment relates with how
do we select random samples one
possibility is to select them
arbitrarily very regularly another
possibility is to let the system run
using the policy that you are evaluating
and that will take you through and
automatically pick the states pick the
simulation States that's also a
possibility in fact has some advantages
and theoretical advantages however there
are reasons why you may want to add to
make the simulation richer not just go
through the states that the policy takes
you because the policy may have
preference for some states but may never
visit some other states and you want to
be able to get a representative and rich
enough simulation sample if you have one
recurrent class yes in theory if you
have a Markov chain to the singular
recurrent class yes you're right if you
have a singular recurrent class
you're guaranteed to visit all states
however with a fixed points with a given
policy some states may be visited far
more frequently than others it may be a
very rare event that a state a
particular state may be visited and and
and then in a in a in practice that
means that it may never be visited ok
and so you may you may your
approximation may be good in some parts
of the state space but not for others
it's a major problem the problem works
explore explorations make sure that
you're getting a representative sample
from that policy that samples a lot of
states so that you build an
approximation that's good enough across
the state space and not within a
subspace on it have any questions here
ok so here are the issues for
indirectness how do you generate the
samples ok and also how do you calculate
the R vector the solution efficiently
from the simulation based approximation
so both of these are major issues ok
let's talk about another indirect method
this method is called aggregation it's
an old method that appears in many
different fields you have a large number
of states now many of these states are
going to be similar to each other ok
think of a case of states pinch of
graphically related you can think of
many examples
the idea is to group many states that
are similar grouped them together into
single group States or aggregate States
so the number of original States may be
gigantic
but you introduce only a few groups of
states and the idea is to assign a
common value of course to each group so
like a piecewise constant approximation
over groups
solve an aggregate dynamic programming
involving the aggregate states to obtain
the the cost associated with the groups
and then use a common cause for every
state within the group this is called
hard aggregation there are many
different types of aggregations the
simplest type of aggregation here's an
example of hard aggregation here we have
nine states and we introduce groups one
group is this X 1 it has states 1 2 4 &
5 X 2 only two states and so on and
we're going to sort of formulate a
problem that operates on the X space as
opposed to the high space we can encode
these dependencies this membership
relations within the different
activities in this matrix here this
matrix okay it has the row dimension is
the number of states it's 9 in this
particular case the column dimension is
the number of aggregate States is 4 so
you see a 1 every time as the
corresponding state belongs to the
corresponding aggregate group okay
so all of this can be encoded in this
matrix field and it is possible to
generalize this idea and and within a
more mathematical view solve a problem
of this form involved in the current
policy where PR is an approximation to
the to the cost of policy mu okay in the
case of hard aggregation what this fee
are is it's a piecewise constant
approximation but generally if you
choose a different matrix fee and also
you choose a matrix D which is a
probability distribution this type of
equation generalizes the hard
aggregation idea
you can get some some intuition about
what this free Andy do is that if you
consider the original system if you if
you okay this is the system involving
rows and columns if you combine
different columns different rows using a
probability distribution D that that
reduces the row dimension if you combine
different columns using a matrix fee
then you get a smaller column dimension
so in this way you shrink the dimension
of the system and you obtain a system
whose rows and columns are obtained by
weighing the call rows and columns of
the original with some more general view
of the aggregation idea and notice that
the aggregation equation has a very
similar form to the projected equation
in fact if Phi D Phi the big matrix like
this these are matrix like that if that
matrix is a projection matrix then the
aggregation method is a special case or
a projection method it turns out in fact
that card aggregation can be viewed as a
projection method with a special choice
of projection matrix
okay now aggregation can be generalized
a lot like I said any matrix fee and any
matrix D whose called whose rows are
probability distributions and columns
and nd whose was also which its rows are
probability distribution defines an
aggregation method so for example if
this row here were not did not have a
one in the first position and zeros and
let's say I had a row of one fourth one
fourth one fourth one fourth that would
mean that state one has it can be viewed
as a member of each one of this group
with probability 1/4 in other words the
entries of this matrix more generally
encode the degree of membership of a
state within an aggregate state it's the
same thing the same kind of
interpretation the rows and columns of T
let me not go into this but I just want
to tell you that there are many many
different ways of doing aggregation and
this is one way and there is also an
interesting way to view aggregation as
problem approximation the original
system is given here at the top you go
from state I to state J with
probabilities P IJ and with costs GI of
U and J now if you establish a
relationship between the original States
and aggregate States and introduce the
system here then you can think of
transitions of going from aggregate
state to original state a transition and
back to aggregate state and define
through these entries of the matrix D
and the matrix P define a system
involving just the aggregate States the
more complicated system is approximated
with the system whose transitions are
between aggregate states it's a little
bit complicated context concept to grasp
and we need to discuss more examples
however the key thing is that if you
look at this bottom system it's a lower
dimensional system whose transition
probabilities are determined by the
transition probabilities of the original
and whose cost function is also
determined from the from B from the cost
function of the original system and this
transition probabilities the PI the P
hats and the G hats can be set up so
that you solve this lower dimensional
problem an aggregate problem get the
costs for that the cost of states of
this aggregate problem and then use them
to approximate the cost of the states of
the original problem
so here are the main elements of this
methodology solve exactly or
approximately this aggregate problem
involving aggregate probabilities and
aggregate costs it's possible to do that
with any kind of value duration or
policy duration method including
simulation based methods you build a
simulator that moves from aggregate
state to aggregate state using a
simulator of the original and then you
use the optimal cost of the aggregate
problem which gives you a value for
every state every aggregate state to
approximate to make a piecewise or semi
piecewise approximation for the cost of
the original problem
so this is also a problem approximation
the original system where transitions
take place between the original states
is approximated by another system that
involves these aggregate states and the
transitions now are like this back like
this go up and down and any simulator
takes advantage of this kind of system
and what you get is an approximation
based on this structure now one nice
thing about aggregation is that you can
use the algorithm that use the policy
duration algorithm you use is an
approximation for the original problem
but some exact I'll good for the
aggregate problem as a result it behaves
more regularly than in the right general
projection equation approach the
disadvantage of this aggregation
approach is that it is kind of
restrictive on the approximation
architecture that you use because it
involves this probability vectors and
what is the projected equation approach
I can use more general type of
approximation architecture the two major
methods for policy evaluation for
approximation value space and policy
evaluation are these projected equation
types in aggregation types
so now let me say a few things you have
any questions please they can be
completely unrelated yeah they can be
completely unrelated of course if there
are relations you can get different
specific methods but we okay the
disaggregation probabilities are the
elements of this matrix D and the
aggregation problems all the elements of
this matrix fish so the aggregation
probabilities are what you see here in
this particular case and the only
requirement is that the rows of V and D
are probability distributions that's the
only requirement for different choices
of course we get particular interest
particular methods that are interesting
so this hard aggregation soft
aggregation the theory okay so what
you're saying is how do we choose P and
D that's the that's the question and the
answer is by intuition to a great extent
you can you can look at error bounds
there are error bounds that are
associated with this methodology but
when it all comes down to application
it's really intuition how what makes
sense from an intuitive point of view as
an aggregate state and that's if you
have a particular problem like a
queueing problem for example you can you
can think of good aggregate States
pretty easily in one aggregate state is
when the system is nearly empty if it
has zero customers one customer to the
say up to five okay that's one aggregate
state another aggregate state when it's
mid loaded another state wins the heavy
loading fail okay that's so you can take
a system you can take a queue that has
many many states and and reduce it down
to four or five aggregate States
that would be an example of intuition
and similarly if you have a queuing
network for example that might be okay
so we're not doing very well with time
with all the delays so I have a few more
slides and let me cover the first let me
cover a few rather quickly okay so we
have issues of approximate policy
evaluation now policy Direction has two
phases policy evaluation and policy
improvement the policy evaluation the
questions actually are quite easy we
it's the policy improvement questions
that are harder in fact okay so what's
the theoretical basis for approximate
policy Direction I mentioned last time
suppose that you do the policy
evaluation approximately within Delta
and you do the policy improvement also
approximately within epsilon could be
the lab saloons equal to zero then
there's an error bound the sequence of
poles that we generate come within this
bound of the optimal so what this says
that is that eventually you're going to
get cost functions of policies that we
are within a zone of the optimum of this
size typically the way these methods
behave in practice is that you make
steady progress up to a point you may
start with a bad policy that has a cost
that's high and then like the next
iteration may get something that's
better and better and better
up to the point where you get within
this zone close to the open and then you
typically may oscillate within that zone
the oscillations are quite unpredictable
it's very hard to tell what's going to
happen it may be that there are no
oscillations at all aggregation methods
actually do not have any oscillations at
all they they terminate somewhere within
that zone however projection equation
metastatic lead to oscillations and
there's some very discouraging examples
of oscillations that have been
constructed where you don't get good
performance at all the method gets
tacked into a barrel slide
in practice people have not have not
seem to worry very much about
oscillations far from the optimum which
this bomb is kind of loose here okay
it's a gigantic number if alpha is very
close to one this is a huge number but
people don't seem to worry about that
the practical studies that people do the
case studies that people do they do not
seem to report any substantial problems
with oscillations there are some
arguments about this but in any case
there is you may read about some very
bad examples of oscillations and with
fairly simple systems okay so this is
the theoretical basis now here's an
here's an issue that came up just a
little while ago with your question
having to do with exploration how do you
construct simulation samples for a given
policy a given policy has a tendency to
go to some states perhaps but not to
others so if we generate the core
samples using that policy this bias is
the simulation by under representing
states that are unlikely to occur under
this policy as a result the cost
estimates for the underrepresented
States may be highly inaccurate we form
a least-squares objective involved in
simulation samples if the simulation
samples do not do not represent some
states then there is nothing in our
optimization this quest optimization
that we'll provide that will provide an
incentive for good approximation of the
states so if you have an inaccurate
inaccurate cost approximation for some
states when you do policy improvement
this may give you nonsense
for the improved policy so serious
problem in fact the most serious problem
for a practical point of view is how to
construct a rich enough simulation
sample to simply original set of samples
to make sure that the
space is sufficiently well explored so
this is known as inadequate exploration
if you have a deterministic system or if
you have a nearly deterministic system
that's a very acute problem because a
deterministic policy will not randomized
at all between states it will just go
along a single trajectory and as a
result we the some states will never be
visited if you just follow this policy
if you just follow single trajectories
of this of this policy what you need is
to is to create a more artificially
create a rich sample by introducing
states and transitions that do not are
not associated with that policy so there
are some remedies that we are going to
discuss later restart the simulation and
ensure that the initial States a form a
rich and representative subset
occasionally generate transitions that
use a randomly selected control rather
than the one that's dictated by the
policy there are also other methods that
use to Markov chains one for selecting
generating States and the other is to
generate state transitions and all of
this is one of these are very important
topics for research within this field
okay we have been talking about Jan
about approximating cost functions
however if you get this approximation
then the policy improvement requires a
model knowledge of transition
probabilities for all the controls and
if instead we approximate two factors
then we don't need a model that's the
advantage of two factors I mentioned
that earlier and it is possible to use a
parametric approximation for two factors
which would be with have features of
both state and control and weigh them
with corresponding weights are
any method that that I mentioned earlier
projected equation segregation bellman
error and so on can be adaptive to adapt
it to work with two factors rather than
States the reason is that there is a
there is a system who state our state
costs are the two factors you may
construct a multiple chain that has
States not the state I of the original
but state control pairs define
transition probabilities between state
control pairs to other state control
pairs as dictated by the policy and you
can apply all these methods I gave
earlier to this other system that
involves a state the state control pairs
so we can talk about the cost function
approximation and everything applies to
to two factor approximation the methods
transfer through on the other hand with
Q factors for a given policy exploration
is a bigger concern because from a state
I you the only kind of state that you
can get to is a state that you this
would be J here by the way these states
where the control is the one assigned by
the policy at J so from I you you cannot
go to many states you can on Google
fewer states only a subset of states and
there's a problem of exploration okay so
let's take a five minute break and then
I have two or three more slides and then
we'll finish some general issues on on
on on this approximation methodology you
may also think of some questions I'm
sorry I had to rush a little bit in the
last part of this
okay let me turn on this mic hello
okay their way okay some generic issues
that do not fit into what I discussed so
far but they are important one has to do
with with algorithms user use simulation
remember that what we were interested in
is solving some linear systems of
equation using sampling like the linear
system of equation that we solve is the
evaluation equation the bellman equation
for a given policy this a linear system
and it's generally of this type x equals
B plus ax X is not because confusable a
state X is the variable of this generic
linear system okay so any linear system
can be written into this form a is a
square matrix here and B is a vector and
we want to find the vector X that solves
this equation we can do it by matrix
inversion but many people use simulation
to solve such systems in specific
contexts
suppose that we don't have access to a
and B ok a and B is something that that
can be calculated only approximately
within some sampling error instead what
you have is simulation samples of B and
a so B is observed M times with error wk
and a is observed K M times with with
with error WK n WK and capital W K
random they're just the simulation noise
so all we have is this simulation
samples and we want to solve
approximately the system of equations
what kind of methods are there for doing
so well we have the particular context
in mind where this is the system is the
approximate value is the response
evaluation system either the projected
equation or the aggregated equation
creation equations now there are two
kinds of methods one is called
stochastic approximation in the
stochastic iterative algorithm whereby
you start with a certain vector X 0 some
guess of the solution and then you use
the current sample ok of evaluate the
sample version of the right-hand side of
this equation ok the sampled B and the
sampled a multiplied with XK that gives
you sort of a direction to go however
because this term is random you should
not go too far if you should some use
some kind of a step size gamma K now
this step size should be diminishing
actually in order to average the effect
of randomness here typically gamma K is
taken to be proportional to 1 over J ok
something like that and you you form the
XK plus 1 is XK plus gamma K times the
error between the sample the sampled the
sample the error in the sampled version
of the equation the sampling okay this
quantity minus XJ now this is a very old
methodology dates the 50s it has very
strong theory people still working on it
and it's one possibility within our
context stochastic approximation another
possibility is to use this samples of B
and a to construct Monte Carlo averages
ok this is the Monte Carlo average of
the samples of B ok and this is the
Monte Carlo average the sample of a this
is some vector B M and a m and then you
form an approximate sample equation
where the samples are replacing we the
sample averages are replacing the true
quantities and then once you have this
equation you solve it either by matrix
inversion or you solve it
by using some kind of iteration both of
these methods are important within our
context I mentioned earlier this method
of TD lambda and q-learning
TD lambda Q learning are examples of
this approach here you collect samples
and you make iterations of either our
values weight values or Java or two
values two factors in Q learning X is a
Q factor vector and we actually Don
iterate on the entire vector but we
iterate one state control component at
times and a synchronous version of this
stochastic approximation that's what
your learning will turn out to be TD
lamda operates in TD lambda the X vector
here is the R vector the vector weight
it operates on weights using samples in
a an iteration that is a special case of
this form however there are other
methods I mentioned LST D and L SPE they
are of the second type you collect the
samples you form averages of the matrix
and vector that's involved in the
evaluation equation and then you use
matrix inversion for this one all
iterations for this one as a fundamental
division to different kinds of methods
and both of them are useful within our
context and they allow you to solve
linear equations where the composite be
the data of the equation is unknown and
can only be approximated by simulation
so we will come back to this type of
methods but I'm giving you now an
overview of where they fit the second
topic I want to mention is that is
whether we should be approximating cost
well it's a good idea to approximate
cost functions should we approximate
cost functions or something different
there is an argument that says that we
should approximate cost function
Farren says in other words not the cost
at a given state X but rather the
difference between the cost at two
different states why do we want to do
that well suppose that we are at a state
X and we want to compare two controls a
U and u Prime in policy improvement then
we should minimize expected value of G
Plus alpha J nu but to evaluate the two
controls we should evaluate this
quantity and subtract what this quantity
and the answer depends on the sine of
this okay
so what enters into this side is the
cost difference not the cost values in
other words if I take a cost
approximation and I raise everything by
a gigantic amount I'm going to get
exactly the same new policy the policy
improvement operation does not involve
does not depend on a cost constant shift
of the of the function that you
approximate therefore it is cost
function differences that are important
not costs themselves okay look at this
expression is the bellman equation
expression for you and the bellman
equation expression for u Prime where X
bar and X bar prime are the next state
corresponding to u and u Prime so this
cost function different is what's the
important thing and and of course it's
possible to evaluate cost function
different by approximating separately
this approximating separately that and
take the difference but the difference
is subject to noise okay you're
subtracting two quantities that involve
noise you're likely to get garbage if
the two quantities are similar to each
other it's a serious concern
now everything that I've said about
approximating costs also approach
applies to approximating cost
differences instead of calculating an
approximation to this I can calculate an
approximation to D mu corresponding to
two different states and the reason is
very simple if you be the the cost
difference function satisfies the
bellman equation and it's a bellman
equation corresponding to a system that
has a states pairs of states of original
system in particular d mu the cost
function difference satisfies this
equation where the one-stage cost is the
difference of one stage cost that comes
in here plus alpha times the difference
of costs at the next states X bar is the
next date starting projects in human
policy mu X bar prime corresponds to the
next state starting from X prime so if I
view X X prime as the state of a new
system and use as cost function this
then the bellman equation for that
system satisfies this equation and gives
you the cost function differences so
everything I said before about direct
approximation and direct approximation
projected equations and related
equations bellman error applies to this
system as well and that's a way this is
called differential training and it is
you can you can learn these of em this
of mu with with the standard methods now
let me show you an example where cost
function differences are important I
mentioned earlier in the previous
lecture that when it comes to continuous
time optimal control
it's the gradient of the cost to go
function that's important and not the
cost role function because the
hamilton-jacobi bellman equation
involves the gradient of
not J and here's an example this is a
very simple comes from a very simple
optimal control problem continues time
optimal control problem you have a
differential equation that's the
simplest that you can think of X dot
equals u okay X is the state is a scalar
and it evolves according to this
equation U is the control and one way to
address this this problem is to
discretize the time okay so we've talked
about the screens ation so let's
discretize I have a typo here this
should not be XK it should be UK okay
I'm sorry
okay there's a typo here instead of XK
it should be UK so this is the delta
discretization of this differential
equation and within a delta
discretization interval the cost is
quadratic let's take a quadratic cost
Delta is the increment of time increment
multiplying the value of the quadratic
so now let's consider policy and let me
take up just a some policy it's minus 2
sub X it's a stabilizing policy it's as
good as any other policy to try to
evaluate I've taken this particular
policy because this example is done in
more detail in the in the textbook so
I've chosen these particular numbers ok
so now if you calculate this cost
function its exact cost function it has
this form it is quadratic it involves
Delta okay it is it is okay it involves
Delta because because Delta comes into
the dynamics here and to first order it
is quadratic in the state and linear in
Delta and it also has some second-order
terms that are negligible so for small
Delta is the first term here the Q
factor associated with you if you can
calculate it has this form here now a Q
factor involves
at term in the state had term in another
term that that that is negligible when
Delta is small and the control part is
this one here and is proportional to
Delta so if you are at state X and
consider applying you the Q factor
involves a big term in the state and a
small term in the control small because
it's weighted by Delta so it's a
quadratic function with a little
perturbation on top of it now suppose
you approximate this quadratic function
the approximation is going to try to
match itself to this first term it's
going to treat this as noise deglet able
noise least squares methods tend to
mimic the course behavior of the
functions approximated and little
variations are being washed out in any
least squares minimization so if you try
to apply 3d lambda Q learning whatever
width approximation then the important
part of this Q factor is going to be
washed up completely for comparing
policies at state X it's only this last
term that's significant that part is
constant it's only the part that depends
on you and Delta dependent so you may be
approximating something that's big and
the important part may be a small
variation on that but the approximation
does not capture that at all people who
work in approximate in adaptive dynamic
programming in approximate approximate
dynamic programming with continuous-time
systems are well aware of this problem
and they do not use to not use the
standard methods in the same way that
people who work on artificial
intelligence - and the reason is
precisely this you should be
approximating in some context
differences of cost ago values and not
cost to go values
there's some questions on this or the
previous part
okay it's late I'm sorry that this has
been sort of a little bit rough session
with all the difficulties in getting the
projector to work and all that and we'll
meet again on Monday and we'll go into
more specifics
[Applause]