[Music]
okay
so let's continue here with aggregation
remember that we define an aggregate
problem a single problem
it's a simpler problem involving
aggregate states using this
disaggregation aggregation probabilities
we can construct transition
probabilities between aggregate States
and transition costs corresponding to
advocate States and controls we can
consider a policy duration algorithm an
exact policy duration algorithm or any
kind of algorithm that solves this
problem exactly it could be also by
simulation and however when it comes to
policy direction there is a certain
certain deficiency it has to do with the
fact that I have to apply control you
the same control you for all the
aggregate for the entire active State so
policies for this problem consists of
assignment of a common control to all
the states that correspond to X it is
possible to address this deficiency and
that's the first subject I want to
discuss now so here's an alternative
policy Direction algorithm and it deals
with a faculty proceeding policy
direction method uses policy that the
site policies designed are controlled
which aggregate state an alternative is
to use policy duration for a combined
system not this aggregate system over
here but rather consider a super system
a bigger system that involves a state's
both the axes and also the eyes there is
a bellman equation associated with the
system in wood for this system I can
assign controls you to each I rather
than to each X let's the a large system
or combined system now bellman equations
involve equations for X equations for AI
equations for J and related to equations
for y so here are the equations here's
the bellman equation I'm sorry we're
having a problem with the audio I don't
know what I have done wrong
okay so the optimal costs of the
aggregate states are related
using these probabilities to the optimal
cost of states I the states
I satisfy this bellman equation here
with a control chosen within the set use
of I and B we the cost of state J are
related to our stash of Y according to
this equation so this is a set of
equations with unknowns both the J
tildes and the J ones can be our stars
or a much much larger dimensional
setting it is possible to use again
exact policy duration and value
iteration and the simulation is process
is similar involving a simulator of the
system but the computations are more
complicated so so there is this
possibility and their approximate value
iteration and polish the duration
methods associated with it you'll find
this in the literature and salvage it
what kind of method okay the second
issue on the touch upon is the relation
between aggregation and the projection
approaches the projected equation
approach involves linear whaling of
features combined with projection to
solve this equation either with the T
mapping or the team new mapping in the
case of single policy the aggregation
equation looks like this again it
involves linear waiting of features now
the features the the weights have a
different meaning they are related to
the optimal solution or the policy costs
associated with the aggregate
there is a reflection that capital Phi
is is is is is a feature it's a feature
matrix basis a matrix of basis functions
but the basis functions here are defined
in terms of probabilities they are not
general and finally there is the mapping
that multiplies T here it is Phi D the
aggregation disaggregation probabilities
here is a general weighted Euclidean
projection now if the product of Phi and
D is a projection matrix a weighted
projection matrix with respect to some
way that you can Indian norm then the
aggregation approach is a special case
of the projection approach with just a
particular instance of projection okay
so what kinds of aggregations are are
equivalent to some form of projection it
turns out that hard aggregations a
special case in hard aggregation where
fish consists of zeros and ones then
this matrix here can be verified to be a
projection with respect to weights
sy I which are proportional to the
disaggregation probabilities if you
assume this aggregation probabilities
that are you that are positive across
each aggregate state and you consider
all of those and scale them so that they
add up to one you're going to obtain
weights according to which Phi D is
going to be a projection that's simple
to verify
it turns out the card aggregation is
just about the only case for which the
statement can be made if you have
different kinds of aggregation however
there is another statement which falls
and is just as good
suppose that we consider aggregation
with representative features this is the
case where the aggregate states are
subsets of states of the original
problem but they may not exhaust the
entire space remember that this was this
contains a special cases both the hard
aggregation case and the aggregation
with representative states will you use
simple state aggregate States single
States okay single States realizations
then for this case it turns out that 5v
is a projection but not with respect to
a normal a projection with respect to a
semi norm how weighted the second one
where the weights are proportional again
to these however some weights may be
zero that's the meaning of seminar let
me explain this you remember the norm
for the case of Euclidean weighted
projection it involves the sum of the
squares of the components of J weighted
with positive components who has
positive weights this is the case of a
norm and excite here is the vector of
this weight however suppose that you
have some size to be positive and some
others be zero then you don't have a
norm you have instead a semi norm a semi
norm is is you corresponds to having
norm zero for some J's that
not zero standard property of the norm
is that the norm of the zero vector is
zero and any vector whose norm is 0 must
be the zero vector okay norm of J equals
zero if and only if J equals zero or
semi norms this is not true
you may have J norm of J equals zero but
J may be nonzero
it's just that nonzero components
correspond to zero weights okay so this
is another concept that I'm throwing at
you it's possible to consider semi norms
and projection with respect rejected
equation with respect to semi enormous
in order for this approach to make sense
it has to be the case that when you
project on the approximation subspace
with a semi norm there's a unique
projection associated with it okay if
you have that property then everything I
have told you about earlier about
projections Norden projections hold also
for semi norms
the key idea is that this pie gives you
a unique projection and then in that
case with a unique solution to this
equation now in order to get a unique
projection for every vector to be
approximation subspace what you need is
this matrix here to be invertible when
you're calculating projections you
invert this matrix here involves
evolving three prime side the diagonal
matrix of weights and Phi which is this
matrix here in the norm projection case
it's AI is is has all diagonal elements
positive this is invertible provided
there's a full rank assumption for this
free matrix however
this matrix here is small dimensional
and and it is possible that it is
invertible in fact it's very common that
this matrix is invertible even if some
of the components of psy are not zero
basically this matrix is a weighted sum
of rank one matrices and and if
sufficient number with rank one matrices
are included with positive weights in
the sum then this matrix is invertible
so if this matrix is invertible then the
entire theory of algorithms and and
contraction properties and so on
generalizes to semi neuron projected
equations and therefore this entire
theory applies to aggregation problems
as well with this kind of aggregation
and the interesting part about it is
that it provides you a way to bring into
play algorithms that are well known and
trusted in the projected equation area
such as calles TD LSP T V lambda all of
those who work in the context of
aggregation based on the fact that they
can be generalized to semi non
projections so sweeping generalization
of all these algorithms anything that
you can do essentially with projected
equations you can do with aggregation
equations the aggregation context the
only limitation really is the fact that
Phi and D have to be have to have roles
that are probability distributions
that's the only restriction before the
logically there is no there is no
difficulty in using projected equation
methodology to aggregation
this is a recent work and here's a
reference for it a paper from 2012 it's
also briefly discussed in bi9 my 2012
book but not in great detail this paper
also describes the method of freeform
sampling that I mentioned earlier in the
lecture and so it's a broader reference
on the material of of today's lecture
okay I need questions on this
that is very recent probability is not
Arabic for the data like we have all
stayed
act politics or predation probability
probability the act is not ever only for
that yeah your question has to do with
which ones of these probabilities are
positive and which are zero yeah
these probabilities in heart aggregation
are always zero for States I outside the
aggregate state so you have this group
of state and D is 0 for X going outside
and it could be positive for states
inside the assumption here is that for
every aggregate state all these
probabilities are positive ok
the fine matrix here no it's not
identity it is it is the matrix that
that involves the weights involves this
probabilities along some diagonal if all
the the probabilities are equal
okay one over m let's say if m is the
number of states in a good state then it
becomes the identity matrix yes well
even even that I'm not quite sure it may
be okay if all the aggregate states have
the same number of elements okay then if
all the aggregate seeds have the same
number of elements in all states within
each one is equally likely then this Phi
D is going to be the identity matrix
otherwise it will be a matrix that name
of nonzero weights okay I mean not
non-uniform way it's non-uniform weights
and the same thing happens here for this
case except that some of the weights may
be 0 it's a similar process okay
okay you're asked an interesting
question is hard aggregation the only
case for which you have a projection if
you look at the proofs if you look at
the analysis you'll see that it must be
the only one proving this theorem right
maybe it requires some formal argument
but if you just calculate the Phi D and
you look what has to happen you know you
have a projection you see that that this
must be the only only case I believe
that under certain assumptions is the
only case which gives you a projection
but there are many many other cases that
give you a seminar projection
yes exactly
yeah yeah yeah if if X consists of a
number of those then the requirement is
that peas are all positive and the
others are 0 for such they have to be in
card aggregation
okay so so there's a close connection
between this methodology of the
aggregation in projection and it can be
exploited very nicely in many different
ways
I mentioned error bounds for projected
equations this error bounds Terry over
to aggregation I mentioned TD lambda L
STD LSP for projected equations these
can also be this method can also be be
used for aggregation in the involve
multi-step simulation okay from
aggregate state two to regular state to
aggregate state and so on over multiple
steps it's it's easy to generalize all
these algorithms to the aggregation
context and this special case is very
general as I mentioned earlier it sort
of includes some of the basic examples
useful examples of aggregation okay now
let me go into the last topic for
today's lecture which has to do with
parallel computation distributed
computation using aggregation so we want
to consider the composition of the state
space and distribute solution of large
scale discounted problems using hard
aggregation we have discussed already
distributed value iteration whereby we
can do value directions simultaneously
for different states in fact the
directions may be a synchronous and
still the method will work we're
considering something similar here we
partition the the big original state
space into subsets so how much identical
ate space we cut it down into many
pieces
and we have a parallel processor that
will do value iteration on part of the
state space okay so that would be the
way to do it and in fact with earlier
theory that we're discussing the second
lecture applies however still each
processor has to consider not only the
states within its own subset but also
the states in the other subsets because
there may be transitions from his States
into the states of other processors and
they have to be taken into account when
you write Bellman's equation or you do
the value iteration so the idea of
aggregation within this context is to
consider exact values for the local
states and aggregate values for the
other states and these aggregate values
will be computed by the other processors
and sent over to each processor who will
then do an approximate value iteration
using exact values for its own aggregate
values for the remainder of the world so
this is the distributed value iteration
scheme we have a processor l associated
with a subset of states as L and this
processor maintains detail and the exact
local cost J sub I for every original
system state that is local within its
own subset and considered aggregate
costs for the other subsets one number
for each subset so I need to maintain in
my memory just the costs of my own state
and one number for every other processor
so it maintains an aggregate cost within
its own local states and it sets
this aggregate cost to the other
aggregate states or processors so how is
this done processor L now the elf
processor updates J sub I and also the
aggregate cost as follows it does a
value iteration for its local states
which involves the current local cost
vector and an aggregate cost vector
received by other processors so RK is
the vector of aggregate cost vector of
aggregate costs associated with the
other professors at time k and this
mapping is one of those generalized
mappings that I talked to heard in the
class and it involves a form of
Bellman's equation modified to
accommodate aggregate cost so this is
the one stage pause this is the one
stage cost associated with staying I
this is the expected cost to go to local
states to J's within SL and get close to
God for going into states into other
subsets so it's an iteration that
involves a much smaller factor the
vectors of chase and one number per
other processor that sort of aggregates
the the cost of aggregates the current
cost value of the other processors and
the interesting thing about this mapping
is that it is a contraction mapping a
souped norm contraction and therefore
this iteration converges in
converges to a unique solution but also
converges as synchronously when
implemented totally synchronously so
each one of these processors computes
whenever he wishes sends out aggregate
values whenever he wishes that it seems
unpredictably values from other
processors combines them in within this
iteration and even with the
communication some health
I'm concerned that somebody may be
shooting at me maybe I'll just I'll just
take it off okay how about that a new
battery we don't really believe that I
would say that since I'm wearing the
microphone for the video I think we're
fine I just talk a little louder okay
okay can you take it off it's this one
right okay okay maybe a matter of
battery okay so oops that's not the
problem
it may be your problem your your
microphone is is the problem okay how
about now okay okay let me review here
and maybe you can think of your
questions a parallel computing setting
with a partition of the state space two
subsets each processor controls the does
value duration for for the states in the
subset and it does the value duration by
maintaining local costs corresponding to
the local state and aggregate costs that
receives from other processors and also
computes aggregate cost which it sends
out to other processors and this is the
value duration and if you look at this
expression here it's not hard at all to
show that's a contraction mapping and
has a unique fixed point now that unique
fixed point of this mapping here that we
compute this way is not the exact
optimal cost it is something that's
approximate it is locally exact you
might say but it uses approximate
quantities from other processors so it's
something that is related within some
error bound of the exact optimal cost
vector but it is not the optimal thing
however this value Direction involves a
lot less computation than if you were to
do value iteration using exact
quantities okay so this slide shows
basically many other things I've said
already we can show that this iteration
involves a sub norm contraction of
modules alpha so it converges to the
unique solution of this system of
equations the system of equations that
you are operating on this is not balance
equation for the original problem it's
something else it's something
approximate and you can show that it's
actually a contraction mapping using the
fact that this is a the disaggregation
probabilities a former probability
distribution
it's also possible to make a connection
with an aggregate dynamic programming
problem the difference being that the
mapping HD involves the exact values of
J within the subset rather than the
aggregate raddish I mentioned earlier a
synchronous implementation in an a
synchronous version of the algorithm The
Advocate costs may be outdated to
account for communication delays between
aggregate states so the process was
making me communicating irregularly but
no matter what the communication delays
are as long as the processes keep
computing this method will work and the
proof of convergence is based on the
general theory of a synchronous
computation a single distributed
computation that we described in the
second lecture and there is a theory
associated with that that you can find
in the references okay so we reached the
end of a lecture there is we covered in
these last two lectures a very large
domain of problems and methods the
problems are challenging approximation
is is is is a difficult process with the
outcome not very certain there are very
few guarantees in this process you try
to solve very difficult problems and
sometimes we succeed sometimes you do
not there are some interesting methods
that you can choose from and you can try
none of them is guaranteed to have
success however you can try it and if
you have some insight and the standard
theory behind them you have a better
probability of success the two signposts
projected equation aggregation are
related I think with an important point
and they are suitable for different
types of problems there are all sorts of
other issues that we have not covered
and
I've just in the last few slides and
just went through some of them but both
projections projected equations and
aggregation involve a lot of interesting
theory and also a lot of unanswered
questions having to do with exploration
having to do with with oscillations some
of the questions that you asked are
unresolved so let me stop here and let
you ask questions have any questions
yes indeed you are asking whether this
method whether whether this method
solves this problem it will solve this
problem it will solve this system of
equations but that's not the exact
system of equations that we want to
solve it's only another system related
conceptually to the origin no but the
problem is approximately an
approximation in the solution is also an
approximation to what we want to solve
the optimal cost factor
one day there's a website and the other
way the rest of the other states
difficult to think about why there's
[Music]
you okay so why is this mapping a
contraction mapping you simply verify
the definition of a soup norm
contraction in other words you take take
two vectors JR and J bar R Bar and form
the difference and then the fact that
these are probability distributions is
very critical and there is also an alpha
term here and this term is going to drop
out from B from from the from the
difference in what's left is weighted by
alpha and multiplied by probability
distributions and and and okay there are
also these distributions in here the
fact that these are probabilities
tribution and these are probability
distributions is what makes the proof go
through I think I can give a
mathematical proof more easily than I
can give you a conceptual proof as to
why this map is a contraction mapping
yeah I understand that
three is a special
for what's the relationship between
I think
okay the question is the following I
have this aggregation scheme where every
aggregate state is a subset of the
original but it is possible also that
this aggregate states do not exhaust the
same or the entire space and I argued
that with these destructions this
contains special cases all the previous
schemes so for case for example three I
have single a single state to every
representative feature state in example
one which is hard aggregation then I
have the sets again disjoint sets but we
exhaust the entire space example two is
hard aggregation is a special case of
hard aggregation because I am exhausting
the space of features and every state
maps into a unique feature so the states
that correspond to any subset of
features is some subset over here but
all of these subsets exhaust the entire
space it's just that the partition he is
quite irregular it's the partitions
regular in this feature space but it is
irregular in the state space so this is
hard aggregation in the two extreme
cases are hard aggregation and represent
all states exhausted representative
States single state eigenstate so it's
it's covering these two base cases and
everything in between
yes how long is enough yeah okay okay so
the question is all of these methods
require a great deal of simulation and
potentially you don't have enough time
for simulation what's enough time it
depends on you how much patience you
have if you are willing to wait for a
week Vence one thing if you're ready to
only for a day to another but if you are
really pressed for time and you want an
answer in five seconds
then probably it's not going to be
enough it there are possible there are
cases where enough to have enough
simulation time you have to live a
hundred years and so you should avoid
methods like that
they it's always part of the art nothing
is guaranteed there are no failsafe but
there's no failsafe advice here you have
to look at your problem you have to look
at your options you have to look at what
environment you're operating in in some
cases you may need an answer within five
seconds if you have real-time operation
and you have to have a decision ready in
five seconds then you may have to do
your simulation within five seconds and
then perhaps simulation may not be the
right idea maybe a simpler solution may
a simpler approach we may have to be
adopted so I can't answer your question
how much time can we afford because that
depends on your personal circumstances
and also how you apply these methods
these are very complicated methods I
don't want to fool you that they are
easy to apply complicated because of the
many anomalies because of oscillations
explorations what have you also because
they require a lot of computation time
in some problems they may work but in
some other problems they may not
you have to make a judgment for yourself
okay so the question is the following
let's say we consider some method that
requires simulation like the simulation
based solution of projected equations I
mentioned one possibility to use a
single very long simulation trajectory
and also other possibilities of using
shorter trajectories many shorter
trajectories which one to use I think
that it has to do with exploration of a
lot and also it's a matter of trial and
error I would say that if one long
simulation trajectory does not work well
it's unlikely that five trajectories or
four trajectories will work well you
probably need many many shorter
trajectories in order to deal with a
problem of exploration we so so the
again there is no unique answer to your
questions to your to this particular
question you need to you need to have
some insight into your problem and and
and develop a better insight on which
method to use some other questions
okay I think we're done for today and we
have one more election Friday which has
to do with things that we haven't
covered so far and I'm not quite sure
what they will be
[Applause]