you must have gotten examinations this
week
studying for examinations undergraduate
oh I think I worry even worse okay okay
so everything so far has been in the
context of projected equations now we're
going to discuss a different approach
that seems to be fundamentally unrelated
aggregation however we will see that
it's also connected with a projection
equation approach in aggregation the
major idea is to approximate either the
optimal cost function or the the cost
function associated with policies with a
cost go function of a simpler problem so
we have a complicated problem we will
try to look at a simpler version of this
problem and solve that in place of the
original and the approach is aggregation
and the main elements are we introduce a
few aggregate states which are viewed as
the states of an aggregate system our
objective is to formulate an aggregate
problem involving just a few states to
do this we need to define transition
probabilities and cost functions for
this aggregate system and in order to
make the aggregate problem related to
the original the transition
probabilities and cost have to be
related to the transition probabilities
and costs of the of the original problem
and we have to relate original system
states with aggregate States after we do
that we solve exactly or approximately
the aggregate problem by any kind of
new generation of policy direction
perhaps even with simulation based
methods to obtain approximations of J
star and J neo and let's say that
aggregate state Y has an optimal cost or
cost of policy R hat Y so this is a
number associated with aggregate state Y
and there several of those wise we use
the cost function approximation which is
a weighted sum of this our hats so we
have a big state space States J in them
in it and we solve the aggregate problem
a different problem that involves this
few but sort of bigger states we get the
cost of those states and then we use a
weighted sum of these costs of the
approximate of the aggregate problem to
approximate the optimal cost of the
original problem now what are these
weights here first of all their
probabilities they add up to one okay
and we call them the aggregation
probabilities and basically they encode
the degree of membership of J into the
aggregate statewide it's how J relates
to why in some sense that this far here
encodes now notice that you can also
view this Phi terms as features okay
basically this is of the form Phi
capital Phi R capital R so these are
matrix Phi here of the aggregation
probabilities weighted by a vector of
our hats a smaller dimensional version
vote for five hats
so this is a linear architecture with a
few J why are the features of state J
one feature for aggregate state one one
figure for market state two and so on so
at a higher level we're not doing
anything different if it is again
a linear feature based architecture but
the training method is different because
now we're looking at the simplified
problem to get these coefficients so now
let's look at an example and see how we
can get this aggregate problem how we
can define it the simplest example is
hard aggregation in hard aggregation we
have this big original system and we
group various states of the system
together as an example let's say we have
nine states of the original system we
group this four together into a single
aggregate state here we group to here 1
2 and so on so we have nine original
system States and for aggregate States
and the aggregation probabilities in
cart aggregation is what you see here
for state 1 these are the aggregation
probabilities state 1 is going to be
related to the aggregate cost of
aggregate state 1 exactly and so on so
if I solve the aggregate problem somehow
I define this aggregate problem I get
four numbers ok the cost of aggregate
state one cost at least eight two three
and four and my original system cost
function is a piecewise constant
function where all the states in here
have the same cost the aggregate cost of
a state all the states in here the two
states have the idea of the state here
and so on and this is what this field
matrix implies the the the features are
lined up like this the columns are the
basis functions
so after I solve the aggregate problem
that's the way I'm going to recover
approximations to the cost of the
original problem however how do i define
subproblems in particular i have to
define transition probabilities from X 1
to X 2 to X 4 2 X 3 what makes sense
here well to define such transition
probabilities basically we have to
relate them to the transition
probabilities between these states and
these states sort of some kind of an
aggregate probability and the way to do
that so that's the question what should
be the aggregate transition
probabilities of X we may select at
random some state here look at how
transitions whether it transitions
within the same aggregate state what
whether it transitions out of that
aggregate state and define define view
this state single state as
representative of of the aggregate state
and in the defined range problems that
way but which states should I use okay
the simplest probability is to randomize
and to say I'm going to select us when I
am in aggregate state that's one I'm
going to take by at random any one state
of the state's here look at the
transition probabilities and consider
the corresponding to could be provided
probabilistic way describing how from
this state I'll go back into the state
or that state so the simplest
probability is to assume that all the
states in within the ugliest a X are
equally likely
however I can consider more general
randomization whereby I use
disaggregation probabilities for
aggregate state X D X I is a probability
by which I select I within here to
define the transition probability
mechanism to agree rather and gate
States
roughly speaking DXi is the degree to
which I is representative of X okay if
there was a dominant state in here I'd
like to use that state more more
generally if there are more states that
are equal that are important I want to
give positive probabilities to goals as
well
so if I have this DX eyes I solve the
problem of transition probabilities
between x1 and x2 a randomized within
here consider the transition probability
from any one of those and see what part
of the transition probability takes me
to states in the aggregate state to
intuitively that makes sense for had a
creation and it is this mekinese that
were going to generalize so here's the
general framework for aggregation the
original system is described by states I
and J with transition probabilities P IJ
that depends on control we introduced
this aggregate stage we want to define
the transition mechanism from X to Y we
introduce now these two transition these
two probability types the disaggregation
probabilities defined by a matrix D with
elements the X I and the disaggregation
probabilities which are defined by this
matrix Phi and the matrices D and Phi
are arbitrary except for the fact that
their rows have to be transition
probabilities these are the aggregation
probabilities and the meaning of Phi J Y
is the degree of membership of J within
the aggregate state Y so if J is sort of
relates to more than one aggregate
States then I will have more than one
nonzero probability spy in card
aggregation only one v is a one and all
the others are 0 more generally however
you could have a fine matrix involving a
different kind of choice now the
disaggregation probability
given that we are at state X it
randomizes within this piece state of
states I according to these
probabilities selects the state this way
in here and then jumps off to J and then
down to Y and the meaning intuitive
meaning of this reaction probability is
a degree which is representative of X so
once I give you these two matrixes D and
5 you have an aggregation scheme
different choices of D and Phi gives you
different types of aggregation schemes
but the theory of all those is quite
calm
okay now suppose I have given you the
disaggregation probabilities in the
aggregation probabilities you can define
the transition probabilities between x
and y the transition probability from X
to Y is obtained as the product of the
probabilities of going to I then P IJ to
go to J and then down to Y according to
this probability so that's the
transition probability and it's well
defined it's a transition probability
matrix in fact it is given by it's given
by this expression and in matrix form
it's given like so the matrix D
multiplies the matrix P of the original
system and multiplies the matrix fee of
the disaggregation matrix 3 and that's
the compact form of the transition
probability matrix of the aggregate
problems then it depends on you because
this p IJ h depends on you this process
of going like this defines also costs
the cost of using control u at aggregate
State X is obtained by randomization to
go into here then cost GI u of j to go
from here to here and then and then in
that and then that's that that's the
cost that you incur for a transition out
of X so the expected transition cost is
this and in matrix form it is d times P
actually piece of you here times G G
being the cost of the one stage costs so
the vector of one stage cause
so if you have a fixed policy for the
advocate problem you can set up balance
equation for it involving this in that
and you can also consider the optimal
cost of the advocate problem which
involves the corresponding operator team
here is balance equation for the
aggregate problem it is the unique
solution R hat of this equation which
involves G hat the one stage cost of the
aggregate problem and the transition
probabilities of the aggregate problem
this R hat is a vector with one entry
per aggregate state ordinarily a small
dimensional vector if a number of
aggregate states is small suppose that I
solve this equation and I solve the
aggregate problem for the optimal cost
then I can get an approximation of the
optimal cost of the original by using
the spice features in these parts are as
weights there is also a bellman equation
associated with a policy it's linear if
you can solve it then you obtain an
approximation to the cost of a policy by
again a linear combination of the course
of the corresponding policy we aggregate
problem
okay so this is in principle the idea
simplify the problem define the data of
the problem based on the data of the
original problem solve it solve the
simpler problem and then obtain an
approximation to the cost of the
original problem by means of a linear
combination now let's go back and look
at various special cases we know that
the case of card aggregation earlier and
here we group the original system states
two subsets view each subset has an
aggregate state this partition is
exhaustive it covers all the states each
state has to belong to one and only one
aggregate state the aggregation
probabilities are either ones or zeros
depending on the membership of original
system States into adequate States again
the same figure I had before now for
this aggregation probabilities there are
many possibilities for example all the
states within a hydrojet state having
equal probability so if there are let's
say M states within navigate state this
probability would be 1 over m in this
particular case with 1 over 4 1 cast 1 1
half however I may use more general
probabilities as long as as long as they
are positive only within the
corresponding advocate States ok now I
know that earlier that because of the
nature of these of these female tricks
what you get in the end is a piecewise
constant approximation over the
aggregate States so there's a single
value of course associated with each
with all the states within here all the
states within here all the states within
here
it's a piecewise constant approximation
in particular if the optimal cost factor
of the original problem is piecewise
constant over the aggregate states then
hard aggregation is exact okay there is
no approximation error and this suggests
how I should be grouping States into
aggregate states similar states with
similar costs should go together okay it
should be grouped together if I have
some insight about what are similar
States I would be able to group them
together into aggregate States there is
also a variant of the scheme called soft
aggregation where the fee entries within
this matrix are not all of them 1 or 0
but for states that are sort of at the
boundary between to to aggregate states
it may be it may involve a randomization
between the the affiliate States and the
boundary so for example for state 5 this
may involve a 1/2 1/2 here ok or there
may be there may be no other entries
here nonzero entries in place of the
zeros this is called soft aggregation
provides soft boundaries between the
aggregate States and it's a it's
something that that's that that that has
been used and I'm just mentioning it
just to give you an idea of a variety of
possibilities so that hard aggregation
each state belonging to an aggregate
state but there's the question of how do
I pick the boundaries of these states
I should be grouping states with similar
cost into aggregates but how do I decide
that states have similar cost well I may
have good features of the states and
therefore I may make the supposition
that states with similar features
features have
similar costs and should be grouped
together this is called feature based
our aggregation so questions how do we
group States together into aggregate
states so if we know good features then
it makes sense to group together states
that have similar features now this
involves a partition that's based on the
space that's based on a partition space
of features from States I get features
by a by a feature extraction mapping
suppose that I discretize the space of
feature more or less evenly and then I
consider a partition of the state space
according to which States map into which
feature so instead of bothering to
discretize this space here I despise
this space here that may be more
convenient each one of these boxes
within the feature space may be mapped
into a unique aggregate state and that
induces a partition of the set of
original States solve an idea that has
been used many times it's an idea that
makes sense if you have good features so
it's a general approach for passing from
a feature based State representation to
a hard aggregation based representation
and essentially we discretize the space
of features and we generate and the
aggregate problem involves constant
aprox bitwise constant approximation
within each one of these boxes states
that have similar features in that group
together obtain as the same cost and in
the end I have a piecewise constant
approximation
we discussed earlier linear feature
based approximations given a set of
features for a steak weigh them linearly
with a weight vector this is not linear
this is piecewise constant approximation
so it's nonlinear it's a much more
powerful architecture potentially than a
linear architecture because it is
nonlinear in the features but also it
may require a lot of discretization here
and a lot of aggregate states to to
reach the same level of performance as
the level of performance of linear
feature based architectures it's a
different way to use features in
approximation
this is still a hard aggregation method
because every state participate into
some aggregate state now let's look at
something different which also has a
long tradition okay here's the original
state space in fact it could be
continuous has many many states I look
at a small subset of states which I call
representative this black circles are
representative states and I associate
with each one of these states an
aggregate state the disaggregation
probabilities are 1 for 0 for the state
the original system state that happens
to be also a representative it is 1 and
all the others are 0 so so here that's
the disaggregation problems are very
simply defined the aggregation
probabilities which correspond to states
that are not representative involve some
kind of randomization to the
representative States so for every state
of the original system there are these
probabilities that relate them the
representative States so for example you
might have a grid discretization of the
original space and four points that fall
outside the grid you have a
probabilistic mechanism to assign the
two states in the grid
the aggregate system works as follows
you start at some representative state
you generate another state J according
to this green arrows according to the
probable transition probabilities of the
original system and then you go back to
the represented States by means of this
red probabilistic mechanism so in the
end you go from representative state to
representative state according to this
probabilistic mechanism and that defines
the aggregate problem this is what's
used when you discretize a continuous
state space that's a general way to
discretize a continuous state space you
generate a grid and then a mechanism of
passing from the grid to the non grid
bigger space it's very well-suited for
discrete Euclidian space discretization
as in control problems for example also
substantial area of application is for
palm DP I don't know if you've heard the
term from DP from DP but when DP starts
for partially observable Markov decision
problems in partially observable macro
Markov decision problems you do not have
exact knowledge of the state the
controller does not observe the state
itself but rather receives measurements
about the possible whereabouts of the
state and formulates a belief state
which is a probability distribution of
the different states of the problem so
from one belief state I receive a
measurement and I moved to another
belief state that depends on that
measurement and this defines a mark of
decision problem on the space of beliefs
a higher dimensional space a continuous
state space because beliefs live into
the unit simplex okay so to solve this
prompt DP type problem you have this
unit simplex you introduce a
discretization of the simplex and you
define an aggregate transition
probability mechanism that involves just
the discrete sub set of beliefs
formulate the corresponding Markov
decision problem that involves just a
finite state Markov chain solve that in
any way you want even approximately and
that gives you by means of this formula
gives you an approximation the solution
of the pump DP which is piecewise linear
according to this proper list this
probabilistic mechanism I don't want to
get into this but this is typically the
kind of discretization you use for
continuous type of state space
okay now here's another scheme that sort
of contains all the previous one are
special cases instead of having the
representative states I have a
representative subsets so an aggregate
state having a state one is associated
with a subset of states idea state two
is associate another subset of states I
have all the subsets
however the subset may involve more than
one state and they need not cover the
entire space to give you an example with
aggregate state X I may associate a
group of states that has similar
features but some states that do not are
not clearly identified with any one of
the set of features that define this
this set are sort of left outside of the
active States so in this scheme I start
out with some aggregate state I
randomize within here obtain the
transition probabilities to go to other
states and then from there I go to
aggregate States according to the three
probabilities there are some researchers
with the scheme the aggregate states
this subset should be disjoint the
disaggregation probabilities are
positive only within here but zero
outside and the aggregation
probabilities we will hear are equal to
one so if you end up with a state J in
here you stay in here hard aggregation
is the special case where these sets
cover the entire space aggregation we
represent
is a special case where these aggregate
states consist of a single element so
more general scheme in quite generally
applicable any questions so far
about how we formulate these aggregate
problems and the different types of
aggregations that we can use
okay so now assume that we have
formulate an aggregate problem we can
try to do value iteration policy
duration or approximate versions of
those let's focus on approximate policy
duration we define which we are the
typical iteration we have a policy that
map states X into controls and we solve
the corresponding aggregation equation
associated with that policy this is this
equation here R is a fixed point of this
equation here these the matrix like this
team U is the mapping that is
high-dimensional y is the matrix its
allegation matrix and R is the vector of
course of the aggregate States for MU
and then we evaluate the policy
according to this equation and this can
be done by simulation if you can do
simulation of the original system you
can also do simulation of the aggregate
system you just use the aggregation
probabilities to map to happen to go up
this way use the simulator of the
original system to go to J and then use
the disagree the aggregation
probabilities to go to Y back into AI
across down and so on the simulator is
very easy to implement what you once you
have a simulator of the original system
and there is there are simulation based
versions for now for for solving this
equation in these equations actually are
exact we solve exactly this problem by
simulation there is no approximation
involved
now look at this equation here it looks
also like a projected equation the
projected equation has this form so if
PR is equal to feed the tip new PR and
5d is a projection then I also have a
projected equation type of approximation
so it looks like the project an equation
approach but it has the advantage there
is no problem with oscillations
why is there no problem with
oscillations because I'm applying policy
Direction exactly with no approximations
to this smaller problem and I know that
this converges in a finite number of
steps a relative to the projected
equation approach there's a disadvantage
in that there is a restriction for Phi
and for D to be probability distribution
I cannot use arbitrary features they
have to have they have to be defined by
probability distributions and that is
this significant resection
so this approximate policy direction
there is also an approximate value
iteration method associated with this
with this aggregation and it is exact
value iteration for the approximate
problem followed by this feature based
weighting that gives you an
approximation to the original problem
now there are some issues associated
with with this procedure and there are
too many for me to cover what I'd like
to do is cover them selectively in the
last part of this lecture so let's take
a break now and come back and discuss
these have any questions yes okay so the
question is does aggregation help with
the issue of exploration and the answer
is yes it is much easier to implement
exploration in a simulation based
contact context within this setting
because you simply choose you choose a
sampling scheme that involves
exploration adequate exploration of
these states here that's much easier to
do
for example they don't have to be
generated by a single trajectory they
can be generated by just collecting a
set of sample States aggregate States
and using that in one step transitions
this will work and it will any pool and
and it will have absolutely no problem
with exploration so yes it's not only
easier to deal with oscillations within
this context but also exploration is an
additional area where you get a benefit
but the disadvantage of course is that
is this restriction that's
okay so let's take a break and get back
in about ten minutes