maybe there's a way to bring other
people in
okay so let's continue we have been
talking about the approximations to the
two basic methods of discount for
discounted infinite horizon problems
value iteration and for the duration and
we saw the approximate version of value
iteration now let's go into an
approximate version of policy direction
okay so policy Direction starts with a
policy evaluated then computes an
improved policy and so on approximate
policy is either iteration simply
involves an approximation at the policy
evaluation stage instead of solving the
corresponding evaluation equation
exactly which is a linear equation of
gigantic potentially gigantic size we
consider an approximation to that which
involves our approximation architecture
in the parameter R and then we use this
approximation to generate and improve
points so how do we evaluate a typical
Coliseum in this box here we will use a
linear cost function approximation
involving as vector matrix of features
phi phi is a full rank and by n matrix
with columns which are the basis
functions and the i throw is defined is
denoted by Phi so Y prime same notation
as we had earlier and the policy
improvement once I have an approximation
from this box here evaluating the
current policy new policy improvement is
obtained from this equation and I assume
that this is done exactly you could
consider approximations to this
minimization but we'll assume that's
done exactly what we want to focus you
is how to deal with this approximate
policy evaluation for the moment if you
do this and if the policy evaluation is
approximate to within Delta okay
there's an error bound that says that
the successive policies come to within
this expression from the optimum and by
the way this is exactly the same error
bound as approximate value direction so
approximate value Direction an
approximate policy duration give you the
same error bound even though there are
different methods it just turns out this
way so that's the overall framework and
now we want to focus on evaluate
approximate points evaluation so I
mentioned last time that there are two
approaches one direct the direct method
and the other one is the indirect method
in the direct method we have this chain
knew that we want to approximate and we
project it down within the approximation
subspace and we could use simulation to
do that as I mentioned earlier this
approach is legitimate but it is not
very popular and are quite a few reasons
for that one of them is that to
calculate this chain new samples of JMU
you need to do simulation for a given
state you need to calculate the
corresponding cost of the policy so you
have to run the policy many times in
average to obtain some an approximate
version of just one sample of chain U
and then you have to do this for many
states and there's a lot of noise in
this a lot of simulation mode noise
involved in this process and this noise
shows up when you try to use this method
you find that you need an extreme
extreme amount of simulation so people
don't use this method very much instead
the more popular method is the indirect
method whereby instead of projecting the
solution you project the equation itself
this is called the galerkin method and
it amounts to solving this equation if
there was no approximation then we would
not need a projection here so what we do
is we project the equation and try to
find an R that satisfies this
equation so the solution has the
property that when you apply T to it and
then project down you end up at the same
point that's the concept of the solution
here so let's accept that this is a
legitimate method it has arrow bounce
it's it's something that does work to a
certain extent practice how do we
implement it how do we find
approximately a solution to this by
simulation that's our issue well first
of all generally projection as I
mentioned can be implemented by
simulation in these squares so somehow
we have to find a way to factor a really
simulation in these squares into this
equation here okay so let's focus on on
this method that uses indirect policy
evaluation given the current policy we
solve this projected equation and then
we approximate so basically we
approximate the solution of balanced
equation with a solution of projected
equation in color questions here well
first of all does the projected equation
have a solution
how do we know that has a solution how
do we know that has a unique solution so
under and so this is the same as asking
under what condition is this mapping PI
T at contraction so that PI T has a
unique fixed point and remember this is
the same issue that we raised earlier
under what circumstances the team a P
and the projection are matched so that
PI T is a contraction so now here's the
magical thing we are going to determine
a weighted norm under which this is a
contraction and here is the assumption
we assume that the Markov chain
corresponding to the current policy
gadi it has a single recurrent class and
no transient states so you plug in this
policy Markov chain runs and it visits
all states infinitely often with certain
long-term frequencies and these
long-term frequencies are we
steady-state probabilities this is
standard Markov chain theory you have a
singular recurrent class no transient
States then the steady state
probabilities
okay these are occupation measures or
the average probability that you will be
at state J if you start at state I in
the limit this is independent of where
you start and it is positive so this
steady-state distribution which is the
state with the distribution involved in
the long term frequencies of the various
states is a positive vector okay and now
we are going to use projection with
respect to this factor and things will
work out this is a magical norm that we
are used that we are looking for here is
a proposition suppose that a projection
is with respect to this distribution
norm okay then PI T nu is a contraction
of modules alpha with respect to this
norm and moreover the unique fixed point
of this mapping which is what we are
going to use to approximate a new has an
error bound that satisfies this relation
okay notice that what you get is not the
projection of Jamie but the distance of
J nu from this approximation is bounded
by a scalar multiple of the distance or
chain you from the approximation
subspace always with respect to this
norm
for the moment this bound is not
important what's important is that I
have found some sampling distribution
with respect to which to do the
projection so that I get a solution of
this equation and the process the ND and
the divergence that I experienced in the
previous method does not occur
okay so let's say a few things about why
this thing works first of all let's talk
about projections an important property
of projection onto a subspace spanned by
the columns of a matrix fee is the tag
Orient theorem okay projection this
vector is orthogonal to this vector here
in the square of the distance or is
equal to the sum of the squares of these
two norms okay
this is a an abstract extensions of the
classical Pythagorean theorem for
triangles for orthogonal triangles and
the orthogonality of courses with
respect to the sky here and here's the
second important fact for us projection
is non expensive if you project two
vectors J and J bar with respect to a
projection a weighted Euclidean
projection norm then the distance of the
projection is smaller or at least no
larger than the distance of the vectors
and the proof of this is one line the
difference between the projections which
is this because pi is linear is less
than that plus some positive thing and
by by the projection theorem by the
Gordian theorem this sum here is equal
to J minus J bar let's not focus on this
algebra just suffice it to say that's a
one-line proof based on the Pythagorean
theorem
now here is the important theorem and
applies to any Markov chain but these
are body suppose that you have a Markov
chain that corresponds let's say the one
that corresponds to a policy new and P
is its transition probability matrix and
sy is the steady state probability
vector corresponding to this Markov
chain then you have this inequality
holding okay so take any vector Z apply
this probability this transition
probability sort of randomized according
to T and we get something that's smaller
a smaller norm okay
the proof of this takes takes like five
minutes to go through it involves you do
the natural things take the square of
that write it in terms of V of sy
okay this is equal to this by definition
and then you use okay there's a there's
a convexity property of a quadratic that
you use here and using the steady state
okay take this out here and then use the
definition of steady state probabilities
you get this equality and this is
precisely the the the norm of Z squared
so it's a one-line proof a little tricky
and but it still fits in one paragraph
so that's not the time to do this detail
proofs here but I want to show you that
this is relatively simple now once I
have this relationship then I used a non
expensiveness of Phi in the definition
the definition of T news of J involves
the cost vector of mu and also the
transition probability matrix of new and
the difference okay I want you to see
how to to look at the difference of Pi T
applied on to generic vectors J and J
bar because of this inequality here when
you subtract these two this goes away
and what's left is okay first we use the
non expensiveness of the projection okay
to get this relation in this relation is
equal to this and now I use this lemma
to get the last part of inequality which
says that PI T is a contraction with
modulus alpha so that's it very simple
proof to establish the right norm for
projection which is the steady state
distribution of the current policy
yes you use the property of their body
because if Sai does not have positive
components everywhere then this is not a
norm anymore okay
you have to have positive components
oxide for it to qualify as a norm
okay so there is also this proof of the
error bound and against a one-line proof
which I will not go through the first
equality here uses the Ligurian theorem
the second inequality uses the second
equality is because jail use a fixed
point of T and Phi R star the
approximations effects point of Pi T and
finally this by we by the fact that PI T
is a contraction of modulus alpha gives
you this take this on the other side and
divide and you get the result that's
that so what it says is that if you
project J according to this side
distribution the corresponding Markov
chain then the error that of that that
that you get is something that is
bounded by the minimum possible error
over the approximation subspace
okay so all of this fuss was to show
this proposition okay now what we're
going to do is put this proposition into
practice using simulation so we have to
project this equation and when we want
to see how do you solve it by simulation
again here's the figure we have a given
policy and the team new mapping is given
by this with PI being the distribution
the transition probability matrix of MU
and G being the cost vector and I want
to find R where Phi R is an element of
the approximation subspace that solves
this equation here okay now I have a
projection here from T news of VR into
fee R and this project in this distance
is orthogonal to be approximation
subspace this is the orthogonality
principle in particular the error the
difference between this and that this
broken line okay is orthogonal to the
subspace spanned by the columns of fee
okay so this error is orthogonal to the
columns of fee
but orthogonal in the sense of the side
normally capital side here is a diagonal
matrix with the steady state
probabilities along the diagonal okay so
that's what we mean by orthogonality
orthogonality with respect to B to the
scaled norm of projection
so the projected equation is equivalent
to a matrix equation and this matrix
equation is just this C R star equals 2d
with the matrix C being you read it from
here Phi X I times I minus AP and Phi
and the constant is this times that so
now this project equation is seeing a
little abstract it has become very
concrete it's just a matrix equation
what's the dimension of this matrix
equation it is small small because the
row dimension because the column
dimension of field is small so this
equation is s by s naught n by n ok it's
a low dimensional equation however
computing this matrix so if I could
compute this matrix a and the vector D
that would be great it would that you
can give to MATLAB okay it's a low
dimensional matrix inversion give it to
MATLAB it will give you the answer but
there is a catch here you cannot
calculate this matrix C easily because
it involves vector or matrix or matrix
matrix multiplies that are high
dimensional this fee prime matrix is
like this it's multiplied with a big
huge gigantic diagonal matrix sigh and a
gigantic matrix again and by n so this
is a huge calculation even though the
end result is low dimensional this is a
huge calculation similarly here I have
this Phi prime which is like this
multiplied with X I which is gigantic
and multiplied with G which is also
gigantic all this inner products end up
you a low dimensional vector but
carrying out these calculations is
difficult what's the answer to this well
last time I mentioned that the primary
use of simulation within our context is
to be able to make huge inner products
make them manageable by sampling instead
of adding all the terms and similarly
that's what we do here we calculate
simulation based approximations of C and
D that are manageable and then we use
the approximations in place of the real
things in this equation and get an
approximation to our star
okay
so suppose that we have I give you C and
D some hub in a magical way we have
found C and D I can solve this by matrix
inversion assuming of course that c is
invertible okay which is not entirely a
trivial issue assuming that is
invertible you can use just matrix
inversion the alternative to matrix
inversion is to solve this linear
equation by iteration linear equations
are solved in two ways either by matrix
inversion or by using some kind of an
iterative method to solve them in
particular we may try to use this
iteration which is called projected
value iteration it's similar to be to
the to the one that I discussed earlier
fitted value iteration how the direction
K you have fields of RK and
approximation of the what you're trying
to compute me Jane you back to apply PI
T to it and then get a new approximation
and keep going
so here's approximate excuse projected
value Direction you are at phase of RK
you go to T Sofia of RK which is this
expression here project it down yet RK
plus one then get another one project
another one project and so on now this
can be also written in terms of the
matrices C and the vector D in
particular the projected iteration tries
to find the vector RK plus 1 such that
the distance between these two is
minimized okay so this is a least
squares problem in our setting the
gradient of this objective to 0 you get
this equation here and after you
manipulate it you see that the new
vector RK plus 1 is given by the old
vector times
some some correction which is
proportional to the residual the error
that RK makes in satisfying the equation
and there is also this matrix here so
again this is a low dimensional
direction but it involves some gigantic
inner products in here in here in here
in this gigantic in their products our
next step is to address them by
simulation to approximate them by
simulation these are two major methods
for solving projected equations but of
course the solution here is exact the
first one leads to a method called LS TD
the second least unethical LSP and we're
going to get into this method shortly
there are also some other methods but we
can't we can't get into those present
okay have any questions here so now what
we're going to do is use sampling to
approximate the Mac in the matrix and
vector involved in this projected
equation approximate C with CJ
approximate deal with DJ and then after
we do that then the matrix inversion
method is approximately implemented like
so this is the air HDD method probably
the most popular method for solving
projected equations calculate by
simulation approximations to C and D and
just use the inverse the alternative is
to consider this projected value
iteration and replace this C with ck
replace D with D K and replace this
again the simulation based approximation
which is possible to do by sampling
and the key fact is that these
approximations can be computed with low
dimensional linear algebra of order of
the number of basis functions in not
only dimension of the space
any questions okay
so now I have a matrix that I want to
approximate by simulation what do I do
well against the old trick if you want
to calculate quantities by simulation
you express them as expected values
somehow you put you you express them as
expectation with respect to some
distribution and then you sample
according to that distribution and you
make the approximate it's similar here
we collect now the main thing if what's
important is to introduce a sampling
method that involves the steady steady
probabilities of the Markov chain so we
can't generate samples arbitrarily but
instead we use the Markov chain to
generate the samples so we have this
Markov chain
I want to involve in the simulation the
size of that Markov chain so I run an
infinitely long trajectory of this
Markov chain it generates a sequence
starting from this state it generates
another state another state and so on
because of the ergodicity that i have
assumed all the states and all the
transitions appear with long term
frequencies I I and P IJ T IJ being the
transition probabilities
with every transition that I generate I
compute the corresponding row or fee
this is a low dimensional vector and the
corresponding cost component so I try
attic simulation infinitely long gives
me a lot of samples of states and
transitions with corresponding costs and
the states appear with this distribution
the transitions appear with a product of
these two distributions and now the
formulas are given here I want to
approximate this vector here okay it
involves this matrix side and this
vector hi view this has an expected
value I write it like this okay if you
expand P and P and so on you can be
written exactly like so and now you can
see that it is a it is an expectation
involving these probabilities now my
simulation generates these probabilities
they are the probabilities of these
transitions SCI is a probability of
being a state i p IJ is a probability of
going to state J afterwards so this is
the steady state long term frequency of
transitions like that and the Monte
Carlo estimate of this is precisely this
so that's the simulation-based estimate
of the D vector run an infinitely long
sequence states and transitions occur
with the right probabilities yeah if you
average this expression by Monte Carlo
up to time K will generate K samples a
fine number of samples it's an
approximation to this that converges to
it for K going to infinity with an
infinite number of samples notice that
everything here is finite is low
dimensional Phi is a small dimensional
vector and this is a number so I'm just
average in small dimensional vectors and
nowhere do I have to deal with a large
dimension of a Markov chain it's the
sampling that takes care of visiting the
various states
now the projected equation involves a
matrix ela vector D the vector D is
obtained like so the matrix C is this
matrix here again low-dimensional but
with gigantic inner products and matrix
multiplies in here and it turns out ok
it takes a little bit of algebra to see
that this can be written again as an
expected value and this expected value
can be approximated by Monte Carlo like
this ok so look what this is it's a
small column vector multiplied with a
small role vector okay so these are
small matrices small rank one matrices
which I averaged over over a large
number of transitions
and that's basically it these are the
formulas and of course there are
extensions but these are the basic
formulas if I also need to calculate
this matrix here I can I can also the
same simulation can give me a simulation
based approximation to this and this is
useful in the case of the iterative
method yes yes right the question is the
following do I need do I need to know
sigh I don't need to know it I just let
the Markov chain work and automatically
it generates transitions and States
according to science I write so I need a
simulator of the Markov chain right yeah
ok ok I'm right you're absolutely right
your question has to do also with
whether we do need this assumption we do
and we don't okay we definitely need it
for the theory as I gave it to you but
there's a version of the theory that
allows you to to allows approximations
of Markov chains that are not exotic and
then what you get with the simulation
procedure is a little different but it's
still usable basically you get you get
that's right yeah ok you bringing up
another interesting question if my
simulation faithfully follows the Markov
chain then I'm going to be encounter
states that are preferred by that Markov
chain so when I do my approximation I'm
going to have more samples from the
preferential States that this policy
likes and the corresponding
approximation is going to be biased
towards those preferred States and so I
may have large errors for the other
states the problem of exploration which
I touched upon you bring it up again
it's a very very important problem and
also probably deal with on Wednesday ok
we're going to focus on policy issues of
policy improvement on Wednesday today
we're focusing only on issues of policy
evaluation without regard of the fact
that we're going to need the policy
evaluation to do policy improvement with
the next policy so that's let's let's
postpone this question until until
Wednesday
so the first I understand we facility
we've had this because the Markov chain
is a positive dependent so we assume we
have the right
in January to be so laughter especially
yes yes the question is that do we need
to have do we need to to be able to
implement this particular policy the
answer is yes somehow either you need to
have some analytical expression or more
likely to be able to simulate
transitions from a given policy now note
that even though we do not have the
policy has a vector of actions because
that's too big the assumption is that at
any state we can generate the action of
that policy there's a computer routine
that goes in and finds the action of
that policy typically of course by just
doing a policy improvement on the
preceding policy so that's so so in
other words you generate the action in
the corresponding transitions as you go
you don't need to have a model ahead of
time and that's that's there's no way to
avoid that
yeah
question so in the practice we always
have a very finite number of samples so
is there any results about onami simple
passes prior to getting high quality
restoration of
yeah the question has to do with how
many samples do we need to have an
accurate accurate enough approximation
of C and D for this method to work in
there are a lot of unanswered questions
around this issue impact in in theory
you would like to have many many samples
that would make the evaluation of each
policy quite expensive in practice
practitioners actually use very few
samples and put their faith in God hope
that this will work and I have a slide
about that
well first of all it's very important to
do exploration and to use a somewhat
rich sample of States to visit also
there are some algorithms that use
relatively few samples with each policy
evaluation but at the same time do not
make the full change than the new policy
okay they change the R vector a little
bit okay and the iterative methods are
better at that but there's a lot of art
in here and there are few performance
guarantees in theory you cannot
guarantee very much theory only gives an
indication of what tricks to try and
then and then you try them and hopefully
they work that's that's the way there is
actually
okay so convergence here depends on the
law of large numbers requires an
infinite number of samples and there is
also a certain theory of sometimes these
methods are called temporal differences
methods and I'm not going to get into
what's a temporal difference is
basically the sum of these two
quantities here and because this
temporal differences appear in all kinds
of implementations of this methodology
very often people view the temporal
differences has been an important
important quantity and and and they call
the methods temporal difference methods
to me temporal differences are not all
that important they just happen to
appear in various mathematical
calculations but you may make up your
own mind if you wish to go a little
further into this field okay so now let
me come to a question simulation this is
the standard version of approximate
policy direction with an infinite number
of samples in between policy evaluations
instead of calculating nearly exact
approximations it is possible to do a
less accurate approximation based on
just a few simulation samples as I
mentioned earlier and this is called
optimistic policy direction why is it
called optimistic well first of all we
can't under the name optimistic earlier
as the value of the policy Direction
could use only a few value iterations to
to to up to to do a policy evaluation
here it's a similar setting but a lot
different because the first number of
simulation samples there are optimistic
methods that just is one sample and they
immediately change the
the BR vector with one sample others
that use a hundred samples other that
use a thousand samples very few methods
in practice use an infinite or the
extremely large number of samples often
you get better results but there's no
Theory really for these methods okay
when you have approximation and and
often times the behavior is very complex
and in the next lecture I'm going we're
going to talk about how oscillations may
occur in how these optimistic methods
may make the oscillations even worse now
here is something that you can say
genetically the matrix inversion method
inverts an approximation matrix ek but
if the accuracy of this approximation is
low the CK matrix will have a lot of
noise if you try to invert the matrix
that has a lot of noise in it then we
get nonsense very often particularly if
the matrix is nearly singular as they
often are here so there's a serious
problem with with the matrix inversion
method because if you have limited
sampling particularly for Co conditioned
the LSPD method does not involve this
matrix inversion tends to cope a little
better because it's also iterative in
nature it adjusts the vector R little by
little and in the meantime accumulates
more relevant samples it's also possible
to put a little step size in front of
the correction of the iterative method
this gamma is a step size which can be
taken to be small so that with few
samples you do only you do only a small
correction
and the noises sort of tends to
attenuate the simulation noise this
gamma step sighs there's a lot of art
involved here and and don't expect
success the first time you try this
well you have okay so what is the
simulation now it's a question is quite
the simulation noise and and whether it
is what is it harmful well there's a we
want to approximate D by something that
involves the noise here so the noise is
DK minus D and similarly here the more
samples that you get the noise is
reduced on the other hand still agree
from the smaller amount of noise this
matrix may become singular or give you
very different inverse that this matrix
here so if you're going to use this
matrix inversion method it's important
that you sort of match the the the
amount of simulation that you do to the
to be the condition number of that
matrix but clearly from the point of
view of inversion the more samples you
get the better off you are but how many
you need is not very clear
okay now there are some generalizations
of this methodology that I want to cover
in the last part of this lecture so
let's take a break for ten minutes I
have a few more slides