okay so let me welcome you to this fifth
out of six lectures on approximate
dynamic programming we spent the first
three lectures on exact dynamic
programming and also an overview of the
general issues in approximate dynamic
programming in this week starting with
the previous lecture we're going to
focus selectively somewhat deeper on
various aspects of approximate dynamic
programming now we talked about
approximate policy duration based on
projected bellman equations last time
however policy duration involves two
aspects there are two parts to each
iteration one is evaluating the current
policy and that's what we talked about
last time approximate evaluation of
policies based on projected bellman
equations and then there's a second part
of iteration that has to do with the
policy improvement process and this
involves issues that are tricky and
important and we're going to discuss
those first in particular we talked
about the issue of exploration which we
touched upon last time how do you
introduce exploration into the
approximate policy iteration process and
then talk about the issue of
oscillations approximate policy duration
is not guaranteed to converge to a
single policy typically or very often it
will just generate a cycle of policies
many policies perhaps and we want to
look at the mechanisms by which these
oscillations occur and see what they can
do to us after we do that we are going
to discuss an alternative to the project
development equations for approximate
policy evaluation and also for
approximate value duration which is
aggregation
this is a very simple approach it dates
to way back
years and and it is related to the
projected equation approached and we
will discuss this this disconnection
after we describe it give some examples
and we say a few things about how we can
implement them by simulation okay so we
continue to look at finite state
discounted infinite horizon Markov
decision problems we have transition
probabilities going from different
states which depend on the control we
want to pick controls so as to minimize
the cost of policies and for a given
policy a sequence of functions from
state to control we have a cost per
stage and and a long-term cost that's
associated with it for any given
starting state is zero by taking the
limit of the expected value of the
series gives you the cost of the policy
at state I and because alpha the
discount factor is between is less than
strictly less than one we are guaranteed
that this is well defined and we want to
find pi such that this is minimized
simultaneously for all states now we
have discussed the special significance
of stationary policies stationary
policies are the ones where the news do
not change from one stage to the next
we have given various optimality
conditions and all that and let me
remind you again of the shorthand
notation for the dynamic programming
mapping and also for the evaluation
mapping corresponding to a policy
whereby given any J we generate t news
of J by means of this linear equation
were this nonlinear equation we solve a
fixpoint equation involving t in in in
to obtain the optimal cost and we solved
the Optima be the bellman equation
involving tinu
to obtain an evaluation of the
polycythemia okay so approximate policy
Direction it's the same thing as exact
policy direction except that we
evaluation instead of finding J nu we
find some approximation to that
involving an approximation architecture
with art being the vector of parameters
in the approximation architecture
evaluate approximately new generate and
improve policy by the prop policy
improvement equation and look around in
the sweat now we focused on linear cost
function approximation involving a
matrix field ok dimension and the row
dimension and column dimension much
smaller yes the columns of this matrix
are our basis functions for a subspace
defined by by vectors like this so we
are looking to find an approximation of
J nu within the sub space of functions
of this form if we call the I throw of v
VI prime which is a small vector like
that the policy improvement process
involves this equation so if I give you
are a good are you can get a good new ok
if I give you a very good art then you
can get a policy that's as good as you
can get it with approximation so the
issue is how do I get a good R and in
the process we discuss we focus on the
right on the evaluation part of the
policy iteration procedure instead of
finding a fixed point of T mu we find a
fixed point of PI mu we solve this
equation which is the projected
equation involving a projection
operation Pi which is Euclidean sum of
squares but also waited waited by
positive numbers the size and we can
normalize the size so that they form a
probability distribution and in this
context we mentioned that given the
policy and assuming this policy gives
you an ergodic Markov chain with a
positive steady state probability
distribution vector then the steady
state distribution waiting the oxide
vector corresponding to quick which is
the state the state the the vector of
steady state probabilities when you do
projection with that then PI T nu has a
unique solution and is tightly Newser
contraction has a unique solution and a
lot of other nice things occur such as
for example various algorithms become
valid including approximate value
iteration and then the methods of LSP
Els DV and so on become possible and the
implementation of the solution of this
equation we know that the possibility of
doing it by generating a single long
trajectory using the current policy this
implicitly generates weights that are
the steady state distribution wait and
make the PI T new mapping a contraction
okay
so that was the gist of last most of
most of what we discussed in the last in
the last time how do you why the steady
state distribution is important and how
do you do a simulation based solution of
this equation using a single long
trajectory that involves the steady
state probabilities in an average sense
there were a number of issues that were
related to this and we're going to focus
on some of them in this lecture but let
me also remind you that there's a
multi-step option in projected equations
whereby instead of solving this equation
you solve an equation involving a
weighted version of T nu whereby T mu
lambda is the sum of powers of T nu with
lambda between 0 and 1 so it's a
geometrically weighted sum of powers of
T mu and this mapping has exactly the
same fixed points as team you okay and
also is a contraction because TMU is a
contraction however has lambda changes
then the projection of this mapping
becomes different of course depends on
lambda its fixed point is different and
also its modulus of contraction is
different as lambda goes to always 1
this becomes a perfect contraction and
this allows you to change this pi from
the steady state distribution and still
have a contraction okay so that will
come into the process of exploration
exploration becomes better behaved when
you have a lambda greater than zero
because you have better contraction
properties however another major aspect
of the weighted bellman equation lambda
weighted is that its solution depends on
lambda and for lambda equals zero that
case over there
it's something that involves an error
that you see here as lambda changes
towards 1 then this error becomes
smaller in for lambda exactly equal to 1
you get the best possible approximation
error just the direct projection onto
the
approximation subspace however to solve
this projected equation involves more
noise because yes you make simulation
based evaluations of this way that sums
each one of those involves more noise
because it's a mapping that relates far
into the future
so more noisy terms more noise here you
need more samples to counteract the
effects of this noise so that's the
typical behavior the typical trade of
great large lambda smaller approximation
error but we need more samples to
generate an accurate solution so
so-called bias-variance tradeoff okay
we're not going to come back to this
other than the fact that as lambda
approaches 1 this contraction property
is improved ok so that's all we did last
time the policy evaluation part and how
to solve it
ok now let's call let's talk about
policy improvement
the first major issue is the issue of
exploration in order to evaluate a
policy new we need to generate core
samples using that policy there's no way
around that however then if you use a
single long trajectory then this long
trajectory using the policy will tend to
go through states that are preferred
from this policy you may have for
example a part of the big state space
that that that that this policy
naturally tends to and very infrequently
goes off to other parts of the space so
the steady state distribution the size
of this other state is almost zero if
the Markov chain is not even ergodic
then some size are going to be exactly
zero so when you do a least squares fit
or a projected equation fit with this
weight
the states that never are never or very
seldom visited by this policy are going
to be underrepresented and the error
that you will get for those states from
the projected equation is going to be
very large
however these states may be important
perhaps not important for the current
policy but important for other policies
and you would like to include them in
the approximation fairly and so there
may be a serious problem the improved
policy may be much different
this is huge errors because because
policies that new regards as unimportant
noubar may make regard as very important
so that's the problem of exploration we
discussed it and it's a very serious
particularly when the randomness
embodied in the transition probabilities
is relatively small if you have for
example a deterministic system then
there is no natural noise in the system
that makes you wander around and explore
the state expect the state the state
space in order to deal with a problem we
need to change the sampling mechanism
and at the same time modify the
simulation formulas in other words we
need to solve a different projected
equation that involves projection by bar
with respect to an exploration enhanced
normal in other words change the weights
instead of sigh the natural weights of
the policy use a different weight
distribution Zeta that weighs other
states more fairly so Zeta is more
balanced than sigh which is the natural
steady state distribution a Markov chain
of Nu so
what how can we generate this
exploration enhanced weights and how do
we solve this equation now okay that's
the issue and by the way one more thing
what happens if new is not ergodic then
some states will never be visited so if
we change the steady state distribution
of new likes I and use another
distribution that goes across her body
classes recurrent classes then that
addresses this problem as well okay now
I'm going to talk about briefly about to
exploration mechanisms one possibility
instead of using a single long
trajectory using the policy that starts
at some selected state and theoretically
visits all other states through the
ergodicity property of the chain instead
of using a single trajectory use
multiple trajectories shorter okay
like ten transitions long five
transitions long one transition long and
we pick the states the initial States of
these trajectories from a rich and a
representative sample so we cover the
states by covering the initial States in
this of these long trajectories and we
use that policy for each one of the
short trajectories okay there are names
associated with this I'm not going to
get into the details of that but your
textbook has a fairly detailed
discussion also gives references
geometric sampling relates to short
simulation trajectories generated
according to a geometric distribution
where by the end of the trajectory is
determined by Alan
the parameter there is a positive
probability lambda that that any one
transition will be the end and you have
to restart from another trajectory
freeform sampling is a very very
flexible and very very general sort of
sampling which has basically you don't
need to it's much it generalizes
geometric sampling and just about any
kind of sampling mechanism comes under
freeform sampling and still you can
solve a certain meaningful bellman
equation anyway with short trajectories
we can choose the starting stage and
will enhance exploration this way
however the simulation formulas to solve
this equation with PI bar not Pi the
simulation formulas become a little
different okay naturally otherwise yeah
it's natural that this would be so and I
don't want to get into the into the
details but the formulas are not
difficult they're just different and the
amount of computation involved in
solving this equation is about the same
as for the regular bellman equation that
does not involve exploration so that's
one way balance the weights of the
states by restarting and many different
points in space the second possibility
is to use a single long trajectory which
however is generated with a different
policy slightly different policy so that
state foil following the policy new at
every step we occasionally deviate we
deviate perhaps with some probability
using another policy that has broader
exploration properties so that will tend
to visit explore more fully the space
and this you find the name in the
literature this is the off policy method
basically here you have two policies one
is the target policy which is the new
that you are currently evaluating and
the other one is the exploration policy
or off policy that tends to take you of
course to visit other parts of the state
and here the modified policy is a
mixture of the target policy in the
exploration policy in this copy off
policy approach on policy for the target
off policy for non tank very old method
goes back to the early days what of the
field however it's important to note
that the simulation formulas for the
basic methods have to be modified so
that you solve this equation rather than
equation involving the modified policy
we still want to evaluate the original
policy now this involves ideas from the
theory of importance sampling so that
all the simulation formulas are what
important sampling modified this is
something that you will see only in
recent writings because in the early
days of the field the idea that the
formulas of LS D D and LSP methods had
to be modified this had not been fully
appreciated
okay now here's another issue suppose we
change from PI to PI bar that will
change the contraction properties of
this mapping here however if lambda is
is positive and close to one then the
contraction property of pipe in lambda
is restored and the methods that need
contraction cabott LS DD does not need
the contraction of this mapping it's a
matrix inversion method that that has a
solution give you a solution no matter
whether you have a contraction in this
mapping or not however the other methods
LSB lambda and T D lambda require that
this is a contraction in by getting
lambda sufficiently large you have this
property
okay so now we want to look at two
issues of policy improvement one is the
exploration issue and that's all I have
to say about that
and now we're going to get into issues
of policy duration that have to do with
the sequence of policies that we
generate we mentioned that approximants
the region does not terminate but rather
generates in the end a cycle of policies
perhaps many policies how can we
understand this phenomena okay so the
certain figure that's a little hard to
understand at first but after you
understand it you get a lot of insight
from it we consider the space of weights
okay so this is a small dimensional
space of the vectors are okay and we
form a partition of that space which we
call the greedy partition every policy
has a subset in this partition and
arsenew is the set of parameter vectors
for which new is greedy with respect to
the cost corresponding to our each are
gives you a certain J tilde cost and if
you minimize in balance equation you get
a policy new the set of all R for which
you get new is called R's of new okay so
in the gist of this is that our view is
the set of all are such as if we use an
R in it then the next improved policy is
going to be new okay so we have the
specialist and there is a partition each
policy has a set associated with it if I
pick my are within that set then my next
policy will be the one corresponding to
the set
okay now notice something else also
suppose that policy evaluation is exact
so for every policy that you evaluate
you obtain a certain weight vector R
something for every new design arts of
new so I can plot these sets arts of new
and I can plot also the point arts of
new in here now here's how approximate
policy iteration is going to work
suppose that I have the current policy
new K and I evaluate this policy
according to a projected equation
there's a unique fixed point there's a
unique are okay now now this arm use of
K is going to fall into sunset our new
and let's say and the set within it
false is going to correspond to the next
policy if I have argue here the next
policy is going to correspond to the set
within which it falls so mu K plus 1 is
going to be the next policy but new K
plus 1 is evaluated using some weight
vector and the next point in the policy
direction process is going to be this
one this vector falls within some set
and it's going to be the set
corresponding to the next policy and now
we are going to move here to the set R K
nu plus 1 is going to fall into a set
correspond to still another policy which
I'm going to go back and at some point
because these sets are finite there is a
finite number of them because there's
only a finite number of policies
eventually there is no alternative that
you will close a cycle and this is the
cycle generated by the approximate
policy duration with the exact policy
evaluation
okay so genetically assuming that you do
the policy evaluation exactly so for a
given new there's a unique weight vector
associated with it there is going to be
a cycle like this that's going to be
closed the algorithm ends up repeating
some cycle of policies with ruk
belonging to R capital R mu k plus 1 nu
K R mu k plus 1 belonging to the set of
Nu K plus 2 and so on
and somewhere a cycling is going to be
closed now you might ask is it necessary
that we have a cycle can this process
terminate sure if arts of knew falls
within the set arts of you then you have
convergence in one step okay it's only
when you have this movement around the
query a little R does not correspond to
to look to to capital R that you get an
oscillation
so in terms of this figure the typical
trajectory of approximate policy
duration is you start with some policy
you move into some new set corresponding
to the policy then you go to a new
weight vector a new set corresponding to
that weight back to that weight vector
involving a new policy and so on so you
meet between policies like that and then
you come to some point where you just go
on a cycle now you hope that this cycle
is a good cycle that all the policies
involved in this cycle are reasonably
good policies practice with many
problems
indeed indicates that that the cycles
occur in good parts of the specs rather
than bad parts of the space however
that's ambitious examples where you get
oscillations within very bad cycles
particularly when the problem is of
small dimension there are very simple
examples to move in two states three
states okay very unusual kind of but
very very very very revealing kinds of
examples
now suppose that are there questions
about this figure I know it's a hard
figure to understand I always have to
look at it again and again to figure it
out yes please yes the question is what
about the quality of this cycle is it
possible that all the policies in this
cycle are far from optimal definitely so
yes definitely so you can compare it to
if you can make an analogy that's
somewhat superficial but perhaps
somewhat revealing with local minima
local minima in in optimization where
the method gets attracted some local
minimum that could be very suboptimal
very far from optimal the same thing can
happen here it's a process of like local
minimum okay here's another yes please
the arrow of the function this
oscillation maybe
yes yes the question is is it necessary
that I get a bad oscillation definitely
you might get converges to an exact
policy in in very few directions and it
is also possible that this oscillation
can happen but all the policies here are
close to optimal actually this happens
quite often in general it will oscillate
and depending on how you do the policy
evaluation it makes typically oscillate
typically yes there is no convergence
guarantee of this algorithm there's only
a fourth that you will get a good cycle
there's also even worse it's also even
worse suppose you get a cycle and you
look at your computational results and
you see well there's got to be a cycle
because I get this policy that's good
but I get this other policy that's very
bad and I keep oscillating between good
and bad policies how do I know that what
looks to you as good policy is indeed
good okay how do I know that there's not
another policy that's much much better
it cannot be guaranteed in general
except for the generic error bound that
I gave you earlier which is so loose to
be in useless in practice convergence
cannot be guaranteed and and you can
gain some confidence about the results
by doing some additional computations
but still there will be some doubt they
may be some doubt as to whether the
results of the computation are good or
bad because you don't know where the
optimum is
okay there's some even more weird things
happening here if we have a certain
policy new kay let's say the typical
policy exactly I'm sorry solving the
projected bellman equation will give you
a unique weight vector however if you
use an optimistic method whereby you
solve this bellman equation only
approximately then you're going to get
something that has some error all you
can say is that from arm UK you can go
towards this point but not necessarily
add it so a different kind of figure
will work then whereby let's say which
we are at we have policy new one and
then we generate policy new to buy
policy improvement and from here we go
part of the way towards this but we
don't quite reach it because we use an
optimistic algorithm and then from here
we go towards here but we don't quite
reach it so what's happening is the
magnitude of the oscillation is is
becomes reduced it becomes less if you
make the we we evaluation progressively
more and more optimistic then you can
get smaller and smaller oscillation and
in fact you can get convergence
convergence of the weight vectors and
then the strange thing is that we can
have convergence of the R vectors as you
are having an oscillation of policies
it's just that you convert that this
joint this junction point in the greedy
partition between policies and you
generate a cycle of policies but we are
vectors seem to converge so you look at
the are vectors and you may be very
happy ok my algorithm is converging but
in fact it may not be converging it may
be oscillating and very widely so
between policies convergence in the
space of our but divergence or
oscillation in the space of MU
it's a very difficult phenomenon to
analyze but you can witness it with very
simple examples
you know like three state examples four
state examples and you can get two state
exams you can get convergence of our two
points that are meaningless okay they're
just Junction points in some strange
diagram that you can never compute you
can never understand okay so what why is
this happening and how can we fix it
mathematically speaking fundamentally
oscillations are due to the lack of
monotonicity of the projection operator
by monotonicity I mean that if I have
two functions J and J Prime when I
project them on the approximation
subspace their order may be may be
switched around now remember that we
have PI T T is monotone a very
fundamental property in dynamic
programming once you compose it with the
projection operator you lose the
monotonicity property and all the proofs
that I gave earlier for exact dynamic
programming which are based on model
ethnicity do not hold anymore
mathematically that's the problem lack
of one authenticity of this operator if
you were to change this operator and use
adapt a different operator say some W
operator that is monotone and also this
is a contraction then you would not have
these oscillations and you will have
converges to a single policy this is a
little difficult to explain but not
difficult but will take us too much time
to explain you may explore it on your
own this is the mathematical reason for
all these oscillations however there's
an important special change for which
the evaluation equation involves a
mapping W that is both monotone and the
contraction and this is the next method
aggregation in aggregation
we do have similarities but a mapping
that is monitored and avoids this
oscillations so let's leave this thought
at this point and then we'll come back
after a break to look at aggregation in
why this is happening and any questions
yes
okay the question is if we have
inadequate exploration how damaging can
this be and how much exploration do we
need to avoid the problems the answer is
that it's very difficult to give
anything to say anything quantitative
about this it's mostly a matter of trial
and error that's that that's the only
way I can answer any other questions yes
okay how do we know that we have
inadequate exploration well basically by
looking at the results if you see that
the policies are changed widely and you
get strange policies by your process
because basically you're using cost
functions that are way off and balanced
in favor of some states and relative to
others then that's sort of a an
indication that your exploration problem
is that you have an exploration prop
usually that's not hard to tell because
the algorithm just completely breaks
down if you have an adequate exploration
so if you see that you're getting
garbage that's that's the first place
that you look it's my exploration
sufficient
okay so let's take a break for ten
minutes and then we'll come back to look
into aggregation