for for exact dynamic programming this
is a subject relating to the
implementation of the various algorithms
such as value duration in policy
duration there's a lot of interest these
days on a synchronous algorithms not
only within the context of dynamic
programming but in the context of of
other optimization algorithms convex
optimization so on now what we mean by
in a synchronous algorithm to give you
an example in value iteration what we
have is safe iterate function cost
function and then we go at state one and
calculate a new function then at state
two and so on and we do it
simultaneously for all states so we
produce a vector JK plus 1 by updating
its components simultaneously given all
the components of JK an asynchronous
algorithm is one that picks some
component let's say component 5 and
that's a value iteration on that and
then at another iteration picks
component 10 at another iteration it
picks component 3 7 and 15 and does a
value iteration on that not only that
the values that we use to make the Z
directions may not be up-to-date because
they may be outdated because these
iterations may be done at different
processors and different computers and
these computers may be having
out-of-date information about the
computations of other computers the
computers may be out of sync
also in the context of so we have
distributed distributed computations
setting involving many computers that
exchange information but information is
out of date and they not be may not be
synchronized in their iterations we also
have a simulation context whereby the
components on which we do value duration
may depend on a simulation trajectory we
let the system run we encounter state v
we do a value direction on that then we
move and encounter state seven we do a
value direction on that so the the
sequence of components that we update is
determined randomly by a simulation
trajectory and that from that context is
very common in in approximate dynamic
programming well we often use simulation
very often the algorithms in approximate
dynamic programming are are synchronous
because okay we can't do them for all at
the same time we have do some coop some
states but not for others and that's the
way the setting is okay so the bottom
line is that value direction and policy
duration surprisingly work no matter how
chaotically you implement them turns out
that they are valid under the most
difficult of circumstances and this is
due primarily to the contraction
property that's involved in there and
also more fundamentally the monotonicity
property involved in dynamic programming
now so that's the bottom line so let's
go one step at a time
here's a general framework we have a
state space X and we partition it in
subsets x1 up to X M and we use a
separate processor L to update the
components that are in the elf set as a
special case these sets in the partition
may consist of a single state so you may
have one processor for each different
state unless partition functions of
course J cost functions J conformally so
J is the component J 1 is a component of
J that corresponds to X 1 and so on so
if X 1 consists of states 1 2 and 3 J 1
is J's of 1 J of 2 and J's of 3
and so on and Jael is the restriction of
Jay on the set on V on the subset of the
state space now the synchronous version
of value iteration has this form now T
here is time okay
and there's a reason why we use a
different notation here
the elf component at time T plus 1 is
updated by using all the components at
time L at time at time T and and and we
apply and we take the component of T at
attacks X belongs to X L so this is a
parallel version of the value iteration
algorithm except that all the components
are updated simultaneously so it's a
synchronous implementation and a
synchronous algorithm updates only some
of the components and also uses values
of components that were way back so here
in this a synchronous iteration I update
the component l only 40 only four times
in a special subset for other four other
components four components for if L does
not belong to this T does not belong to
the subsets I lived and changed so this
allows basically two so let's say
component one for l equals one component
one may be updated at time 1 5 15 and
500 okay and then 5000 whatever our l
would consist of 1 5 15 1000 but can't
remember the numbers ok you understand
the meaning so this is the set of times
where we have components updated and
there are different times for every
component
moreover the values that are being you
in this update they are not tea but
rather Assam Tao Tao being perhaps less
than T the difference between current
time and the time when this component
was evaluated is this and can be viewed
as a delay a communication delay between
processors so there's a huge difference
between this all the all the processors
have to wait for its other values to
become globally known and then the
components can be updated in lockstep
with each other
here everything goes chaotically
whatever components i have from other
processors i can use them to do my own
update if i want okay if i don't feel
like doing an update i don't have to do
it okay now a special case of this an
important special case is when you
update one component at a time update
want to state for state 5 now and then
get the results known to other
processors and update estate 7 then a
state 1 and so on so only one state at a
time rather than all states at once so
we assume that there are n states a
separate process for each state in no
delays and we generate a sequence of
states somehow perhaps by simulation
however every state is supposed to be
generated infinitely often and then a
synchronous value iteration does an
update only for one state the state that
happens to be happens to be generated by
this trajectory a special case where I
go through all the states cyclically
first update for 1 then 2 up to n and
then back to 1 and so on this is a
well-known method this is called the
Gauss Seidel version of value iteration
and it turns out it's faster than the
ordinary badly duration method okay
Gauss Seidel start with state 1 to a
value duration use the results to do a
value iteration for state to the
and so on that's different than doing a
value iteration for all states
simultaneously okay so this gives you an
idea that perhaps a synchronous
iteration not only works but also it may
work faster and indeed that can be shown
in some lab a convincing way and also in
practice okay now when you have an
algorithm that's so wild like this that
it worked why should it work it turns
out that it does work and there is a
theorem that dates back now to I don't
know maybe 30 years which gives you a
pretty good idea why what makes the such
algorithms work the bottom like as I
said is that value iteration and also
policy duration still work on
implemented synchronous by the way what
would be an a synchronous version of
policy duration in policy direction we
don't have just updates of course but we
have updates of policies as well so
example I processor one that controls
state one updates policy okay
just as policy then processor two
updates updates at state to its cost
then another processor updates either
policy or cost or groups of processors
updater policy circles totally a
synchronous updates of the policies the
local policies and the local cost and
again communication to other processors
with delays now you need a little bit of
a modification in the ordinary version
of policy direction for this to work
fully but basically it does work now
what I'm going to do is give you a
theorem that allows you to analyze that
it
nations that are a synchronous first of
you all you need a certain assumption
you need an assumption that every
processor updates infinitely often ok if
a processor stops updating then you can
ever hope for the algorithm to work the
second is that the communication delays
do not stay finite so as time progresses
to infinity then the tau times also go
to infinity even though there may be a
gap forever that we be the processors
keep using up more up more and more
up-to-date components so that's the
basic assumption and here's the theorem
suppose that you have a map in T think
of this as the value as the map in T of
dynamic program it's actually more
general than that supposedly has a
unique fixed point J star and suppose
that you can find a sequence of sets of
functions s of 0 s of 1 s 2 and so on
that are nested they are shrinking and
they have two properties the first
property is that if you have a sequence
of functions with JK being the
corresponding set SK then then then such
a sequence converges point-wise to j
star that basically says that you have a
sequence of sets that serve like so
luckily up no function and they're
shrinking in at the intersection is this
J star and you have the following
property that if you start with in the
set SK applying the T mapping to all
components simultaneously takes you
within the smaller set so this is a
condition that asserts that the the the
value iteration Albert the the fixed
point iteration using T
converges you start out from the big set
in one iteration you get one set inside
and so on all the way to the
intersection
now the key additional assumption that
you need which which guarantees are
synchronous convergence is that presets
are not just nested but they are boxes
they're partition brought boxes of
component sets and they are and they
have and in that's that's the the the
key thing if you have these two
assumptions then the conclusion is that
for every J function every starting
function that's within s0 the sequence
generated by the a synchronous algorithm
converges to J star okay perhaps this a
little bit too long but let me
illustrate by means of a figure there
are two assumptions here okay and the
second assumption the box condition says
that these sets are half box structure
like this so f0 is this outside box s1
is another box within it
s2 is another box within that and these
boxes are nested within each other and
have as intersection J star the box
s0 this assumes just two processors the
box
s0 constants or Cartesian product of s1
which is for the first component J 1 and
and s2 which is for the second component
J 2 J vectors consists of two components
here because this two-dimensional
picture and what we what our assumptions
say is that if you have a J that's
within SJ this box here then T sub J
brings you within SK plus 1 this is the
synchronous convergence condition and
the box condition is of course that the
sets SK have this structure
so these are the assumptions you have a
sequence of sets of this type that's all
that that you need and the convergence
mechanism is that you can do iterations
on any one component but you get
independent improvement of other
components so let me illustrate this by
starting at this vector J suppose that
processor one does an iteration then the
second component is not going to change
just the first component is going to
change and it's going to get within this
range okay because that's the
synchronous convergence condition now
processor one may do many iterations but
no matter how many it does it will still
stay within here at the first time that
processor do will do an iteration it
will bring you into the into into within
this interval here it will get into the
smaller set as k plus 1 so you have this
iterations going on but the first time
that the first time that you have any
direction from all processors you end up
in the better set and then in the better
set and so on I'm not sure I'm
explaining this very well I'm doing this
in a carry in perhaps you don't have
much background but it's not a difficult
proof to understand if you understand
these figures here now this is a general
convergence theorem for a synchronous
iterations and it applies dynamic
programming because the boxes that you
have in dynamic programming are spheres
associated with the maximum norm the
maximum norm within for which T is a
contraction has these spheres as as the
spheres are pub are nested and each one
of these spheres is scaled by the
discount factor alpha relative to the
proceedings fears so by taking these
boxes to be super non contract
since fears the theorem applies and it's
actually a very simple argument to see
that the argument for a synchronous
convergence of policy direction is a
little bit more complicated but still
based on similar ideas okay I'm going to
stop here and I can take your questions
this is sort of takes us to the other
edges of the theory and and we're not
going to revisit it but I want you to be
aware of the fact that when we talk
about our synchronous algorithms there's
something like this going on that makes
things work
questions yes the first condition the
assumption that when you start with a J
within one set then T so J will bring
you to the next set that guarantees
convergence in a synchronous fashion so
if you were to apply the directional
component simultaneously then from one
box you'd get to the second box the
third box and so on in this yeah the
boxes converge to ones to one point
that's the assumption in this in this
theorem however there is a more general
version of this theorem where the box is
converged to a set of solutions okay
that's right okay yeah your question has
to do with whether what happens if you
have not just a single fixed point but
you have multiple fixed points then you
have a whole set of solutions and the
assumption would be then that the
intersection of all these boxes is the
set of solutions but there is no
guarantee that there will be convergence
to a single fixed point it
maybe that you may be wandering around
the periphery of the set of solutions
and converge to the set rather than
converge to a single point yeah that's
true
any other questions
yes if we want to so approximate suggest
that we have to construct okay okay the
question is what happens if you have
approximations and instead of
considering exact value duration
consider approximate value duration or
even worse randomize kind of algorithm
involving samples in which case the T
mapping contains uncertainty contains
stochastic stochastic element okay the
best view of convergence has to be
modified in that case the classical
proof of V of convergence of Q learning
I'm sorry the classical view of
convergence of Q learning involves an
argument like that but more
sophisticated to take into account the
presence of uncertainty so to give you
an idea
the assumption the synchronous
convergence assumption that from J tfj
brings you to the next set has to be
relaxed and and with something like that
eventually with sufficient number of
samples you're going to get into a
smaller set however it may be that just
a single iteration will not bring you to
the set but with many iterations over
time you will get to the set the box ok
so is the Box random no the box is not
random but the algorithm involves random
elements so it may be wandering around
but you can prove in the case of Q
learning that with probability 1 it will
get into the next box and then with
probability 1 we'll get to the second
box and so on so there is a more complex
version of this argument that involves
an algorithm so cap stick iterative
algorithm that's what I'm saying the
boxes will go stay the same they're
going to be soup norm spheres around the
optimal solution ok this is actually the
paper of the proofs convergence of Q
learnings and actually very very
sophisticated and it's hard for me to
explain the values no one says but at
it's at the heart of the proof it's this
kind of picture that that is that
underlies that yes
in a bit so we're here now whether the
optimal valerie's it's a single value
[Music]
okay yeah that's a good question how do
we know that the intersection of this
box is a single point the set of
solutions a single point well in some
cases we know that it's a single point
for example if the mapping T is a
contraction mapping the soup normal
interaction mean has a unique fixed
point in this balls converge to the
unique fixed point if the mapping T is
just monotone it may happen that you
have multiple fixed points and then you
need to be to be more careful it's also
possible to have okay in the case of
monotone mappings you may be able to you
don't have a contraction but you may be
able to show by other means
[Music]
the number of the areas I think your
question has to do with the co-operative
question of whether the solution set is
connected or not in dynamic programming
the set of solutions of balance equation
is either a unique fixed point or else
it has some nice structure in other
words it is the set of it can be
characterized in alpena as the set of
all functions that lie above a certain
floor function something like this you
don't really seldom do you have where it
is i don't know of cases where you have
isolated solutions at in in space and i
think that i think however this is true
for exact dynamic programming for
approximate dynamic programming you can
have very wild set of attraction points
of different algorithms you may have
things like local minima that are very
complicated in which the structure of
which are not and is not understood that
present
convergence to the assumption I think
this RL the second one when vehicles to
infinity and this cow also goes to
infinity that means every state or every
region has to be to be updated
meaning not terminating the finite
number of iteration so I think
intentionally it's very difficult to
because some state may be trapped I mean
the value of may be trapped in some
subset of the state meaning if I have a
long evaluation in a finite number of
iterations and then okay I think I
understand your question let me rephrase
your question what you're saying is that
is that suppose that you use simulation
to pick the states at which you update
the algorithm how do we know that we're
going to visit all states if we can't do
if we're not sure that we can visit all
states then this algorithm will not work
you have to be able to guarantee that
all states over an infinite amount of
time will be visited infinitely often
this is this is frequently an assumption
in various approximate dynamic
programming algorithms so how do you
enforce that okay I'm not sure that
there's a foolproof recipe warrant yes
okay so what is the practical
significance of all this the practical
significance is that just about
everything in dynamic programming it
revolves around a value duration policy
duration even though my viewpoint here
is a little abstract in mathematical
that doesn't mean that the algorithms do
not apply to practical problems there's
a vast array of problems for which these
algorithms are used and in many of these
problems you have you want to use
parallel computation or you the
assimilation driven and I mentioned to
learning earlier which is definitely a
practical algorithm so so that's the
reason we want we want to look at
practical algorithms that have very wide
applicability but we want to do them
from a theoretical point of view in the
most economical way at least that's my
style I'd like to do them in a unified
way so I don't have to prove many
theorems about many different problems
I'd like to prove just a few theorems
that cover many problems ok but some
legitimate question you know why do we
have to go to this kind of abstraction
or what's the meaning of all this do I
have to go through all this this seems
very difficult very legitimate question
to ask any other questions
okay so next time in the next lecture we
are going to to go into approximations
and the next lecture is going to be an
orientation lecture it's an overview of
the field of approximations and then in
the second week next week we're going to
focus on specific aspects of the field
of approximate dynamic programming
algorithms and we're going to go in more
depth in those at that time okay
[Applause]