okay let's get started let me welcome
you to this last lecture last time the
six lectures when approximate dynamic
programming I have a feeling that my the
sound is not very good let me just make
an adjustment I'll put it over here and
see what happens
okay is that are you guys doing okay
okay
okay I think this a little better at
least it sounds my ears a little better
so this is the last lecture lecture six
out of in an approximate dynamic
programming and we have discussed quite
a few topics so far and mostly having to
do with policy duration cost function
approximations today we're going to look
at two factors and model free
implementations of approximate dynamic
programming algorithms so we are going
to review Q factors in the corresponding
bellman equations then talk about value
and policy duration for two factors and
then discuss Q learning it's an
important algorithm that can be viewed
as a sampled version of value iteration
you can do Q learning for two factors
but there is no corresponding algorithms
are great for costs that's an
interesting fact then we are going to
talk about Q learning in combination
with cost function approximation then
say a few things about adaptive dynamic
programming a few things about
approximation policy space and then we
are
to have a more general discussion to
close the course so let's do a little
review we continue to talk about a
finite state system involving states 1
up to n a finite set of controls for
each state I the system is defined by
transition probabilities that depend on
control and we consider policies which
are sequences of functions from state to
control nu 0 mu 1 and so on and given a
policy starting at a state I we can
consider the sequence of generated costs
over time discounted by a factor of by a
discount factor alpha and take the limit
of the series as n goes to infinity this
defines a number for every policy in
every state so J pi is a cost function
we want to find the minimal cost
function in a policy file that attains
the minimum we have seen the importance
of stationary policies policies where
all the mutates are the same equal to
some new and optimal optimal policies
can be find among the stationary
policies in those of the stationary
policies and in the various algorithms
such as policy duration and so on
let me remind you also of our standard
notation which we use occasionally to
denote the dynamic programming mapping
and the corresponding mapping
associative policies Maps jay Park
functions or n-dimensional vectors in
this case into other n-dimensional
vectors TJ or team use of J and now let
me remind you about two factors we
discussed those learning the second
lecture so first the second lecture the
given J star the optimal cost function
the optimal Q factor at the state I can
control you
is given by this expression it's the
expected one stage cost starting from I
using you plus the optimal cost to go
starting from J so it's cost associated
will start me state I but using you
first and then optimal after that okay
so this is a bigger function than J star
J star is defined for every step you
started to find for every state and
control okay now we have balanced
equation J star satisfying equal to this
expression here therefore if we minimize
on both sides of this expression we see
that Jake starts of I is the minimum of
the Q factors so if I have the optimal
few factors I can obtain the optimal
cost by minimizations over you moreover
if I substitute this expression here in
place of jstor I have an equation that
does not involve a star at all it's an
equation for Q factors this equation
holds for every I and you so it is a
number of nonlinear equations with equal
number of unknowns but a bigger equation
that Bellman's equation has more
variables in more equations okay now we
can use this equation also as a bellman
equation we can view Q star has been the
fixed point of a certain mapping okay
and the mapping is the one here on the
right-hand side so it is really a
bellman equation such this one here and
inherits the same properties as other
bellman equations in fact you can
consider I you as a state of a bigger
system and we move from I you to other J
u Prime
and the minimum over here denotes the
minimization over control so there is an
underlying dynamic programming problem
on a bigger space that involves the two
factors in involves of states the pairs
I nu and the bellman equation for that
problem is this one so everything we
have said about bellman equations for J
star or Ju applies to two factors as
well so there's a unique solution to
this equation this map here is a
contraction mapping a lot of cool stuff
that we discussed earlier apply and
there is also similar mapping describing
the Q factors of a policy and let me get
into those given a stationary policy we
can consider some larger system that
moves from IU to our use of J and then
continues according to this mechanism
and the two factors of a policy satisfy
this equation equivalently q mu is a
fixed point of this mapping this is a
linear equation now has all equations
that have to do with single policies are
a linear equation involving these
unknowns defined for every policy in
having an unknown for every I and you
and we can use this equation we can
solve this equation we can evaluate the
two factors of a policy and that's
useful in policy direction
I didn't understand yes it's a number of
states that's true yes yes yes this in
this is only one of the several possible
transitions from I you okay
it's a several address there are n
possibilities yes okay P IJ you are the
transition probabilities starting at I
going to J over you will be using those
for six lectures so so okay that's fine
okay so we have two fact optimal two
factors two factors of a policy and
generally you value direction in policy
direction can be carried out in terms of
two factors now if you do value duration
for two factors in all policy direction
for two factors you're not getting
anything different than for course
mathematically they're equivalent you
just operate on other things you're
you're operating on you're using a
transform versions of the same algorithm
so for exact so for exact policy
evaluation policy direction and value
iteration there is no difference between
using two factors or policies except for
a few things so let that leads us to a
question
why do we want to use cue factors what's
good and what's bad about them first of
all all the exact theory and algorithms
for costs applies to two factors balance
equations all the things that we were
discussing the last in the preceding
lectures contraction mappings
contraction properties optimality
conditions convergence and value of
valuing policy direction all of these
things apply all the approximate theory
that we discussed also applies projected
equation sampling exploration issues
oscillation aggregation and all of these
phenomena manifest themselves in Q
factor land just as well as in cost land
now here's one big thing about you
factors it allows if you can find them a
model free controller implementation
once we calculate these few factors for
all I and you we can calculate an
optimal policy not by minimizing on the
right hand side of the bellman equation
but rather by just looking at this list
of Q factors and selecting the one
that's numerically smaller
okay so implementation once you have
these Q stars is very simple and
moreover I do not need to know the
transition probabilities of the system
ordinarily you need to minimize the
expected value of the current stage cost
plus the expected optimal costs ago that
involves calculating an expectation and
involves knowing the transition
probabilities here you don't need to
know the transition probabilities you
don't need to know the model if you can
find these q stars okay that's the big
incentive for using q factors similarly
if you calculate a parametric
approximation of the q factors involved
in some approximation architecture with
a parameter vector r you can obtain a
suboptimal policy by minimizing
again these few factors without the need
for a model what are the bad things
about you factors
well greater dimension more storage and
some complications in calculating these
or that that's a rough cut about what
what we can expect from two factors in
particular if you want to calculate
exactly factors then the difficult is
increased for large-scale problems and
you have to think about aggregation or
other approximation procedures in order
to calculate you factors okay now here's
one thing about two factors that we
don't have for cause it's an algorithm
called Q learning in this is in addition
to everything else we discuss this is
new and Q learning is a sampled form of
value iteration it is a stochastic
iterative algorithm that generates
iterated values of these Q factors by
using samples from the system and it
resembles value generation but it's not
value duration it's a sampled form of
value iteration okay so here's the
description of Q learning in the
classical form there are many variations
but this is the standard view learning
algorithm remember we want to calculate
Q of all I and you so we select a
sequence of pairs of states and controls
we have a system sample we get one state
control pair here another one another
one we have a whole large number of them
and we can use any mechanism for doing
that probabilistic mechanism or
deterministic mechanism as long as all
the state control pairs are represented
and are sampled infinitely often was
this an idealized algorithm practice we
would not sound every state control pair
infinitely often but that's the
theoretical
version of the algorithm so a
degeneration cake we had some two
factors QK a whole big vector of two
factors and we update we said we have a
sample we have this ika okay and we
sample the next state according to this
transition probabilities so we have I K
UK and JK and we have we an and we
update the Q factor of that particular
pair according to this formula and we
live only all the other two factors
unchanged okay so here i am i select ika
UK and i pick the key factor of only
that pair and i sample the next state to
obtain JK and i calculate this
expression which is a sample of the
expected value that appears in balance
equation okay
sample because it's not some over p IJ s
but in rather just j k okay and we move
the Q factor of only that pair in the
direction of this sample but we also
interpolate with a current value gamma K
is a step size typically a small step
size in fact it is necessary but the
step size goes to 0 lightly at a rate of
1 over K proportional to a constant over
K so we calculate the sample which is
like value direction okay but it's only
a sample and then we make this update
leave all the others and change then I
pick out the next sample i ka plus 1 u k
plus 1 i do again a change for that you
factor and keep going like the
all the few factors are going to be
updated infinitely often but only one at
a time okay so that's the idea
value direction would move in that
direction fully with step size equal to
one Q learning moves in the direction of
a sample of this by a step size gamma K
so let's say let's before we go into
questions as to why this works and so on
let's just look at it and try to
understand it a little bit better here
is the algorithm I've just restated the
algorithm here the first thing is that
to implement the algorithm I don't need
to have a detailed model of the system I
don't need to have the pIJ probabilities
all I need is to have a simulator or
some mechanism so that given AI K and UK
I can generate the next state so all I
need is a box that samples next States
and also gives me values of one state
cause there is no need for a model the
other thing is that it operates at only
one state control pair at a time and
this is convenient if you want to
generate the state control pairs by
simulation so you have one to state
control pair that moves you to a next
state and then you use that next state
as as part of the next state control
pair and so on so even though the
mechanism for generating this this state
control persons arbitrary often times
you use us the simulator of the system
and in that context it's convenient that
you operate at only one state control
pair at a time because that's consistent
with simulation however with this type
of operation the algorithm becomes a
synchronous remember we talked about as
engrams algorithms backing in second
lecture where we operate somewhat
chaotically among the components of the
vector that we update so and one
possibility is to update components one
at a time well that's what we do here we
operate on two factors of only one
component at operate and only one
factor at a time now there are no
approximations in this out good we aim
to find the exactly optimal few factors
okay we don't cook multiple suboptimal
here we want to we aiming straight for
the optimal few factors and then the
question is why does this work why does
this algorithm converge to Hue star we
ought not few factors and also why can I
not use a sample version of value
iteration to calculate optimal costs
well the reason for this is actually
Mathematica it's just a fine point in
the mathematics generally speaking for
stochastic iterative algorithms to work
what you need to have is an expected
value an iteration that involves an
expected value that you can sample
however in melman's equation you have a
mapping that does not involve an
expected value only but rather the
minimum of an expected value if I were
to sample this expected value and
consider an algorithm that invoke
minimization over example this would
just not work the sample of minimum of
minimum works but many more sample the
mathematics don't work because when you
take expected values of a minimum of the
sample you don't get the same as the
minimum of the expected value so it's a
fine mathematical point but it makes a
big difference because I would like to
work with I would like to have a sampled
value iteration of involved in cost but
I can't do it because the minimum and
the expectation are in the wrong
relation okay we're not going to go back
to this point but instead let's consider
why do we get convergence
I think questions at this point
okay you can show convergence to the
true exact you factors and the fairly
mild assumptions and the line of proof
involves two types of arguments two
types of theories why is the theory of
stochastic approximation iterations and
the other is the theory of a synchronous
algorithms mathematically the key fact
is that the q-learning mapping that
map's
Q into FQ is a contraction with respect
to the soup norm okay
the maximum norm contraction is
important in order to be able to use the
Cask approximation soup norm is
important because because of the a
synchronous operation you may remember
on my discussion about a synchronous
algorithms a synchronous values are
valid provided there's some kind of
contraction light property with respect
to the soup norm if you remember this
box conditions and so on that's what in
effect here when you look into in depth
into the proof soup norm works well with
a synchronous contraction works well
with stochastic approximation okay
now let's understand the connection with
stochastic approximation let's step take
one step back from Q learning and look
at a generic fixed point problem
involving an expectation we want to find
a fixed point of this expected value of
f mapping where W is a random variable
okay so in our case of course this
involves a bellman equation so one but
let's in what in greater generality and
let's assume that this mapping is a
contraction mapping with respect to some
norm so that this equation has a unique
solution and also this iteration
converges to the unique fixed point okay
now how would you work this how do you
modify this outward
so that instead of iterating with full
expected values you just use samples
sampled approximations well we could
generate a sequence of damages and use
the sequence to approximate the expected
value appears in this direction so the
duration K to approximate this
expression here this expected value
let's use a Monte Carlo average using
the first J samples okay
that's certainly an algorithm that makes
sense and as K increases this Monte
Carlo approximation is going to be more
and more accurate so asymptotically
you're getting this algorithm in this
it's very simple to show that this kind
of algorithm works
it's like iterating with a contraction
fixed point iteration that converges but
there is a problem with this and the
problem is the following
here at every Direction K I have to go
back and calculate this expression for
all the previous samples so there's a
lot of computation involved here an
increasing amount of averaging as the
time progresses so we need to compute
all these values here for all the
previous WT so a more convenient
iteration is to replace this with the
expression that you have already
computed at the duration T that's a
major simplification because you don't
have to recompute all of these things
again from time 1 to K but rather you
can use the previous values that you had
so this is similar but requires much
less computation because it leaves only
one value of F per sample now it turns
out that this algorithm is kind of slow
because it involves average
and and then then the XS do not change
very much over time so X of T at
previous Direction is fairly close to
the current XK and this thing is close
enough to this so that this replacement
is valid but that's what the successive
approximation algorithm does it replaces
the naive Monte Carlo approximation with
a more convenient computationally
approximation now if you take this
expression and you can rewrite it in a
recursive form like this with gamma K
equals 1 over K so that you only need
one sample represented at each direction
and now you can see that this iteration
is sort of the same thing as the Q
learning direction it involves moving at
the edge in the direction of a sample
doing interpolation between the current
point a and B and the the other sample
so to learning is stochastic
approximation if it were done for all
two factors simultaneously it is to cast
approximation with just this F mapping
being this mapping here and using a
single sample in here instead of the
expected value so this provides the
connection between Q learning and
stochastic approximation to learning now
has a little bit more into it because
the durations are done 1q factor at that
time but then again this will involve
the theory of a synchronous computation
and that's also what will come into the
proof of convergence so this is not a
proof of convergence by any means this
step has to be justified and also there
are other things that we have omitted
but gives you an idea about the
mathematical connections with other
skill methodologies okay
let me mention a variation of Q learning
that's computationally more efficient
this is the Q learning direction right
we pick a pair i k UK and we calculate
this expression and we move in the
direction of that expression now this
expression involves minimization over
all controls and if you have a lot of
controls this may involve a substantial
amount of computation it would be more
efficient to remember the good controls
instead of minimizing over all the
controls minimize or over the good
controls or perhaps just one control
this leads into the idea of maintaining
a policy a sort of current policy which
you use in here instead of do using a
minimum and if you try to connect it
back to two policy direction and
optimistic policy direction you may
consider a sample version of an
optimistic policy Direction algorithm
which evaluates the current policy we
evaluate the Q factors of the current
policy by using a finite number of
values directions which would not be
important in minimization here and then
improves the policy occasionally after
new K steps by means of this iteration
so this is a more efficient version of
this but it turns out not to work
there's an all the work
dating back to 1993 which says that if
you implement Q learning are
synchronously with with maintaining both
a policy and few factors then you may
get oscillation
however it turns out that this can be
rectified by there's a simple
modification of this algorithm which is
does not involve much overhead that
overcomes this convergence problem and
this is recent research and I refer you
to a series of papers and I'll leave it
at that
okay so we have to learning for exactly
factors we have optimistic versions of Q
learning combinations with Polish
narration all of those for exact few
factors however we mentioned that for
large-scale problems the exact form of Q
learning is not is not it cannot be
applied because of the storage and
dimension problem so let's try to
consider basis function approximations
so we introduce a Q factor approximation
which is linear and involved this basis
functions visa is a feature vector
associated with I nu and R is a vector
of weights and we can try to train our
by for example approximate policy
direction pick a policy calculate the
corresponding our policy improve and so
on and you can use several language for
policy evaluation like l STD LSP and
others that we have discussed very often
in practice people use optimistic
versions of the policy duration method
whereby they have a policy they collect
a few samples maybe one maybe ten maybe
a hundred but not a very large number
and then do an approximate evaluation
based on the current weight the current
policy then do a policy improvement or a
step towards policy improvement collect
more samples and so on so policy
evaluation with a few samples policy
improvement by adjusting the weight
vector again more policy evaluation and
with samples and so on the most extreme
type of algorithm of this type uses just
a single sample a single sample in
between policy updates
okay so here this algorithm generates a
trajectory of state control pairs as
follows given the current weight vector
that represents an estimate of the okay
together with five gives you an
approximate cost function of a current
policy you simulate the transition using
this this the transition probabilities
of P of the system then generate a
control by minimizing the two factors at
the new point and using that control you
update the corresponding policy by
changing the the weight vector R and
this is this is done in the direction of
a TD lambda type of iteration correction
or lsbe direction some kind of iterative
algorithm that makes a correction after
a single sample so I have a state
control pair I use that to generate a
new new state then reevaluate the
control at that state by minimizing over
the Q factors then move again and so on
a very chaotic type of algorithm with
some connection to theory some
connection to validity but very unclear
properties very complex behavior and
clear validity oscillations all over the
place but people have used it a lot they
claim claim success with it you have to
judge for yourself what kind of success
this is or you know what it means there
is however solid basis for a version of
this algorithm for one for one type of
problem problems of optimal stopping
optimal stopping problems we have
very much optimal stopping problems
involved just two controls for each
stage either stop or continue okay
an example is when you're trying to
optimize optimize the time that you
exercise an option like a financial
option what you exercise the option you
sell the option or you keep it for one
more step you either stop or continue
okay
turns out that you learning is used very
widely in practice in financial
engineering financial programs that that
value options and and the optimal
stopping formulation is the one that
comes in there and there are and in this
particular algorithm is valid for this
for this for this problem
okay now let's talk about another type
of algorithm that involves Q factor
approximation
instead of using projected equations and
the algorithmic we have discussed this
another approach that we mentioned but
it did not discuss very much the so
called bellman equation error approach
okay so we'll describe this approach for
two factors given a policy new we
approximate the Q factors of that policy
using a linear approximation
architecture that is obtained by
minimizing the error in satisfying
Bellman's equation okay so this is Phi R
Phi R is the approximation to Q mu and F
nu is the mapping associated with with
the the policy mu involves expected
value and so on so this is a least
squares problem and the norm here is
Euclidean work with respect to some
distribution side this approach is
related to somewhere to projected
equation approach and and you can and it
works as follows given a policy you
solve this problem to find our new then
you improve the policy and that allows
you to solve this problem for the new
policy and so on now let's look at this
for deterministic problems okay
this approach has found more application
for deterministic problems rather than
for stochastic problems and there are
reasons for that let's look at the
special case of deterministic problem
now in the deterministic problem given a
state in the control pair the next state
is completely determined okay there are
no transition probabilities there is a
unique state which you go so here's how
this approach would be implemented
given a policy will generate a large set
of sample pairs high K and UK
corresponding deterministic covers and
corresponding transitions which are also
deterministic to the state determines
the state jk jk is the next state in
news of JK is determined from the polls
now you can use a simulator of the
deterministic system to generate such
sample pairs give an eye and you the
next you tell the simulator to generate
JK for you and you have a policy that
gives you the control at the next state
which you need for me you need to plug
in here so given all these samples you
put them together into a least squares
problem that emulates this so it's the
sum of the errors in satisfying balance
equation right
it's a deterministic Dalton equation so
this is the error corresponding this
error here but instead of taking over
all states you take it only over those
samples if this summation includes all
states these two would be a dime
equivalent so instead of sampling all
the states I sample some representative
states i form the error to satisfy
balanced equation
minimize that to obtain the weight
vector that corresponds to the policy
it's a linear least squares problem it
can be solved the solution of this can
be done in many different ways you need
to have enough samples in order for the
matrix involved here to be invertible to
have a unique solution but this can be
easily arranged
it's not not a problem okay
let me mention also that for stochastic
problems is a similar approach but it's
more complicated it involves taking two
samples per iteration it's it's more and
it's it's it's more complicated and and
there are reasons for that
refer you to the text however the
approach is model free and for the
termina stick problems it is very
attacked attractive for adaptive control
of systems with unknown dynamics for
example you may have a linear system
like a process or some kind of a robot
that does things but because of the
circumstances which operates you don't
know the dynamics of the system may be
linear but you don't know them the
coefficients the coefficients that
multiply the state coefficient that
multiplies the control and so on this
approach provides an avenue for dealing
with such problems without knowing the
dynamics you go directly towards finding
an optimal policy what more Q factors
lock no policy so that's the next topic
I want to talk about but we'll take a
break this relates to something called
adaptive dynamic programming which is
really adaptive control based on
approximate dynamic programming adaptive
dynamic programming a DP has the same
acronym as approximate dynamic
programming which is a DP also but
adaptive dynamic programming is really a
subset of approximate dynamic program so
we'll talk about that after we take a
break any questions
[Music]
okay but that's a good question
we have been talking so far about
discrete space systems finite state
systems however this approach also has
an analogue for continuous space systems
and in fact it is continuous space
systems that involve for which adaptive
control is most applicable basically you
do the same thing for continuous space
systems you just sample States okay we
have to distinguish between okay your
question is the following suppose I have
a continuous space problem to begin with
does there exist an exact Q learning
algorithm that operates on the
continuous space of states the answer is
no we don't I don't play the literature
has there's no non version of the
algorithm probably it's much more
complicated perhaps you can you can
figure out how it might be but there's
no analysis of such an algorithm now
that's one thing Q learning per
continuous space system in exact form
that we don't know how it how it
operates but it is possible to apply
your learning for a continuous space
system with cost function approximation
and the R vector then the vector of
weights the basis functions is only a
finite number and for that theory so
there has been a lot of work
okay so the question is how fast
what's the put what are the performance
guarantees for good for disabilities III
okay
the Q learning algorithm involves
several complicating factors one is the
resemblance to stochastic approximation
in the use of samples and the other is
one Q factor at a time if we were to do
all two factors simultaneously and
obtain basically a stochastic
approximation algorithm then there are
convergence rate results about
stochastic approximation algorithms
however the Q learning algorithm more
complicated because it involves a
chaotic kind of chaotic trajectories
over state control pairs and you update
only one at a time and I don't believe
that there are interesting convergence
rate results for this type of algorithm
if you want a qualitative answer the
algorithm is very slow very slow very
often and that's typical of stochastic
approximation algorithms so if you are
interested in high accuracy then that's
probably something that you cannot yet
but sometimes you get convergence
reasonably fast particularly if you've
got no good starting points if you have
if you have if you do the sampling in an
intelligent way if you've your first
experiences with Q learning are likely
to be frustrating frustratingly slow
form of it it if G were continued okay
so so what kind of G function here would
help perhaps yeah would be also if you
use cost function approximation if you
know the form of G you may be able to
exploit it in order to pick your basis
functions appropriately and that problem
is going to be helpful
any other questions
okay so let's take a break for ten
minutes come back