having done that
doing the short break here we go bring a
number to be that you may address for
the TA
they're teaching the area
as a possible
[Music]
this
yeah
[Music]
okay maybe we can get started
so I will pick up again on this dynamic
programming algorithm we define JK's of
xk it will be the optimal cost the tale
problems starting at xk and given the
solution to all the ten problems of
starting at k plus one we can generate
by the principle of optimality
essentially the optimal cost of the tail
problem starting at time k go one step
and then go optimally on the tail
problem at time k plus one and minimize
choose you to minimize the sum of the
two ok so this is an algorithm that a
computer can understand but it can be a
very very difficult algorithm to execute
and that's the problem here with dynamic
programming recognized in the very early
days let's see what are the difficulties
with this algorithm well first of all
the curse of dimensionality exponential
growth of the computation and storage
requirements as the number of state
variables and control variables
increases so for example if you have
motion of a vehicle in some three
dimensional space we said the six state
variables okay six state variables if
you discretize each axis with a hundred
points this is a hundred to the sixth
discretization points so at each one of
these ten to the six discretization
points you have to calculate this
expectation okay and then minimize
overall you that's a lot of
minimizations to do and this is only one
time step if you go back many many steps
the requirements increase proportionally
so there's this curse of dimensionality
which manifests itself on many many
computations to be done here and there
is also a problem of storage because if
you have you have to store the say a
hundred to the six numbers
to store this function JK plus 1 so
again and a hundred to the sixth for
problem is relatively small if we will
look later at some problems that are
much much bigger than that so that's the
curse of dimensionality it's a real
formidable object object or obstacle
okay the curse of modeling here in this
algorithm we need to have we transition
the probability distribution of wk and
that's easy that's not so easy to get
you need to have an equation here FK
that may also be difficult to have in a
give a practical situation so it would
be nice if we did not have to calculate
this entire thing in detail then
calculate the whole thing and this is
what you learning does somebody
mentioned Q learning earlier later we're
going to see that the Q learning
technique is a dynamic program entitled
up of techniques that is model free you
don't need to have a model of the system
or a model of the uncertainties to apply
it
here's another difficulty there may be
real-time solution constraints
oftentimes you need you have really a
family of problems and you don't know
which problem you're going to solve
until the very last minute so for
example suppose you want to dispatch
some trucks to make deliveries in
various parts of a certain area you
don't know you may have a good map of
the area but you don't know where the
deliveries are going to be until the
very last minute when the orders come in
so this has to do also with real-time
operation the problem being revealed at
you in real-time
however if you have real-time situations
required fast solution and the dynamic
programming algorithm is not fast you
can may take a very long time to produce
a solution is basically an offline
algorithm and many times you have online
situations
moreover the problem data may change as
the system is controlled for example in
the city in deliveries there may be some
new deliveries that are scheduled as
your trucks are moving ok so the problem
of the data of the problem may change on
you and then you need to do online
replanting and the dynamic programming
algorithm is not suitable for this sort
of thing all of these difficulties are
our motivation for considering
approximations to the algorithm and also
simulation to deal with this curse of
modeling so here's a major idea of
approximation it's not the only one but
it's an important one instead of using
the optimal cost to go function JK plus
one in the algorithm we replace it by an
approximation that is more easily
computable in other words we use a sub
optimal policy nu bar not new star nu
bar
which at time K attains the minimum of
this expression now how is this
expression different than the one we had
before
instead of having j k plus one we have J
tilde k plus one an approximation so the
thing that gives us trouble this JK plus
one we approximate it with something and
I haven't told you how and then use the
minimizing control as a substitute for
the object this is called approximation
in value space okay we approximate the
optimal values here by something and we
go from there
how can we compute an approximation to
the optimal cost to go well we may
replace the problem with a simpler
problem and use as J tilde K to be the
optimal cost of that simpler problem
that simpler problem may be obtained by
discarding some dynamics by simplifying
the trying to the probability
distributions of the problem make the
problem simpler to to to solve exactly
perhaps by dynamic programming be helped
by other means and stick it in here to
get the benefit of feedback
here's another example J tilde K is a
high dimensional object and you remember
that the state space may be very large
there may be many many states so this is
a function that is represented by a list
of many many values okay it may be
possible to represent this function
approximately with a parametric form a
function that depends on some parameters
a small number of parameters which are
tuned or trained by some heuristic or
systematic scheme and this is going to
be a major object for us to look into in
a major portion of new Rosner learning
the approximate dynamic programming
neural dynamic programming deals with
parametric approximations of the cost to
go function JK he is a third approach
which is simple but very effective often
called the roll-out approach in rollout
we use as J as an approximation J tilde
the cost of some other policy not the
optimal on some suboptimal policy some
heuristic policy which is calculated
which is such that you can calculate its
cost either analytically or by
simulation so you have a heuristic
instead of the optimal cost you use the
cost of agrestic in there
the rollout as I mentioned is a is a
very effective technique very simple but
we're not going to go into it much in
this course because we just don't have
time but let me spend one slide on it
because I think it's an important
algorithm okay so here's our all-out
algorithm I have some heuristic policy
which I call the base policy and I
calculate somehow the cost of that
policy associated with the next states
that I may land using control UK and I
minimize this expression so I calculate
this in some way and here's the
important property the roll out policy
the roll out the policy that you are
going to obtain from this minimization
is always no worse and usually much
better than the base policy so starting
from any heuristic if you can calculate
this cost you can stick it in here and
get a better heuristic often
significantly better offer pretty close
to optimal and this is suitable for
online operation because as you go on
then what you need in order to apply
controller time UK you need to calculate
this expression here and you can do it
by forward simulation often so you are
at IMAX that at time estate XK you
calculate you consider all possible use
and then from the state whether you land
you run the heuristic from there and get
a number that will give you a number for
every control and you pick the control
that minimizes
there is a potential difficulty
calculating the cost of a heuristic may
itself be computationally intensive and
one possibility is to use Monte Carlo
simulation
if the problem is stochastic however if
the problem is deterministic then this
calculating this quantity does not
require Monte Carlo simulation it can be
done by a single run of the
deterministic heuristic and this is a
this is this this is important in
discrete optimization problems where you
have combinatorial problems you're
breaking them up into decisions over
stages and you have a heuristic which
are at certain point you've calculated
the solution a partial solution to
calculate the remainder of the solution
you use this heuristic and calculating
the associated cost requires only a
single trajectory simulation there is
also a methodology that's very important
in control theory model predicted
control control system design in these
days is done to a large extent with this
model predictive control and control
turns out to be a special case of
rollout with a special heuristic in the
special context of this NPC I'm not
going to get into this like I can post
literature on the website but an
interesting connection because MPC has
been hugely successful in control theory
and it and then this connection
indicates of how things may go from here
and why rollout is also is could be a
very effective technique it's a success
stories were all out as well as the
control theory
okay so now I'm going to turn to
infinite horizon problems for final
equalizer problems we have one algorithm
we can consider approximations but
basically that's it there's not much
more Theory for finite horizon problems
the interesting theory comes foot to
infinite for infinite horizon problems
points an infinite horizon problem is
the same as the basic - operation
problem except that the number of stages
is infinite and the system and cost is
stationary there is no dependence on J
if I can turn you back to this model
here sorry for the flipping backwards
okay so this is our generic fine horizon
model if there is no dependence on K
here no dependence on K here and the
horizon is infinite we get an infinite
horizon problem
okay
now
we want to minimize in a major class of
problems we want to minimize the total
infinite horizon cost so we form the
finite horizon cost and we introduce a
discount factor alpha to the K alpha may
be either 1 or less than 1 if it's less
than 1 then it discounts it diminishes
future cause it makes this expression
bounded it keeps it real number so
plugging in a policy for any finite
horizon gives us a number and take this
number to go to 4 n to go to infinity
the sequence of numbers to go to
infinity and that gives you the infinite
horizon cost associated with a policy
and with an initial state and there are
several categories of problems here one
is discounted problems where alpha is
less than 1 and G is bounded okay
it's values right within a bounded range
and this makes this series convergent
okay G is bounded alpha goes down as a
geometric progression makes the series
convergent and therefore the optimal
could be the cost of any policy is
finite there are other ways to keep
across finite and not explode to
infinity even with alpha equals to 1 if
there is a termination state consider
the following problem you want to go to
some gold stay for something where you
want that you want to reach and go there
in a in with minimum cost now this is
really a finite horizon problem because
you will be at the termination state
within a finite number of steps but the
horizon is not fixed rather it is random
and the corresponding cost is finite if
the expected time by which we reach the
world is also finite
so that's a major class of problems so
Kasich's showed this path problems and
you make me familiar with a
deterministic version of this problem
the deterministic shortest path problem
within a graph go from a node of a graph
to another destination node in the graph
traversing arcs which some is whose
heart length is minimum so stochastic
extension it's an important model but
we're not going to discuss it very much
in this course because we just don't
have a time problems involving unbounded
cost per stage either the scandal or
undiscounted are more difficult than
these two and we are not going to cover
and actually there is only now emerging
theory of approximations for problems
like that it's also another major
infinite horizon model average cost
problems for problems where there is no
discounting in this term here the sum of
the finite horizon cost may explode to
infinity you may divide by 1 over n here
and make the average cost finite these
problems are a little bit more difficult
than v's but we are not going to cover
them again because we don't have time
they have a substantial theory
associated with them these are the four
major classes of infant horizon problems
there are some others but these are the
major ones ok
now why do we want to deal with infinite
horizon in reality we never have
infinite horizon life is finite you know
it's always a finite number of steps
there is some mathematical benefit in
dealing with infinite horizon problems
solutions are more elegant we can
restrict attention very often to
stationary policies policies that do not
change over time what you apply today is
the same rule that you'll apply tomorrow
and the day after tomorrow basically
because you are facing the same tale
problem the tale problem is from now to
infinity it doesn't become shorter at
any with any passing day as a result
policies turned out to be stationary so
you have to remember only one meal as
opposed to a sequence of memes also
there are some interesting new
algorithms that arise in this infinite
tourism context and very often the
solution turns out to be more elegant
and for the mathematicians among you
there's much more interesting
mathematics in this area than there is
for finite horizon problems also the
theory of approximations is typically
developed for infinite horizon problems
so that's an extra motivation for us to
focus on infinite horizon
okay so we have gone from final Horizon
to infinity horizon and now let's focus
on discounted problems with bounded cost
this is the most well behaved class of
infinite horizon problems we have a
stationary system notice no dependence
on K XK and XK plus 1 and XK plus 2 they
all live in the same space everything
stationary here wk also has the same
distribution for each K it's a
stationary system and the cost of a
policy which is a sequence of functions
is obtained like so it is the sum of the
discounted cost from 0 to infinity
so for each PI you plug it in here you
get a random variable you average it you
get a number and take the limit as n
goes to infinity you get you get a
number again if G is bounded for some
capital when you assume that G is
bounded for some capital M we assume
that the values of the G takes but its
absolute value is bounded by M then it
is easy to verify that this quantity
here is a real value function is bounded
in fact and and and that's the nice
thing about this model the boundedness
of G guarantees at all costs the course
of all the policies are bounded by this
expression in tract M is an upper bound
on G 1 over 1 minus a is the sum of a
geometric progression the space is that
X and you live are arbitrary only the
boundedness of G is important some of
you that may have mathematical interest
for continuous spaces there are some
that very fine mathematical points
having to do with measure theory but in
practice they are not so important and
we're not going to deal with them
an important special case is when all
the spaces are finite okay the finite
spaces case X takes only a finite number
of values so the system is a Markov
chain in a finite state Markov chain so
finite number of states and we move
randomly within the states of that chain
the control takes also a finite number
of values and usually such a problem is
called the Markovian decision problem or
MVP
some people use MVPs the name MVP for
arbitrary spaces but they tend to
qualify it as much as infinite spaces
and repeat when I talk about MVP I mean
finite spaces here if you want to solve
the problem algorithmically ultimately
you have to work with a finite spaces
approximation you have to discretize the
problem have discretized space space to
control space and so on so in the end
it's going to be a finite space SMD
field which is why this model is
important and people artificial
intelligence almost uniformly use finite
spaces and DP as the starting point for
their analysis and their algorithms
okay so this is the problem we are going
to consider first and the analysis of
this problem becomes very complicated
because of notation notation dynamic
programming is a bit of a curse
maybe you should add it to the curse of
dimensionality or the curse of modeling
the curse of notation long expressions
which clutter your clutter be your
vision and there is a shorthand notation
which facilitates very much the B both
the analysis in the insight that you get
into problems and it may be a little
challenge because it's abstract but it's
really very convenient if you want to do
a short course there's no other way to
do it than to resort to some kind of
shorthand notation so let's introduce
the shorthand notation okay for any
function of X remember we're looking at
cost function any function of X let's
consider the product of the dynamic
programming step starting with this
function J can you recognize here the
current stage cost and the cost to go
alpha is the discount factor and many
more plays so TJ is another function so
beauty as a box you put J N and T
produces is an operator that produces
another function TJ and its values are
given by this expression more concretely
TJ is the optimal cost function for a
one-stage problem with stage cost g +
terminal cost function alpha j
now for discounted problems she operates
on bounded functions to produce other
bounded functions okay and we can
introduce a similar mapping for any
stationary policy remember a stationary
policy is one that does not depend on
time you plug it in here in place of you
and you get another black box that
generates from given a function J it
generates another function team use of J
by means of this formula now the key
point is that the details of the problem
do not really matter what really matters
is the structure of the map in stee and
comune the dynamic programming mapping
all the interesting structure from a
theoretical point of view in an
algorithmic point of view all the
interesting structure of the problem is
captured by T and T mu and the entire
theory of discounted problems can be
developed in shorthand instead of
spending like 15 pages you can do it in
three slides or four slides maybe four
this is important to get used to this
idea of a black box operator that takes
J's and produces T news of J's or PC but
actually it's not so hard because this
is really the operator of the dynamic
programming algorithm that's about goes
backwards using this operator many times
so TNT new provide a powerful unifying
framework for dynamic programming and
this is the essence of this book but
listed in your list of reference to the
abstract dynamic programming book that I
wrote last year instead of focusing on
specific problems focusing on properties
of T and T new that give you the basic
theory now we are going to use this
abstract notation to develop the theory
of infinite horizon discounted problems
but let's see how you can use it for
final quarter
produce okay so let's consider an end
stage policy with terminal cost J and
discounted cost per stage okay so the
cost here of this policy starting at X 0
is the cost of the end stages discounted
plus a terminal cause that's also
discounted by alpha now you can write
this as okay take the first stage cost
so take it out of here and then take a
common factor alpha and then what you
have is that this can be written as the
cost of the first stage plus the cost of
the remaining stages so using our our
notation 14 you this this is this is
obtained by applying
tinu 0 to take by ones of 10 where PI 1
is the tail policy this is really
expression to the principle of
optimality the original problem can be
obtained by from the cost of the tail
problem of one stage less by applying
this in new 0 operator and if you take
this and apply successfully n times you
come up with an expression of the cost
of any policy that's very succinct very
compact you start with J the terminal
cost this is the first step of the
dynamic programming algorithm the second
step operates on whatever you get from
the first step in going forward all the
way to the initial State
if you have a stationary policy as
opposed to a time-varying policy then
this expression simplifies further it
can be written in this very compact form
starting with J apply n times the
composition of n times of this operation
and get the cost of the stationary
policy over n stages so this is T nu T
nu square Tim youth to the cubed power
to the end by the n fold convolution of
T new the composition continue and
similarly the optimal end stage cost
function is T to the end t is the
minimization operation and you have this
formula which is just the dynamic
programming algorithm Anik program now
it can be written in this short
expression n minus 1 tail problem
optimal cost is used to obtain the end
stages tail problem course by applying
dynamic programming mapping
okay just to take you back
tea involves the minimization team you
involves just a poly senior
okay so this map is give you a succinct
expression a succinct form of the finite
correlation theory and now we are going
to use it to express the entire theory
of infinite horizon discounted problems
in one slide we're talking about the
infinite horizon problem for any policy
PI the the cost of that policy starting
from state X is obtained by taking the
limit of the finite horizon cost which
is given by this expression and for a
stationary policy you have even
something it's even simpler and j0 now
is zero okay the terminal cost is zero
for the event horizon problem we don't
have
now the optimal cost function satisfies
a fundamental equation for infinite
correlation problems in this fundamental
equation is precisely this J star is the
optimal cost and it is a fixed point of
this mapping T okay in other words if
you plug in J star within T you get back
J star moreover for every policy mu
again you have balanced equation J nu is
the solution of this equation
in fact turns out to be the unique
solution of this equation
another result has to do with the
optimality condition a policy a
stationary policy is optimal if and only
if it attains the minimum on this
bellman equation the seer may have a
better slide
okay okay
there's an algorithm called value
iteration value iteration is simply the
dynamic programming algorithm applied an
infinite number of times
starting with heavy J compute apply
dynamic programming once twice many
times and take HK to go to infinity and
then you get the optimal cross function
another way to say this is that the
limit of the optimal finite horizon cost
is the optimal infinite horizon cost and
the other major algorithm is the so
called policy duration algorithm given a
stationary policy new K find the cost of
that policy by solving this equation
then you do a policy improvement five
new J plus 1 such that new k plus 1
attains the minimum in the minimization
operation involved here and so from UK
you get new K plus 1 mu K plus 2 and so
on and it's a basic algorithm that has
the property that it converges to the
optimal policy these are the two major
algorithms these are the two major
results I haven't proved any of those so
far but I'm I want to tell you that with
shorthand notation you have it all in
one page
okay so maybe we can take a little break
now and then I'm going to go into into
how we address these results and what we
get what we get from the theory are they
questions
is there any patient
for the polish duration algorithm under
what conditions it is valid is like a
question
the initial policy can be arbitrary any
policy will be sufficient
within this discounted problem context
any policy yes and you get convergence
in a finite number of steps here of
course we remember discounted problems
finite spaces discard the problems
that's what I'm talking about for finite
space is discounted problems it's a
finite number of states fine number of
controls to find a number of policies
stationary policies so you terminate in
a finite number of steps
yes okay what happens well those are all
outfit into this it turns out that the
rollout is simply one iteration of this
algorithm you start with a base for this
some heuristic and through this policy
evaluation and improvement you get a
rollout policy okay so your question has
to do with error bounds unfortunately
there is very little in the way of error
bounds all you really have is that the
base policy the rollout policy is better
okay is upper bounded by the cost of the
of the base policy and it's very
difficult except in some special cases
people have been this recent research in
specific types of problems like knapsack
type problems or other problems of you
know specialized problems where people
have been able to obtain bounds for the
performance of rolla but in general
there is no result it's the claim to
success is based entirely on
experimental evidence here
one predicted control well okay I
mentioned earlier the the result that
the rollout policy is better than the
base policy in model predictive control
this results translates the following if
you start with a stable policy you're
going to get by NPC you're going to get
hey also another stable policy and
that's that's not very much but but but
still is important because it provides a
guarantee of stability of the what you
get Randy's this of course under some
assumptions people have been using MPC
in other contexts but there are no
guarantees at all
yeah if you do multiple rollout and
you'll be doing this policy direction
but all out is just one step of this but
it's not so easy to do this by
simulation at least in the traction that
people use rollout no two states are
allowed is computationally very
intensive yes yes if you could do it but
unfortunately this policy evaluation has
to be done efficiently for this
algorithm to to be viable and in rollout
the policy evaluation is very
time-consuming because you do it by
simulation Monte Carlo simulation so you
have to - to roll Monte Carlo simulation
within Monte Carlo simulation and pretty
soon it becomes not viable but if you
were to do it theoretically would lead
to the object
I wouldn't say that value iteration does
not use policies okay it applies a
minimization operation does not use any
policy evaluation nor does it compute
intermediate policies yes okay let me
take you back to to this slide and roll
out okay
in rollout we have some base policy some
heuristic and we simulate it in order to
calculate this expression here so each
time we need to calculate this
expression for a given value of FK and
so on for given value of next state from
that state we simulate the the the base
policy many many times and then we take
the expected value of that that's that
it's very simple just you have a random
number generator calculate a lot of
Monte Carlo trajectories starting from
this and you get a number that's the
number that you plug in to this
algorithm but you have to do it for
every possible value of U okay for every
possible here for every possible value
of U and so that's a lot of computation
ok let's take a break because we're
running a little late and I'm going to
get into I want you to take if you could
use the break to eyeball these two
expressions here and because they are
going to figure importantly in the in
the next few slides
seven minutes please okay
[Music]