[Music]
okay is a new room and a new direction
somewhat different direction in our
class in the first week the first three
lectures were primarily directed towards
background and overview background on
exact dynamic programming with an
emphasis on discounted infinite horizon
problems and in the third lecture an
overview of approximate dynamic
programming which is our subject in this
week these three lectures today
Wednesday and Friday I'm going to focus
selectively on various topics of
approximate dynamic programming we are
going to go into a little bit more
detail but we will by no means exhaust
the subject we will be very selective
we'll pick some of the important topics
and go a little bit in depth into them
to give you an idea of how the field
looks like it will also give you a start
if you are interested to go more deeply
you can get started and expand your
understanding and background on the
subject so what we'll spend some time
and review a few slides and then the
focus of today's lectures are
approximate value iteration and policy
direction for discounted problems we
mentioned earlier that exact value
duration and the exact policy duration
are the two main algorithms for infinite
variety of discount dynamic programming
now we are going to introduce
approximations into value and policy
duration using the idea of approximation
in value space the approximation value
space means that I have a
action and I approximate this over a
lower dimensional space we talked about
how you can do this by simulation that's
the idea we're going to be using here
for different functions like the cost
function or cost function of the problem
or the cost function associated with a
policy and so on so I think I mentioned
the projected bellman equation we're
going to focus into that and see how we
can solve it approximately by using a
matrix form of the equation how do you
deal with the large inner products in
matrix vector products that are involved
in this projected equation by using
simulation Vietnam where you talk about
a couple of specific methods that are
central methods in the field the LSPD
and the LSP method these are simulation
based methods for solving the projected
equation optimistic version of policy
duration then some more advanced topics
on multi-step projected equations and
things related to that so a few slides
we'll review and you may interrupt me if
there's some question that's burning
question but that you'd like to bring up
it's a smaller group now so we can do
that we have a finite state system a
Markov chain with states 1 up to n and
the finite control set use of I at state
I the chain is described by transition
probabilities whereby if you are at
state I in you apply control u you go to
state J with probability pIJ of U so
it's a Markov chain if you fix the
policy if you fix these controls
it's a Markov chain but it's a control
Markov chain in the sense that we want
to find the good values of U and the
policy that produce good effects in
terms of a cost function so give
a policy a sequence of functions at
every time step PI we can plug it into
the cost function which involves a
course at every stage K discounted by a
factor alpha to the K with alpha between
0 & 1 take the expected value of that
the limit as n goes to infinity an
infinite number of stages and that gives
you a number which is the cost of policy
pi starting at state I so for every I
for every state there is a cost and is a
vector of course and dimensional vector
of course as associate with a policy and
we recall that we used a lot the
shorthand notation which is TJ for a
given vector J TJ is another vector and
dimensional vector with components from
1 to N given by this expression this
part is the expected cost of the first
stage this part is the expected cost of
what you will get at the end of the
first stage measured by J ok so you can
view this cost of the first stage cost
at the end of one stage ok and the
minute this is TJ and T nu J and we have
seen that is 2 nu J and TJ are central
in expressing the theoretical results in
particular the optimal cost vector is
the unique solution of this bellman
equation or equivalently the functional
equation is nonlinear n equations with n
unknowns and for a fixed policy is a
corresponding bellman equation again n
equations with n unknowns but it's
linear okay it is linear and therefore
it can be solved by by standard methods
the optimality condition is but if I can
find jelly star then by minimizing in
this equation by minimizing in the right
hand side the bad equation I can get an
optimal policy in reverse every optimal
policy has to satisfy has to minimize in
the right-hand side and the two basic
Alcazar value duration whereby I start
from some J vector arbitrary J vector
and iterate with it with T do a dynamic
programming step on it then another one
and another one sequentially and in the
limit I'm guaranteed to get J star the
optimal cost vector that's why the
direction in policy Direction iterates
with policies at the typical step the
case step I have a policy which is a
control to apply at every step I
evaluate the policy by solving the
corresponding bellman equation were in
shorthand like this after I evaluate it
I plug it in here and I get a new policy
by minimization and in shortcut is this
now the policy evaluation is equivalent
to solving a linear system of equations
and by n equations but we are interested
in huge dimensions and extremely large
so you would never think of solving this
equation by Gaussian elimination or
giving into MATLAB or whatever you have
to use a different kind of approach and
one possibility is to try a finite
number of offer well one possibility is
to use approximations and we will see
how approximations come into the picture
for evaluating for solving approximately
this equation okay
so now I may approach these optimist
approximation in value specs there are
these objects of interest Jade star
ingenue and we want to find something
that's lower dimensional is described by
fewer numbers and in particular were
interested in a function J tilde that's
a function of state but also depends on
some parameter vector R and R is a
vector with M components actually s
components should be yes okay a type but
a small number of components which you
can tune you can adjust to achieve a
better approximation so think of M be
huge but s the number of parameters
being small and there are many types of
different approximation architectures
that I can use polynomial approximations
interpolations domain-specific like the
tetris problem i discussed last time
depending on the problem you would
choose a parametric for a general
functional form of dependence of J tilde
on iron r and the objective is to get a
good R okay in what sense
well any are defines some function here
and if this is a good approximation to
jstor then I hope that my minimizing in
this approximate form of the right hand
side of balance equation I will get a
good good suboptimal policy new tilde so
the whole game is to find a good are
good in the sense that it gives me a
good muted now we are going to focus in
this in this lecture exclusively on
linear architectures where the
of jail killed on our is linear okay so
this is a linear for a given J this is a
linear function and more generally the
vector of these is a matrix a gigantic
row matrix or a dimensional matrix and
small column dimension multiplying R
which is a small dimensional vector so
this is a huge vector but R is a small
vector and v is a matrix of basis
functions in particular let's recall
what a linear approximation architecture
is for every state I there is a vector
Phi sub I ok small number of terms which
we view as the features of the state I
and this is these features are weighted
with a vector R and this gives you the
approximation form Phi I prime is the I
throw of fee sophie has Phi 1 prime Phi
2 prime Phi 3 and so on and n of those
and alternatively you can write this
entire vector as a linear combination of
the columns of fee okay
weighted by the corresponding
coefficients of R so if I give you R how
do you get an approximate evaluation of
whatever you are approximating this J
tilde for a given state whenever a state
comes to you you extract its features
numbers that describe in some broth
where a rough but effective way the
state so you get this vector Phi sub I
this is a small vector okay and you
weigh this with the small vector R and
you get a prop cost approximator
so if you have this linear map
this our then and you have congest good
features you're in business okay now
another view of approximation is based
on this equation what this says is that
we are looking for approximations of
whatever in the subspace Phi R where R
lives in RS is a vector in R s and this
is the the subspace spanned by the
columns of field so J whatever you are
approximating lives in a gigantic space
okay but there's a smaller space defined
by these features and what we want to do
is approximate it down into the smaller
space so that's the idea instead of
computing janie or j star which is huge
dimensional we compute the lower
dimensional our vector by using lower
dimensional calculations okay low
dimensional calculations is not so easy
to do okay you're going to collect
information about huge dimensional stuff
in low dimensional calculations that's
where simulation becomes important
that's what simulation will do for us
will allow us to obtain low dimensional
approximation with low dimensional
calculations
okay so now we will consider the two
basic methods value direction and policy
direction and make a first attempt at
introducing approximations into them now
this okay this approximate value
direction sometimes is called also
fitted dragged with direction you'll
find this term in the literature and
what it does is very simple value
iteration calculates J 0 T sub J 0 T
squared or chain 0 and so on so at every
step of this algorithm we introduce an
approximation which involves some kind
of a projection to a lower dimensional
space and keep going
so the initial function J 0 is given may
be some value R 0 and here's the
algorithm we started J 0 I have the
vector T sub J 0 and I find some kind of
approximation
onto the lower dimensional subspace of
that so J tilde sub 1 is an
approximation of TJ 0 now I apply T to
it again then I approximate it down the
lower dimensional space again and so on
can i generate a sequence of lower
dimensional vectors R 0 here R 1 R 2 and
so on okay if I were to do value
iteration
I've start at this J 0 I would go to TJ
0 T squared J 0 T cube J 0 and so on
here i generate T sub J 0 approximate
that then another T approximate that
another T approximate that okay that's
called fitted value directions are very
very natural algorithm I have an
iterative algorithm i approximate every
step of the algorithm in a lower space
then after I do a large enough number of
iterations let's say capital n the final
J tilde is going to be an approximation
to whatever approximating J star here in
particular this can be used with both T
equal to the minimization mapping or for
a specific policy can be used and how do
I find this J tilde approximation from
this well one possibility is to use some
kind of approximate projection done with
respect to some projection norm
typically our Euclidean norm although in
principle doesn't have to so
approximately what I'm doing is from J
tilde K I apply T and then I project it
down and that gives me at least
approximately J tilde K plus 1
it's an old algorithm very old idea
perhaps it goes back to the to the 60s
or even 50s people have thought of doing
this it's very natural however you'll
see that it's not as simple as it
appears okay so since we are into the
subject of projections
let's look let me remind you what we
mean by projection in the particular the
projections for today are not going to
be with respect to a Euclidian norm
however with some weights sigh okay so
if X is equal to 1 this is the standard
norm square root of the sum of the
squares
however we introduce excite vector here
with positive components in fact there
is no difference there's not without
loss of generality I assume that's a
probability distribution the sky vector
is a probability distribution with
positive components and I'm going to
consider our weighted norm and I can
tell you ahead of time that's important
to consider why it's here ok now let's
consider projection onto this subspace
with respect to this weighted norm in
other words we want to find and our
vector of parameters such that Phi sub R
star is equal to the projection how do
we do that well I want to find within
this subspace an approximation in this
sense of the weighted norm of J so given
J our star is solved by solving this
what this this quadratic problem shall
be squared problem however the problem
the difficult is the following J in our
context it's a huge dimensional vector
so I can't possibly compute it and then
try to approximate it ok so instead I
mentioned in the previous lecture that
we may use sin
relation how the simulation go I compute
some values for some states of this may
be my states are let's say 1 million and
I compute J sub I for 10,000 states ok
which I generate somehow by sampling at
sample the state space I calculate this
and then I can make a least squares fit
that is not as computationally intensive
ok so that's how simulation goes and in
particular I can there's a formula that
I gave last time that the implementation
by simulation of this projection with
respect to this norm is done as follows
we sample J sub I for a set of states I
1 I 2 and so on and then i saw i
restricted least squares problem ok this
is the same as ok you can do it in two
ways approximate an expected value or
solve a corresponding problem however
notice the following that the samples
have to be collected according to the
distribution sigh okay because if you
sample according to a certain
distribution the corresponding terms
involving I will appear with different
frequencies the frequencies
corresponding to sigh that's why the
solution to this approximates the least
square solution with respect to the sign
norm
ok so what do I gain here first of all
no gigantic calculations I just need to
be able to generate samples perhaps
approximate ok samples of some point and
second the other thing that I gain is
that is that I am able to control the
norm by sampling according to the
corresponding distribution
that's an important idea for our context
low dimensional calculations can control
the projection approximation through
sampling any questions yes how can we
guarantee the accuracy well in practice
it's more of a trial and error process
you can get of course some kind of
confidence intervals here but they're
not very useful in practice
I don't think okay perhaps they are
useful but I don't think that's the main
issue how do you get the accuracy you
just try to get as many samples as you
can and then your accuracy improves as
much as possible okay as many samples as
you can give them the computing time
that we can afford
you mean the the the Phi matrix okay
this is very much problem dependent and
also it is a separate decision okay you
there are two issues first select the
approximation subspace then you then you
try to solve try to find an
approximation with the subspace the two
are different of course if you are not
satisfied with the results that you have
you may go back in may add some more
features secret kind of features there
may be a process of iteration between
approximation and RT and in modifying
the approximation architecture
- we fix the distribution to decide
okay you okay so if you know the
distribution you can incorporate it into
the sampling now how you choose the sky
is a major topic for today's lecture
okay so I'm going to get to that okay so
remember we are talking about this
fitted value direction successive
approximation and now let's try to use
projection here here's a naive
implementation of fitted value direction
I have a large number of state a large
state space let's select a small subset
of representative states okay okay I
call this subset and for every state in
this subset calculate this expression
here okay so instead of calculating for
all states you calculate only for the
small subset now how do you calculate
this okay so this is an expected value
here this is given okay this is given
this is an expected value so likely
you'll do this by simulation okay and
you'll do it for every u and then you
have to minimize over on you so we're
talking about a substantial calculation
here for every I but at least you don't
do it for all the states are you doing
only for a subset so these are the
samples that we compute and now we fit
the samples to the new iterate okay so I
have a small set of values here and I
use a form of approximate projection to
fit a new function J tilde k plus 1 and
if you use simulations here then you
don't need a model by the way okay you
don't need these transition
probabilities if you can simulate them
by some
the computer and there is some error
bound that theoretical Arab and that you
can compute for this process and this
error bound says that if okay let me go
back to this figure here if this
difference is within Delta okay if these
differences are within Delta so
presumably you have chosen intelligently
enough the subspace so that the iterates
do not differ are not too far away from
this subspace if this differences are
within Delta then in the limit of this
process of successive fitting you get a
function which is within this quantity
of the optimum for all okay for all I so
this looks somewhat nice okay that is
some guarantee even though this this
alpha here which appears squared 1 minus
off in the denominator which is a little
discouraging nonetheless it's not as if
okay some result however there is a
potential problem with this and I'll
show you what the problem is in the next
slide
because it may be that you cannot
guarantee that this holds uniformly
there's a delta that holds uniformly for
all K okay here's an example a very
simple example what is this algorithm
fails completely suppose that you have
just two states okay Stage one and two
okay two states and there's only one
policy so let's forget about
minimization there's only one policy we
just try to approximate the cost
function of that policy now let's assume
that this Markov chain from State word
goes directly to state to that
and if it is that state to just state
that state to you can't get any simpler
than this okay two states
deterministically from wanted to or stay
within two and with no cost
okay so trivially the cost function as
the cost vector associated with its
Markov chain is zero and zero there's no
cost okay
your humilate zero at every step no
matter what you do well there's only one
thing to do but your accumulator
so my desire object is the zero vector
and i want to approximate it within some
subspace and i will choose the sub space
that is spanned by this vector here so
let's consider the value iteration
scheme that approximates that
approximates the tracks approximation
start with in this subspace so this
subspace is described by a single
parameter R and the subspace are all the
vectors that are multiples of one and
two okay so Jake star is 0 it is a
subspace here spanned by a single line
now 0 belongs to the subspace so you
have here even the luxury that JH star
the object that you're looking for
belongs can be approximated exactly okay
with zero error so it's a favorable case
now let's see how this fitted value
duration scheme is going to work what do
we do well we have a vector in the
approximation subspace a vector of this
line defined by RK and we find a new
vector on this line according to this
projection which I be the weight of the
projection though the norm so that's
that's that's the fitted value direction
I have a line I have some point in the
line
and I go to another point in the line
another point in the line and ideally
you'd like to go to zero so how do you
do that well you approximate this vector
R to R you try to find a least squares
fit to these values here now this values
are RK + 2 RK so it's a very simple
calculation here it's a linear least
squares problem with a single parameter
I'm not going to go to the mechanics of
solving this problem I'll just give you
the solution the solution is that RK
plus 1 is alpha times beta R K so RK is
a point on the line RK plus 1 is another
point on a line a multiple of R K by
alpha beta alpha is the discount factor
less than 1 and beta depends on the size
okay this comes from this calculation
this minimization so I have this weight
vector and notice if you look at this
weight vector notice that's always
greater than 1 so alpha is some number
less than 1 is multiplied by a number
greater than 1 and the product could be
greater or less than 1 if it's less than
1 then I have converters but if this
beta is larger than 1 over alpha then we
get divergence okay so for example okay
so if alpha is greater than 1 over beta
for example if this if you choose just
the uniform norm okay so is equal to 1
or maybe 1/2 to make it a problem
distribution then you can see that this
number here this number here becomes
greater than 1 and you get divergence
the method just diverges so the error
bar that I gave you in the previous
slide and does not hold because you
don't have given for
approximation here's the zero reckon you
just keep going off and there is no
there's no this table is in the method
fails now it's a kind of a devastating
example and stop provoking because it
says that you just can't arbitrarily
simulate project approximate and things
will work out very easily you can get
things not to work you have to be very
careful about what you do notice that if
you choose the size properly in
particular if you choose side too much
larger than 1 then this becomes less
than 1 and you get convergence so the
trick is to choose properly the
distribution here of sampling and more
fundamentally the difficulty is that yes
the T mapping is a contraction as we
have seen in iterating with T
convergence
however what we do here is we apply PI T
and it's not necessarily true that the
projection composed with T is a
contraction
who this happening here is what's called
the norm mismatch problem and let me
look at the picture again remember that
this fitted value duration start with
some j 0 applies t 2 it projects down
with respect to this projection norm
again projects down and so on so you
generate a sequence of vectors J tilde 1
J tilde to J tilde 3 and so on by
iterating with the mapping PI T and the
problem is that Phi T may not be a
projection may not be a contraction even
though T is a contraction if you didn't
have intermediate with a projection
there would be no problem but because of
the intermediate projection you can get
divergence because there is a norm
mismatch C is a contraction sum up sum
norm but Phi it's not the contraction
projections are not contractions but
they are non expensive non expensive non
expensive means that if they iterate on
two vectors and you project those two
vectors then the distance between the
projection is no larger than the
distance between the originals okay I
have two vectors projecting down the
projections are closer together than the
original okay so
if T is a contraction with respect to
the way that norm this weighted norm
then there is no problem
P contracts vectors and projection does
not pull them apart so you still get a
contraction and you get convergence
however if you have T being a
contraction with respect to one norm and
the projection B with respect to another
norm you may get a normed mismatch and
create a divergence in the iteration so
what does this say it says that we need
a special side ax I that works together
with T in order to get a method that
works just choosing an X I arbitrarily
if the sampling distribution is
arbitrary then you can get a real
problem so that's the norm mismatch
problem finding a distribution X I such
that projection with respect to that
distribution composed with T is a
contraction in particular find a magic
way that normal
under which T is a contraction and use
that for sampling now it's a very
central issue in approximation with the
codex often and programming and
simulation and we'll come back to this
issue because it also appears in
approximate policy direction here we saw
it we Michalek top approximated election
it also appears in the context of
approximate policy direction many
questions can clarify this a little bit
it's important to have the product of is
to be a contraction and to choose Sai
properly for this to happen okay so
maybe we take a little break like like
ten minutes just to digest this and then
we'll go into approximate polish
direction which will take a little
longer to go to go through