started
okay so this is the entire theory of
discounted problems in short can without
groups of course - just let me remind
you the problems we the the infant
correlation discounted problem involves
a stationary system a cost per stage the
stationary and in the involves a
discount factor less than one the course
is bounded so this is not this is a real
function that takes real values for
every initial state and what we want to
do is find a policy that minimizes this
this cost function and here's our
shorthand notation this is the cost per
stage the one stage cost and this is for
any J this mapping produces another map
in T so J by taking the minimum this
expression which is really the dynamic
programming type of minimization and for
any policy you remember stationary
policies the one that applies the same
you for every stage we have another
mapping where there is no minimization
but instead of you will plug in with
like news of X the the control dictated
by this policy so we have these two
mappings and the entire theory is
described by is given in this slide here
there is this bellman equation J star
satisfies a certain equation for every X
is an operator equation okay the entire
function is J star is obtained by
passing J star through teeth fixed point
of T and similarly for each policy the
cost of the policy is a fixed point of
this mapping optimality condition value
duration policy duration so now to use
effectively this mappings T and Tim you
we have to recognize some of the major
properties and there are two major
properties of these mappings
the first one is monotonicity
for any J and J prime such that J prime
is bigger than J okay if you apply the
map in T to them inequality is preserved
so if J prime is like this and J is like
that apply T to them they both change
but their order is preserved for every X
this is called monotonicity and it
applies both 14 you and for T and this
is extremely simple to see the reason is
that J is multiplied with a positive
number in this J in this TNT new
mappings going back to okay notice the
J's multiplied by alpha which is
positive and is the plus sign here so if
I increase J take it up to a J prime
then the right hand side is going to go
up the left hand side is also going to
go up and similarly for Team u
monotonicity is a universal property in
dynamic programming problems it holds
for all problems not just discounted by
any kind of problem dynamic programming
problem turns out to have such a
monotonicity property
it's very fundamental
here's another property that sort of
specific to to discount problems the
constant shift property okay if I take J
and I increase it uniformly by a
constant then TJ is also going to
increase uniformly by a constant except
that it will be multiplied by alpha and
similarly for teen you again if you I
ball this team you mapping and T if I if
I add a constant R to J then you're
going to get a constant alpha R that can
be taken out of the braces and the
minimization so again a trivial property
this constant shift there are variations
of the constant shift property for other
dynamic programming problems
this is shorthand he is the unit
function okay again shorthand notation
that you may need to eyeball a little
bit more closely to get familiar with so
monotonicity is present in all dynamic
programming problems constant shift is
special to discounted problems models
and it turns out that discounted
problems have another property of major
importance not all models have this
property but that's why they start the
problems are so is so much easier
because the T mapping and the T new
mapping are contraction mappings in a
mathematical sense given two functions
when you apply T to them their distance
shrinks okay that's what contraction
means and we will show this later so now
we start proving the basic theory it's
not going to be hard first of all let's
show that value iteration converges
starting with a zero function and
applying DP to it many many times gives
you the optimal cost function at the end
and here's the proof
for any initial state x0 and policy PI
infinite horizon policy
the cost is by definition given like so
okay now I break this cost into the cost
of the first K stages and the remainder
the tail portion the tail portion is
from K to infinity now the interesting
thing is that this trade portion because
of the discount factor here becomes
negligible as time goes to infinity
because it's multiplied by alpha to the
K here which goes down to zero
geometrically so the tail portion
satisfies because this G is bounded by M
and the remainder of the of the series
adds up to alpha K over 1 minus alpha it
satisfies this inequality so the state
portion goes to 0 as K goes to infinity
and take the minimum here I bound this
by this expression take the minimum here
over PI and the minimum here over PI the
minimum here over PI gives me simply J
times T times J times T times the zero
function so and after I take the minimum
ok so I get the j star equals less or
equal to P to the K of J 0 plus
something that's negligible and now take
the limit as K goes to infinity and I
get this result okay
I mean here mean here take the limit as
this is negligible this side gives you
this this side gives you that
it's really a very simple proof after
you look at it for a little while it
becomes very simple so that's it
now Bellman's equation the optimal cost
function satisfies this expression in
other words J stars of X equals min
expected value G Plus alpha g star J sir
and here's the proof okay we shown in
the previous slide that the case stages
cost is obtained is bounded by the
infant horizon cost and there's also a
tail portion that has this form apply
now T to this relationship now T is
monotone applied T to this side is going
to give me something that was still
bigger by applying T to this side so
what we get is applying T I get this
applying T by monotonicity inequalities
preserve and by the constant shift
property alpha to the K becomes alpha K
plus 1 here okay take now the limit as K
goes to infinity this thing goes away
this thing converges to J star so I have
J star bounded between T sub J star on
one side and P sub J star on the other
side and that's that using the
convergence of value direction this goes
to that this goes away and we have this
expression
that's it again very simple just so big
of a base of fundamental properties
okay I'm going to go to the third
property and I'll give you a chance to
ask questions contraction property given
any two bounded functions J and J Prime
I have that this expression here which
is the soup norm the maximum norm of TJ
- piece of J piece of J prime is less
than alpha the soup norm of J minus J
prime okay so look at what this says
view this as a measure of proximity of J
and J prime apply t to both of them then
the distance between them shrinks this
measure of prescribing the strings by a
factor alpha
similarly for team you
and the proof of this again two lines
denote by C the maximum over all states
the supreme north here the maximum X
then J prime is bounded between J plus C
the upper bound of the distance between
them and J prime J - minus C apply T to
both sides and apply and use
monotonicity use also the constant shift
property then apply T gives you this
applying T to this side gives you this
because of the constant shift property
if I change this expression by a
constant then after applying T it
changes by alpha times the constant and
similarly here and now bring this in
here and we have that the distance
between these two is less than alpha C
and that's that
okay so we have that in now the last
property a stationary policy is optimal
if and only if news of X attains the
minimum in balance equation in other
words in abstract notation this holds or
equivalently in more in more expanded
notation when you minimize the
right-hand side of balance equation
involving change star and you take the
minimum over you then you get news of X
so if you know J star by minimizing here
you get an optimal policy conversely if
you have a policy that satisfies this
minimization then it is optimal it's a
guarantee that's optimal it's an if and
only if relationship to write down
analytically the proof using this XT the
expanded notation takes perhaps a couple
of pages here the proof is a couple of
lines couple of short paragraphs askew
well here's the proof let's assume first
that new attains a minimum here so this
relationship holds then I want to show
that new is optimal okay
now using Bellman's equation we have
that this is equal to j star i have this
expression but this says that J star is
a tricks point of the mapping team you
and Tim you has as its unique fixed
point J new because of well it's it's
part of the bellman equation here so new
is optimal conversely suppose that you
have an optimal policy I want to show
that that takes the minimum here so if
it's optimal then J star is equal to J u
therefore I have because J nu is a fixed
point of t new I have J star equals to T
mu J start and combining this with
Belmonts equation because J star is
equal to this I have that TJ star is
equal to mu J star which is what I
wanted to prove again a few lines may
seem like they carry but it's not it's
correct okay you need to get used a
little bit to the abstract notation
so now we have the entire theory at
least we'll accept for algorithms for
infinite varieties and discounted
problems and you may want to ask
questions about this this about this
mapping century and in the proofs that I
have given is it clear what these
theorems say perhaps you can digest the
proofs a later but it's important to
understand what the theorem say I have
no more slides time for questions
there are different equations this
equation
perhaps I can write actually on the
blackboard
you can turn on the light please
okay Delmas equation is this okay now
this is equivalent to if I write it in
expanded form it's equivalent to
okay minimize over you expected value
over W and this holds true for all X so
it's a functional equation okay if X
takes a finite number of values then
this becomes a nonlinear system of a
final number ability if X takes n values
okay state of an end both of its an N
state Markov chain that you have then
this becomes a system of n nonlinear
equations with n unknowns okay and the
unknowns are this J star values J star
then becomes a vector of n components
so this is a long hand expression of
this if you have an infinite number of
states then this becomes a functional
equation like a partial differential
equation you know up an equation with an
infinite number of variables okay so
this is Bellman's equation
it's the equation it has a unique
solution for the infinite horizon
discounted problem within the class of
all bounded functions and now if you
write we if you write for a given policy
if you write this equation now this has
a similar character but it gives us
unknowns the components of J nu nought
of J star and equivalently this is
written as J mu sub X equal to expected
value over W G of X muse of X W plus
alpha J mu f of X news of X
so these two equations are have a
similar form but they are different and
they have different unknowns this has as
unknowns the optimal costs for the
corresponding starting States and this
has B as cost attached a solution the
cost of the policy new starting from all
possible states the malady condition I
don't know what you mean by optimal you
mean this is the optimality condition
when you say optimality conditions you
mean optimality condition of what
optimality of a policy you know what
what's optimal okay so that's what this
says here it says that this minimum here
is attained for new okay so if you
combine these two and they are really
identical then you have an optimal
policy so for an optimal policy these
two become the same yeah perhaps you
that's what you meant but for an optimal
policy they become the same but
generally they are not the same
okay
so this is the theory here and and it's
important for algorithms now in in the
next lecture on Wednesday we are going
to talk about algorithms particularly
this policy iteration algorithm and also
discuss the related models we're going
to focus also a little bit on value
iteration and then start talking about
approximations to these algorithms which
solve approximately the problem-solver
cups approximately this bellman equation
or find approximate approximately
optimal policies so that's where we're
headed
exhaust the subject of exact over the
next covered including next time and
then we go into approximation
bounded operator okay perhaps a rounded
operator but you know the term bounded
is used in a different context that's
more specialized so you have to have a
and a normed vector space perhaps and I
don't think that such a connection has
been useful in I think what's important
here is that the T operator is a
contraction yeah yeah I see what you
mean what you say is here is look at
this you take a look at this iteration
and you take it to infinity and
eventually you get J stark which is a
fixed point you have okay you have the
finite horizon dynamic programming
equation if you if you take the limit of
that when you get balanced equation so
it made one may be able to derive it or
understand this bellman equation the way
you describe but the way that I like to
understand it better is that p is a is a
contraction mapping and it has a home
unique fixed point this is a classical
theorem that that sort of relatively
simple to prove
before it sells it escaped optimality
condition that maybe show the existence
of the finality point so they show the
existence of the six points yes yeah
it's useful to know that there exists a
unique solution within the class of
bounded function so it gives you
existence as well as uniqueness that's
right the contraction property its
existence as well as uniqueness
although we do know that the optimal
cost function is bounded from elementary
arguments by the fact that the the cost
of every policy J PI is bounded
therefore be how you take the minimum
it's also you get also a bounded
function
yes
I don't understand the difference
because I don't understand the other
technique very well okay yeah there are
many schools of several schools I would
say for example the people artificial
intelligence have a different mentality
than people that are in operations
research in control theory if I could
make a superficial distinction between
different schools one is the artificial
intelligence schools the other one is
the operations research school and the
other one is the control engineering or
control fielding school and I think
there's also another line of research
called ADP but not approximate dynamic
programming but adaptive dynamic program
it's actually quite popular here in
China because because because because it
applies to control systems in the
context of automation robotics and in
manufacturing and process control and
people like that and it comes from a
tradition started by Weber's Paul
warbles and it's connected to nonlinear
control theory adaptive control and the
Frank Lewis for example has done a lot
of work his own ping he's earned whom I
met actually last week is also another
major player in this area and so there
are several different lines of research
now what's the difference between
control theory line of
operations research I think that work is
basically I think what major part of it
has to do with the type of applications
that that various various schools of
thought consider like Warren Powell for
example there's a lot of work with
logistics scheduling fleets of trucks to
do deliveries and to do things and and
there are people also who are more in
the traditional decision and control
framework like yourself and other people
that go to the CDC which have more of a
mixture between operations research and
and and control theory mentality I think
this is good because it provides greater
cross fertilization of ideas but
if you put together some people from our
professional intelligence and people
operations research you'll find that the
commonality of thinking is minimal and
they don't quite understand each other's
problems and techniques I think it may
be true also of control theory people
and operations research in operations
research took its people in control
people and in field and efficient
intelligent people in learning talk
about talk about not so much about
algorithms but but about learning toe
fury look at a lot
any other questions
okay so see you on Wednesday and I'm
told that we're going to have a new room
likely so look out for announcements and
the check the webpage and Sam will may
have more to say about that