so okay so as we want to go through the
subject of adaptive control control of
dynamic systems with unknown dynamics
and used to learning for that purpose
let me review this slide we want to do
approximate policy iteration for two
factors where policy evaluation is done
by solving the by minimizing the squared
error in satisfying the bellman equation
and so this is the mapping associated
with mu and use a Euclidean norm circle
to some distribution and now we focus on
deterministic systems while we consider
samples of state and control because the
system is deterministic the next state
is completely determined and then the
transition is to a Q factor involving
the people the the current policy and we
set up this least squares problem in
this form in fact this would be exactly
the same squares problem if we were to
use many many samples of state control
pairs but in practice we would use
perhaps a limited set of state control
pairs solve this get our selenium
squares problem and then that's the
that's our mu for the for the for this
policy and then we can use policy
improvement to get to define the new
policy which is going to be used to
drive the next cycle of policy direction
okay so now we're going to look into
this in the context of continuous space
and control systems and we're going to
consider a classical example of control
involving a linear system XK plus 1
equals a XJ plus bu K XK is a state
vector the state vector is a vector in
RN okay so it's a vector of n
continues state variables okay has n
components and UK is a vector of control
components of M control components okay
a is an N by n matrix B is an N by M
matrix and this is the standard
discrete-time linear system time
invariant because a and B do not change
over time and a classical problem is to
find the control sequence from 0 to
infinity that minimizes a quadratic cost
ok now Q is an N by n positive
semi-definite matrix X prime Q X is the
quadratic form associated with Q X prime
is a row vector Q a column vector such a
scalar quadratic form that penalizes
large values of XJ similarly here we
have a quadratic cost on control R is a
positive definite matrix and it
penalizes large values of control so
basically we want to drive the state
towards zero with small with relatively
small amounts of control and we want to
do it gradually over an infinite horizon
it's a classical formulation and that
meets a very elegant solution the
optimal policy is linear so the optimal
pulse is some matrix multiplying X
that's the optimal gain matrix of the
problem and if we can find that we
measure the state then we multiply it
with L and get to control the linear
feedback control scheme and it works
very nicely ok now how about few factors
well actually does the given any linear
part suppose you have a linear policy it
turns out that the Q factor of a state
control pair is a quadratic involving
some matrix chain you the same matrix
for all state control pairs okay the
optimal cost is actually
quadratic function of X the optimal Q
factor were more generally the Q factor
of any linear policy is a quadratic
involving some matrix here J mu that can
be calculated if we knew a and B however
we want to look at the case where a and
B are not known and when you want to
evaluate policies by finding the scale
mu using a simulator of the system as
opposed to using a and B and for this we
will use Q learning or Q factor policy
iteration approximate policy duration
with a Q factors represented as a linear
combination of basis functions but here
we are very fortunate because we know
ahead of time that the two factors of a
policy are quadratic so the thing that's
unknown here is this K nu but the basis
functions are the quadratic functions
the right but the right basis functions
are quadratic functions in this game you
can be viewed as a vector of ways that
ways the quadratic basis functions so
we're going to use as basis functions of
these things here all possible products
of state components with other state
components so X 1 squared X 1 2 X 1 3
and so 1 X 2 squared and so on similarly
we're going to use all quadratic
components involving control u 1 square
u 2 square and so one you want you to
all the possible cross terms and
similarly all the possible cross terms
between state and control so what is the
the the matrix fee here it is for a
given X and u the role of fee of course
fee has an infinite number of component
row
Rose okay but it has a finite number of
columns which correspond to these basis
functions and for a given X you the row
of fee is part precisely of all these
components so if you can give me if I if
you can hear me acts on you I can
calculate the the corresponding row very
easily and the Q factor of a linear
policy because we know that it has this
form it can be exactly represented
within the approximation subspace okay
we're very fortunate here because we
know good basis functions ahead of time
and if I can find the corresponding
weight vector this is the same as
finding this matrix chase of Nu and Q
learning is going to be used to find
this way to weight vector without
knowing and a and you just by use it you
a and B just by using a simulator of a
system in other words instead of having
area B I got the system and when I put
in here to I measure the state you need
to put in certain control it generates
another state and that's all I know
either all I need in order to apply to
learning more precisely suppose I have a
policy new and I want to evaluate it and
find the corresponding set of weights I
set up the bellman error squared I
generate a set of state control pairs
and write down the bellman equation
error form this least squares problem
which is linearly squares
remember these are the rows of the
matrix P okay for a given X in U and
similarly here and R is a vector
multiplying with growth
a column that my prince Robert is
awaiting before all this this basis
functions this is the one stage cost so
this is a linear least squares problem
and XJ U K XK plus one are many samples
generated by a system or a simulator of
the system and after I find after I do
the policy evaluation I can do policy
improvement by doing this minimization
at a given state X I minimize over here
but this minimization can be done in
closed form because this FS here are
what are this are quadratic in U so I
can very simply do this calculation so
that exact policy duration for Q factors
exact because I'm fortunate to know good
basis functions and knowledge of alien B
is not required it's quite remarkable
actually because people have been
working on adaptive control of linear
systems since time immemorial since the
50s okay this approach is relatively new
but actually discovered in the early
days of approximate dynamic program in
the early nineties but it has picked up
it has been picked up by control in the
control field quite strong recently okay
so because all of this is essentially
exact if you use a sufficient number of
state control pairs here and in fact you
need only a finite number in this
particular case
convergence to an optimal policy can be
shown now the basic idea of this example
has been carried further within the
field of adaptive dynamic programming
where you may have a nonlinear discrete
time system or you may have a cost
that's not quadratic and then what you
need to do is basically approximate
patience of these things here but still
you may with with with model free policy
duration ideas you can obtain viable
schemes that people have been have been
have been dealing with or experimenting
with for quite a few years now yes this
is XJ plus one because that's this is
the the cost approximation at the next
state right according to the formula of
Q learning so give an XK and UK you
generate XK plus one from that okay and
that's the yeah you need the XJ plus one
here not XJ if you go back to the Q
learning formulas let me just go back
okay the next state comes in here and
I'm sorry I can find it but
yeah actually here okay it's the next
state okay okay so you're looking the so
I think your question is okay i i i i
use this algorithm i calculate our new
by solving this problem and that gives
me the matrix chain new for the policy
that policy and then but i generate a
sequence of policies and the k news of
the different policies will converge the
k star let's say the k star
corresponding to the optimal few factors
I'm not sure I understand complete your
question you ask you the question of
convergence of this algorithm this
algorithm generates a sequence of
policies and the sequence of weights
weight vectors so where do these weight
vectors converge to they will converge
to the optimal weights that correspond
to the optimal matrix can you not argue
does not converge to you have our new
zero R mu 1 mu 2 and so on and these are
going to converge to our new star let's
say okay the our new corresponds to a
single policy
incidentally I'm asserted here
convergence but there is something that
but-but-but we have discussed
convergence of policy direction only for
the case of a finite number of states
where you have convergence in a finite
number of iterations right that's what
the only thing that we have talked about
convergence of policy direction in an
infinite space context is not a foregone
conclusion okay
it turns out however that for this
linear quadratic problem and also for
other related problems you get
asymptotic convergence of the optimum of
asymptotic convergence of the of the
generated few factors to the optimal new
factors and asymptotic convergence to an
optimal policy but only because you have
a lot of assumptions here it's a linear
quadratic problem has involved a lot of
structure so this again a result that
goes back to the late 60s convergence of
policy duration for the linear quadratic
problem okay now if this is a vast
subject and I we're not going to go into
it let's talk about another major area
but we also are not going to go in very
deeply what just summarize we have been
talking so far about approximation in
value space or approximation in q-factor
space now let's talk about approximation
in policy space where instead of
parameterizing costs or few factors we
parameterize policies so we parameterize
policies by a vector R of weights and
the corresponding weights or parameters
this is an approximation architecture
for policies so the policy that
corresponds to a weight vector R gives
you controls to apply at every possible
state which depend on R now for a given
R the policy is defined
and therefore the corresponding cost
vector is defined as a function of our
so ours
give me policies and I want to find good
arts that give me good policies that's
the idea and to do this we may wish to
optimize some measure of this cost
corresponding to R over R for example we
may formulate a cost function that
involves the weighted sum of costs
corresponding to the policy that
corresponds to R and X I are some state
dependent weights this is a scalar cost
function that depends on R minimize this
with respect to R gives you an optimal
parameterization of policy in an optimal
policy within this class optimal with
respect to this cost function there is
an issue here how do you weigh the
various states and so on but let's
bypass this ratio you may use any of a
large number of at least in principle
you may use any of a large number of the
term of optimization algorithms
iterative optimization algorithms for
minimizing subjecting for example a
random search method for a gradient
method or some other kind of method
that's the basic idea now there's the
question of how do you parameterize
policies generally the parameterization
is problem dependent you look at your
problem you know what is a good special
structure you look at you you know that
for simpler you have some idea about the
structure of optimal policies you try to
match the approximation architecture to
that structure okay but here's one
general way to use state features to
parameterize policies introduce a cost
approximation architecture we shall call
V here
okay depending on a parameter vector R
which and define indirectly a
parameterization of policies by means of
this minimization so if you know good
features you can still parameterize
these policies this way however it's
also possible to use different
parameterizations for state and for
policies in the parlance of this field a
policy approximate is called an actor
okay
and the cost approximation is called a
critic and many times and often these
type of systems and involve our
imaginations of one or both are called
act or critic systems or critic systems
or actor system actor only systems and
so on now let's look more specifically
at just be parameterization of policies
and this kind of objective how do you
minimize it one possibility is to use a
random search method there are many many
methods of this type very old and very
straightforward to apply the idea is
that you are at a given point at a given
set of parameters you look around this
set of parameters you search around and
you look for a better are so I'm at the
given are I know the cost here because I
have evaluated by simulation or
something then I generate different
values around it I calculate the cost
corresponding to each new value and I
move to another point that has better
cost okay this the rough idea there are
many many ways to construct
neighborhoods to search among
neighborhoods and is a method that has
gotten good publicity recently called
the cross enter
method which you can find in the
literature among others it has been very
successful for this tetris problem the
test case of the tetris problem that we
have talked in earlier lectures and it
beat by a large margin approximate
policy duration methods value
approximation value space you can apply
this to discrete state spaces or
continuous state spaces and control
spaces and the performance of random
search methods is notoriously inducing
kradic you may get excellent results or
you may get abysmal failures they can be
very slow it can be very unpredictable
but you can get success often enough to
consider them as viable possibilities
they are very simple that's that's
what's great about random search method
very simple and they in theory in paper
they they are guaranteed to converge in
practice that's not so but in theory
they're guaranteed converge to a global
optimum okay an alternative to a random
search is a gradient type of method like
the ones that you use in nonlinear
programming but perhaps adapted to the
context that we have here including the
stochastic context simulation so on
these maps are called policy gradient
methods they have also been used
extensively they have been researched on
extensively studied extensively again
they are also very unpredictable in
terms of their behavior the idea is to
move along the direction of the gradient
you have this cost function that depends
on R you calculate its gradient or an
approximation to the gradient perhaps a
sampled
version of the gradient by taking some
samples of this this cost function and
then you move in the direction of that
gradient according to some step size in
dynamic programming for particular
formulations there are formulas or
convenient formulas that give you
expressions for this gradient that you
can use and these formulas can be
approximated by simulation all gradient
methods suffer in principle by slow
convergence local minima and these are
no exception and because these are
implemented usually with simulation the
simulation noise can be a real problem
there have been successes here but they
have also been don't don't count on it
okay don't count on success you may be
likely but but but chances are that that
to have success you need to experiment a
lot and the outcome is still uncertain
okay so now let's look how
parameterization of point system work in
the context of approximate policy
direction in in in policy direction you
have policy evaluation and you also have
policy improvement policy improvement
involves a minimization overall policies
right over all controls suppose we try
to do the minimization only over the
parametrized class then you get
approximate policy improvement you may
have approximate policy duration but you
get approximate policy improvement
involving the parametrized class so
let's look at those a little bit more
closely given a certain policy defined
by its it's a parameter vector we
evaluated perhaps approximately with
some critics some kind of approximate
policy evaluation that produces some J
tilde of mu okay so this is a legitimate
cost approximator of policy and then
instead of using the policy improvement
process which is like so minimizing this
expression we do it approximately by
minimizing over a parametric class of
policies now that means that we minimize
over weight vectors of the parametric
class some kind of cost function that
weights the various components here so
you want to to minimize over R this
expression and you take weight and you
weigh the various states with with
different weights and you can try to do
this by some means some type of gradient
method but in the space of parameter
vectors
so here a gradient type of method given
a set of parameters of the actor moves
along the direction of this of the
gradient of this expression to get a new
actor value than a new actor value and
so on
perhaps one or more several steps so
it's an alternation of critic implement
critic approximations and actor steps in
between the critic changes schemes like
that have been used extensively in the
field of adaptive dynamic programming
for continuous pace deterministic
problems particular this adaptive
capable systems unknown parameters it's
a lot of research here very active field
of research and there are considerable
theoretical issues to be resolved
particularly for stochastic problems
most of the work has been for
deterministic problems and even for
those there is a lot of a lot of mystery
about how these methods work any
questions
yeah this can be different yeah this is
an this is in the context of actor
critic methods a critic is okay an actor
is evaluated by a critic and then the
actor tries to perform approximate
policy improvement the critic does
approximate policy evaluation the actor
does approximate policy improvement each
one within its own parameter space
[Applause]
the nation policy space
okay your question has to do with this
okay we mentioned it's possible to have
a different approximation for the cost
function a different approximation for
the policy now in this stage here in
this equation there is only one
approximator the approximator is in R
but it is defined implicitly by an
approximator of cost okay so this is
really an actor system which uses
acrylic in order to define the actor
this R is defined implicitly through the
critic approximation but you will use
this in a scheme which minimizes this
expression
okay so let's take a break for 5-10
minutes and we'll close the course and
you may ask also your questions
and and and so let's get back in the ten
minutes
okay so we are very close to the end of
the course and we carried a lot of
material more than I thought actually we
would but still there are many many
topics that we have not covered I'll
just make a list of those cases someone
wants to ask some questions I don't know
or after the end of the class we have
focused on discounted finite state
problems but with but that there are
continuous time version of those the
semi Markov problems the theory for
those the approximation algorithms and
all that are very similar to the
discounted case it's just that the
discount factor is a state dependent we
there are stochastic shortest path
problems there are discounted and
involves a terminal stay to which you
going to go with minimum expected cost
they have similar theory to discounted
problems but it's it's a little bit more
tricky but a lot of the theory extends
average cost problems are still more
tricky but some of the theory expand
extends sequential games where in
addition to the expectation it's the
stochastic nature of the problem there's
also an antagonistic opponent the the
approximation theory for those is is
more complicated as far as I know
incomplete because this is they're just
more difficult problems and this is the
maximization operation that makes things
complicated when you try to do sampling
continuous space problems well we talked
about them this at some points in the
class we mentioned that that when well
they are interesting in the context of
adaptive dynamic programming and we
haven't gone too
into this subject it's a very fertile
ground for further research and
application continuous time problems to
have with continuous space these are
continuous time optimal control problems
they're very interesting and we have not
discussed them and they also have this
interesting idea of Amy to approximate
the derivative of the cost to go
function as opposed to the cost to the
cost function itself this is an area
where there's a lot of a lot of things
to be done to clarify and and some of
you may want to look into those adaptive
dynamic programming for deterministic
optimal control problems there is the
issue of again if you have continuous
time problems then there's the issue of
cost function approximation of cost
functions everybody's or cost function
differences I think this is an area
where that's not very clear and needs a
lot of research approximation policy
space I think from my comments you may
have realized that it's not a failsafe
type of method there's a lot of research
to be done in random search and gradient
type methods here's a subject that we
did not discuss how do we pick the the
the approximation architecture how do we
pick the basis functions suppose that we
have our collection of basis functions
to choose from which are parameterized
can we make an optimal choice between
them bye-bye within this parametric
class is it possible to generate basis
functions automatically some very very
important questions
but not enough has been done in this
area yet fertile ground for research
okay here's another area from discussed
at all a lot of the things that we
covered had to do with solving linear
problems such as linear equations or
least squares
squares problems and solve them by
simulation in other words using Monte
Carlo methods to solve linear problems
now these problems arose in dynamic
programming in this class but the ideas
extend much more generally so you might
talk about a field that you might name
Monte Carlo linear algebra which is the
use of Monte Carlo methods to solve
linear problems that arise in fields
other than dynamic programming not only
dynamic programming there is the husband
work in this area it's an old field by
the way he dates Monte Carlo methods for
solving linear equations had had been
advocated by fond Newman 91950 it's an
old idea to use simulation to solve
linear problems but it has received a
lot of attention recently and that means
an interesting field for research ok
now let's focus on the things that we
have covered we cover met we went
through many methods and I want to tell
you right ahead of time with certainty
that there is no clear winner there is
no best method if you're looking for a
best method there is no such thing there
are good methods for some problems and
it's a variety of methods and it's
important to understand them both
theoretically and and be aware however
that they do not provide higher on clad
performance guarantees you may try a
method but there's no guarantee it's
going to work you may have to try
several methods or you may have to be
more creative about how you apply it or
maybe invent a new method for your
problem all types of methods have major
flaws in approximate policy duration
projected equations particular you have
the issue of oscillations in the issue
of exploration
in aggregation you have restrictions on
the approximation architecture in other
words the basis functions happy to be
defined in terms of probability
distribution and that's a restriction if
you want to do approximation in policy
space optimization policy space then all
the methods available for this at flaky
are unreliable gradient methods based on
simulation random search these methods
this may or may not work for you despite
all this discarding and disappointing
picture there have been impressive
successes with enormous Lee complex
problems for which often there is no
alternative methodology we are looking
at difficult problems for which there
are few methods and you should not be
discouraged by the fact that that we
don't have a methodology that's
foolproof we have focused on approximate
policy duration approximate value
duration q-learning
versions amusing few factors but there
are also some other methods that we have
not covered at all we mentioned rollout
which is very simple often successful
and generally reliable if I had to pick
the most reliable method within this
landscape but all out is the one it it
doesn't it's not very ambitious but
reliable and often will give you very
good results approximate linear
programming which uses linear
architectures to approximate a certain
linear programming formulation of the
bellman equation for MVP is is also
another methodology that has its
successors and has received attention
both fear
it can be impractically it's another
alternative worth considering I hope I
gave the message to you that even though
this is a field where there's a lot of
trial and error theoretical
understanding is very important in the
fear is non-trivial you need to to dig
into the theory to be able to apply
these methods in practice still however
for all the theory that you may know
practice is a challenge it's an art in a
challenge to creativity very difficult
problems you should expect that so
that's it that's all I have to say and
now it's a good time to ask questions
and incidentally if someone has a longer
question perhaps we can discuss it after
the class or during the next couple of
weeks that I'm going to be here I think
why you may send me an email and try to
make a arrange a meeting so questions
yes
[Music]
we knew already the pro-soviet
so my question is what is the efficient
[Music]
okay so your question has to do with a
linear programming approach toward
solving dynamic programming problems and
whether this is an efficient approach
for exact implementation and also for
approximate implementation okay let me
say a few things about linear program
this refers to this Bellman's equation
can be equivalently written as the
solution of a linear program and this
linear program involves involves a large
dimension potentially there is a
variable for every every state and
control pair okay and there's a
constraint for I'm sorry there's a
variable for every state and there's a
constraint for every state and control
pair so so so but it is a legitimate
method for solving exactly finite state
dynamic programming problems it cannot
be applied to infinite state dynamic
programming problems because there are
no infinite dimensional linear programs
there are no algorithms for infinite
dimensional linear programs that are
effective the actual linear programming
and policy direction are related in
other words one can show that the policy
Direction is an execution of some
variant of the simplex method that
solves the same linear programming
problem people have used have looked at
this the issue of comparative efficiency
by complexity analysis and there has
been some interesting work I can't
remember exactly the details but linear
programming is a polynomial algorithm
and people have worked on complex
analysis for policy direction they have
made comparisons when it comes to
approximations it's really very hard to
tell which whether approximate linear
programming or approximate policy
direction will work better on a given
problem it's it's just one of those
things for which there are no guarantees
in this field you can try both of them
and see which one works better and there
are a lot of cases that is that argue
for approximate linear programming and
also case studies that argue against it
so that's all I can say there is no
clear answer for the case of
approximations some other questions
okay I want to thank you for your
attendance and like I said you may
contact me after the lecture
[Applause]