okay we have been talking so far about
costs of course function supported
skillet optimum cost function now we are
going to talk about I related quantity
or the Q factor for the function prepare
X cube compares for states and controls
okay talk about you to practice our
functional cares of state and control
another state like jh5 state and control
and by definition the optimal to partner
of Xu is this expression here we explore
next you asking you then just a
well-defined one feet right and it is
the first over of starting at x applying
cube in the first stage
I'm gonna put it here
okay
start again okay the Q factor of a pair
xu is what you see here in this line by
definition j star is the optimal cost
function x bar is the next state so this
is starting at state k the the cost of
the first stage by using you and then
plus you add the cost of all the
remaining stages using an optimal policy
so j star had x you start at x and you
use an optimal policy all the way
through q star of x in you you first use
you some you whatever it is okay not
necessarily optimal and then you use an
optimal policy after that okay
now this seems a little strange but if
you look at this expression here it is
the right hand side of Bellman's
equation and you can write balanced
equation in terms of q factors like this
and also if i give you the optimal q
factors you can calculate the optimal
policy by minimizing this expression
here rather than minimizing this entire
expression okay now not only that but i
can write the value iteration method in
terms of two factors it's given by this
expression here okay given qk the
minimum of qk is is is the internet of
via turret of value iteration and then
QK plus 1 is given by this expression
and if you minimize over you if I write
the minimum of this over you you get
exactly value iteration so it's another
way of writing value iteration only this
memory wasteful perhaps because now you
maintain a function of both X and u
however there's a big benefit from that
because if you can calculate Q of X and
u then you can obtain the optimal policy
by means of a simpler minimization
that's one idea behind you factories
okay now to factors there are other ways
to interpret them you can view them as
cost functions for a different problem
that involves an Augmented state where
the states are x and u rather than just
X so you have a pair X u and then we and
then if you set up a bellman equation
that involves this mapping here then
that's bellman equation for this
Augmented problem so in particular by
using this interpretation all the
results that we have for cost functions
carry over to Q factors so you have
value iteration for two factors that is
the same as value iteration for the four
course you also have policy narration
for two factors and you have also a
bellman equation where the mapping is
not T but rather it is this F that
operates on two factors to produce other
Q factors
now if you're doing exact if you are
applying this all going to value it in
policy direction exactly then
mathematically whether you use two
factors or costs is the same thing it's
exactly the same mathematical operations
you just keep track of a larger vector
or a larger function so you need more
storage but the amount of computation is
equal and the results are mathematically
the same however differences start
properly occur when you are using
approximations you use approximate value
direction or approximate or Z Direction
the main thing is that if you have
optimal Q factors then you can obtain an
optimal policy by this minimization and
in the context of approximation if you
obtain good approximations of two
factors then you can get also an
approximate policy through this equation
and the nice thing is that you don't
need to know G and the expectation
operation also is not needed in other
words you can compute policies in a
modern free fashion okay
let me explain this a little bit more in
in in in the standard way of obtaining
ten optimal policies is you compute J
star and then you minimize over you this
expression to do this minimization you
need to have a model for G you need to
have a model for the random variable
involved here so you take the expected
value you need to have a model for the
system f to plug in here so given J star
you need to have a model to compute an
optimal policy however if you have Q
star somehow then you don't need a model
anymore
you can simply minimize this expression
here and that's that now this turns out
to be a great thing
approximate dynamic programming in many
contexts will you have a simulator of a
system but you don't know the internal
dynamics and you have data coming in
from the simulator and data coming out
you use this data to calculate few
factors and after you have the cue
factors then you have a list of all
these cues in whatever state occurs you
look in your list and you obtain the
optimal policy without having to know
the model in any at any point of course
so far I have not told you how to
calculate you factors other than by
using the model however there's a method
called q-learning that we're going to
discuss later next week whereby we use
samples of this expectation obtained by
some black box some simulator in order
to calculate the sort of approximate is
mapping and to calculate by simulation
these 2-star factors or some
approximation to them and in the end no
model is necessary two factors can be
calculated in a model free fashion by
sampling it turns out and that's the big
thing about them however we haven't
talked about approximations yet so we
will postpone this discussion for next
week but I just wanted you to know that
there are these few factors and in exact
when you're doing exact calculations
they are no different than costs it's
only in the presence of approximations
that they make a difference okay
now we have focused on discounted
problems these are the easiest problems
the ones for which this the strongest
theory however there are other dynamic
programming modules and let me give you
some examples we're not going to cover
them in any detail but just don't want
you to be aware first of all there are
undiscounted problems where the discount
factor is exactly equal to one there is
no discount factor now how do you keep
the cost the total cost of such a system
finite well many of these problems
involve either convergence or reaching
exactly some kind of a cost free state
well the cost does not accumulate any
more so for example there may be a
special termination state some
destination which once you reach then
you stay there with no further cost like
reaching a goal okay in minimum with
minimum cost or a robot completing an
operation at some time in the future and
then after completes the operation there
is no more cost associated with that now
such a problem is called usually a
shortest path problem or if there is
uncertainty about this a Markov chain
involved and some kind of stochastic and
certainty in the system it means called
a stochastic shortest path problem there
are also other problems where the
termination stage is sort of reached
asymptotically and of course accumulate
to something finite we call this
generally and discounted problems and
they have their own theory it is not
quite as strong as the for discounted
problems but depending on the
assumptions that you have you may get
pretty strong results another major type
of problem is when time is not discrete
you may have a finite number of states a
Markov chain but it may evolve in
continuous time like for example
queueing systems queueing systems are
typically finite or maybe
countable number of states corresponding
to the different levels of loading of
the queue different numbers of customers
in the queue and then a customer departs
and the state goes down by one what a
customer arrives in the state goes up by
one however the time that it takes for
the customer to depart may be random
okay and may dependence on your control
action and the time that it takes for a
customer to arrive is also random
our customers may be arriving according
to a Poisson process they may arrive
very quickly or may take a long time
depending on the roll of the dice okay
now if you have a transition that takes
a long time and you use discounting
continues time discounting the discount
factor is going to be stronger for the
cost associated okay if a transition
takes a long time then the cost that
will incur at the end of the transition
will be discounted more strongly so what
you have is essentially discount factors
that are random and depend on the state
and possibly on the control that you
apply other than that these problems
finite state continuous time problems
which are also called semi Markov
problems otherwise are pretty similar to
discount the problems the main
difference is this they can be viewed as
discount problems with state in control
dependent discount factors so what's
going to happen is the T mapping is
going to change somewhat to incorporate
this this discount factor that's state
dependent the T new mapping is going to
change but everything else will say
pretty much the same in terms
mathematically speaking and these
problems have about a strong theory are
discounted problems
now let's look at another class of
problems that is harder okay more
difficult continues time and continued
space models now these are the classical
automation problems that you encounter
in practice like controlling an aircraft
controlling a car controlling a robot
controlling some kind of a process a
chemical process the traditional control
theory problems are typically continuous
pace and often continuous time you apply
control not are discrete intervals but
that contain over continues over time
now here there are some substantial
difference from the screen time first of
all mathematically these are far more
complex particularly if you have
stochastic uncertainty there's some
pretty substantial mathematics
associated with with with the continuous
time stochastic processes involved here
that diffusion models they are models
involved in continuous time white noise
which are little calculus we are talking
about some pretty heavy-duty mathematics
even for deterministic problems which
are continuous time there are tricky
issues associated with differential
equations there is something called want
reactance maximum principle that governs
the the solution of is there's a is a
very strong and theory that goes back
hundreds of years or the calculus of
variations the types of Euler and
LaGrange they were considering this type
of problems it is possible to address
problems like that by dynamic
programming based on time discretization
mathematics here a little shaky and you
need to be careful how do you what kind
of statements you make but I'd like to
give you an idea of how dynamic
programming applies to these problems
basically you have a continued
time system involving a differential
equation or a system of differential
equations so X of T is a vector function
of time and you have a differential
equation on the right-hand side there is
X the state of the system and the
control that you apply at time T from
some constraint set there's also a cost
function that is an integral from 0 to
infinity and typically for this interval
to make sense you have to have some kind
G has to be 0 at some state which we are
trying to to regulate the system to okay
let's call J starts of X the optimal
cost starting from initial state X and
let's try to address this problem by
time discretization
let's discretize the time in intervals
of delta small delta then the system
becomes discrete like this okay we
differentiate this derivative here
XK plus 1 minus XK by PI Delta and we
sort of assume that over the small Delta
interval the control that you apply is
constant so piecewise constant control
but changing very frequently now you get
now a discrete problem where the cost
Porter stage is this G multiplied with
Delta
okay so bellman equation for the Delta
discretized problem looks like this okay
I indexed by Delta and the optimal cost
is the minimum over U of the cost per
stage within this Delta interval plus
the optimal cost at the next state which
differs from the current state by this
Delta times F okay now let's suppose
that that we can take the limit as Delta
go to 0 and we obtain the optimal cost
suppose that this limiting operation is
ok and it is okay under some conditions
but you have to believe it
about how you about these conditions
then how does this Batman equation
become in the limit take this on the
other side this is a constant not
depending on you and divide by Delta and
take the limit as Delta goes to 0 then
Delta is going to be canceled out you
get 0 on this side and on the other side
you get the inner product of the
gradient matrix of J star gradient with
respect to x times f of X you okay this
is called the hamilton-jacobi bellman
equation
Hamilton Jacob you lived in the in the
18th century okay and so this equation
dates from way back bellman is more
contemporary and and he played around
with this equation quite a bit and
brought it to life again in the 20th
century so his name is associated with
it it's a famous equation not to be
confused with a discrete-time bellman
equation this is the continuous-time
analogue and it involves the gradient
here of J star how do we know that J
star has a gradient well the answer is
we don't know
we hoped it has a gradient but we don't
really know they have two big conditions
to guarantee that it's quite possible
that J star has some corners but may
even be discontinuous some points ok but
assuming that this equation this
discrete is this limiting operation is
correct you have the situation and now
the optimal policy can be obtained by
minimizing for each X in here like in
balanced equation now notice an
interesting thing okay let's so let's
see how policy direction will work
informally policy direction for
continuous-time systems goes as follows
given the current policy do a policy
evaluation which is to find a function J
mu that satisfies this equation
without the minimum here of course this
equation is obtained from the bellman
equation for the new policy by taking
the limit as Delta to go to zero then do
a policy improvement which is to
minimize this expression with J mu and
get a new policy nu bar that's a
legitimate policy direction Albert that
people have been using increasingly in
the last few years however there's a
very interesting thing to not be noted
in order to do policy improvement we
need to know the gradient of J mu naught
J mu it's the gradient that we need to
know and this perhaps should give us
some pause to think about the
discrete-time case should be we be
trying to learn cost values or cost
difference values okay we'll come back
to this point again in the next lecture
but for the moment I'd like to notice
that as time it becomes continues than
the character of this equation the
bellman equation changes at this
particular point
okay have any questions so we have all
these many problems perhaps we'll touch
upon some of them at some point but in
but really there are many different
variations of problems and we would like
to have a unified way to treat them we
don't want to prove the same theorems
over and over again for slightly
different versions of the same problem
so what I'm going to get into now is a
couple of more advanced topics that have
to do with a unified way of dealing with
dynamic programming problems so let's
let's look at a more abstract view of
dynamic programming and just to just as
a mathematical preliminaries suppose
that you have a space any kind of vector
space with some norm RN could be one a
function spaces could be another and a
contraction mapping is a mapping f that
map's Y in the space into itself and has
the property that that when you apply
this F to two vectors Y & Z you get
their distance to become smaller than
the distance of Y & Z so this is the
definition classical definition of
contraction mapping Rho is something
between zero and one it's called the
modulus of contraction of F that's
definition in an important example
that's relevant for us is that if you
let X to be a set like the state space
in dynamic programming and V is some
positive value function a functional f
of X that is takes positive values let's
consider V sub X which is the set of all
functions on X such that the ratio of J
and V is bounded over X J itself may not
be bounded but when scaled with V it
becomes bounded okay
if V is identically equal to one then
this is just the set of all bounded
functions and we can define a norm on
this function space the weighted soup
norm which is the maximum of this ratio
here so if V is identically equal to one
you get the case of the maximum norm but
this is a scaled norm and I'll show you
why this is convenient this is the
important special gift for the discount
problem the Pappy is T and T mu for V
identically equal to 1 and Rho equal to
the discount factor they are contraction
mappings in the sensor ok let me give
you an example why this contraction
mapping ideas may be useful in dynamic
programming suppose that we want to we
have a problem where the state space is
not finite but rather it is countable
let's say the states are 1 2 all the way
to infinity like for example a queueing
system with infinite storage you can
have 0 customers one customer to any
number so a number of states is
countable and not only that but the cost
per stage which depends on the state may
not be bounded for example if you have a
hundred customers there will be a
greater cost than having Tadcaster less
than if you have an infinite number of
customers you may want to have an
infinite cost so there may not be a
bound on the one stage cost function
naturally in some of these problems
however if we introduce a weighted norm
which takes into account the change in
the cost function then the cost per
stage will become bounded but in the
sense of the weighted soup normal ok now
here is a theorem that says that if you
have the mapping team you to have this
Natick form so remember I is here the
the states one two and so on and let's
say the team you mapping has the form a
constant which represents the cost per
stage a state I and also it is linear
with coefficients AI J being being like
the transition probabilities for example
from I to J suppose that you have a t nu
has this form where bi and AI JSON
scalars then team use a contraction
mapping of modules row if and only if
this relationship holds now if the a IJ
is our transition probabilities they add
up to 1 but when scaled with this V that
schemes also the one stage cause if if
you have this relationship holding in
other words the future V okay a IJ
depends on J so V may be increasing
relative to Y but if a IJ decreases
faster as J increases then you make up
this relationship holding and then you
may have a contraction mapping for team
you and if you have a contraction
mapping for TM u then the corresponding
T mapping is also a contraction mapping
so if your model satisfies this
condition which in queueing systems is
sort of a standard condition then you
have all the necessary structure to
obtain the strongest possible results
balanced equation has a unique solution
there's an optimality condition there is
a value iteration works policy Direction
works everything that works for finite
state space and bound at one stage cause
extends to unbounded one stage cost
provided you can apply this kind of
structure so this is an example where
you can extend the range of the nice
results by using some analysis involving
contraction
generally speaking with contraction
mappings the main result is that they
have a unique fixed point this is a
classical result from analysis if you
have a contraction mapping F with
modulus Rho then it has a unique fixed
point within the set of B sub X of
bounded functions so in the context of
dynamic programming this is just
translation to the fact that Bellman's
equation has a unique solution
furthermore if J is any function B sub X
then if you apply F repeatedly to J then
in the limit you get J star and you have
also this estimate of the error okay the
error of F case of J - J star decreases
with Rho to the K as as K increases
since the classical contraction mapping
theorem and and okay this is the proof
of this you can find in the textbook and
there is also there okay there's also
group all the mathematical details are
there that's the that's the key the main
theorem for contraction mappings now
what we would like to do is leverage the
power of contraction mappings and into
dynamic programming so that we don't
have to deal with all these different
models that that that very insignificant
details we don't want to deal them with
them separately so let's look at an
abstract form of dynamic programming
based on the fundamental properties of
monotonous T and contraction suppose R
sub X is the set of real valued
functions J and let's introduce a
mapping age that takes States controls
and functions J into other functions T
sub J so instead of dealing with
expected G Plus alpha J
so on we abstract it more generally and
let's introduce policies in a more
abstract way let's consider the set of
policies which are functions mu such
that muse of X belongs to some
constraint set for every state and
consider the mapping team you associated
with a policy mu which is obtained from
H when you plug in mu let's consider the
problem of finding a solution to this
equation J star equal to DJ star so this
is very similar to what we have been
doing except we use a more abstract
function H for the expression in the
dynamic programming algorithm now if we
introduce this framework we
simultaneously can deal with many many
different problems one example is the
discounted problems that we have been
looking at which is this expression here
one stage cost plus alpha times the J
function another case is the semi markov
problems I was talking about earlier the
continuous-time problems after all the
mathematics are said and done then it
turns out that the right expression for
V that you should be using is the sum
over one stage cost plus another
expression here which involves this this
state dependent discount factors I
talked about earlier so instead of
having here alpha times the transition
probabilities you have some numbers that
involve I could that in that add up to
something less than one and also but are
have a little different section than
here a third type of example arises in
game theory sequential games where W is
not chosen randomly
not random but it's chosen by some
opponent so I choose my you now in my
opponent looks at what I chosen and
chooses W from sunset trying to make
things bad for me
then I choose another you after having
looked at what he has done
then he chooses another W and so on this
again has a dynamic programming
structure pretty similar to the Socastee
case from one state I apply a control
then some W occurs and then I go to a
new state apply another control and so
on it's just that W is not a random
variable but it's chosen
antagonistically so instead of having an
expected value you have a maximization
and the corresponding mapping becomes
like this so minimax control problems
robust control worst-case control games
against nature game suggests
antagonistic opponent all fall into this
category here's another example shortest
path problems okay it's a very simple
type of problem you have a graph with n
nodes in the destination node each time
you go from one node to another node
there's a length associated with it or
cost and you start at any one node and
you want to find a path that has minimum
length a path to the destination that
has minimum length you can view this as
a dynamic programming problem where the
states are X okay the nodes of the graph
U is the choice of next node that you
make the branch that you go from that I
love which you go from the current state
and J is is a cost function associated
with the different nodes in the graph so
the H mapping has this form except if if
if d if u takes you directly to the
destination in which case there's a zero
cost after that
so this is the deterministic shortest
path problem there's a stochastic
version of this problem where when I
choose you the next node is chosen
according to a probability distribution
which represents W or there is a minimax
version of this problem where the next
node is chosen by an antagonistic
opponent in which case I get a none
discounted version of this type of thing
here all of these problems can be cast
as special cases of the general
framework and I can use a unified theory
to treat all of them simultaneously
these and a few more ok so the
assumptions I'm going to use here are
first of all monotonicity of this
mapping age if you have two functions J
and J Prime one of them higher larger
than the other then applying h maintains
the the the direction of the inequality
and we can show all the standard
analytical and computational results of
computational dynamic programming within
this more general context if
monotonicity is satisfied and in
addition you have a contraction property
and the contraction property for this
mapping h is that a map in steam mu and
TJ are contractions for every j team use
of j and TJ belong to B sub X and for
some alpha and all mu and J prime J you
have this contraction property so the
contraction assumption holds if the team
new mapping which is obtained from h by
plugging new in terms of instead of you
has is a contraction if you just have on
the tonicity then as you program in
undiscounted problems then you can still
show various forms
the basic results under some conditions
but the fear is not quite as strong and
a weaker substitute for the contraction
assumption is something called semi
contractive nests who are roughly
speaking for some policies mu T mu is a
contraction but for others it is not
also there's some additional assumptions
that guarantee that the non contractive
you are not optimal so essentially
you're operating within the range of the
contractions and and and the contractive
Theory comes into play more or less
we're not going to go into great detail
of this I just want to sensitize you
that there are these extensions of the
theory and we're not just dealing with
discounted problems and I'll just sketch
the results if you have this contraction
and monotonicity then first of all team
U and T are weighted soup non
contraction mappings with and they have
unique fixed points so Bellman's
equation holds based on the contraction
properties of age the second is that
value iteration converges within the
small general setting starting with any
J and applying tmu you get the cost
corresponding to a policy
similarly starting for 40 starting at
any J if you apply this mapping T
repeatedly in the limit you get J star
you have that you have an optimality
condition that that mu attains the
minimum in the definition of T if and
only if J mu is equal to J star and the
proof is very similar to what we gave
for discounted problems if you have
assuming both one of the Nestene
contraction you have that that the fixed
point of T J star is the minimum over
all J mu you also have
that for there always exists for any
epsilon and epsilon optimal policy a
policy that attains the optimum within
epsilon you can consider also
non-stationary policies and you may
define for any non stationary policy the
cost associated with it like so in
pretty similar way as for the discounted
case and finally that J star is not only
a minimum of a stationary point is not
only optimal over stationary policies is
also an optimal over non stationary
policy as well if you recall I gave you
a reference to a research monograph that
I just finished about a year ago and all
of this abstract dynamic programming
stuff is part of that monograph so I
couldn't resist the temptation of
telling you about okay so now also we
have algorithms of valuing policy
duration with this this more general
framework value iteration is is
convergent in this sense here for any
starting J policy direction is defined
in the abstract way that we have seen
earlier given a policy mu K we evaluate
it like so by finding it as a fixed
point of the map continue okay find UK
plus one by taking the minimum in the in
the T mapping and it's everything goes
is defined in the usual way there's an
optimal optimistic version of policy
direction where the policy evaluation is
done with a finite number of values
directions rather than with an infinite
number of value durations which is
policy duration or with one which is
value iteration and so everything goes
through with in the abstract framework
and we cover in this way an enormous
range of problems
without much analysis and with a common
understanding for all of this
so that's one theoretical offshoot that
I wanted to sensitize you to and the
second one has to do with our
synchronous algorithms but let's take a
break for ten minutes and then we'll get
back to that okay have any questions yes
I'm wondering if we don't know there are
many examples wondering if we don't know
the distribution about uncertainty how
to model these problems with the worst
case we don't amount of customer butter
we can observe we can use the history
informations first several stage we
don't know the if the Japanese produced
I even will however a long time we don't
know the exactly introducer
yes and we may update our update our
estimation equality tribution
but can we improve okay the question is
the following we have okay we have this
stochastic model and perhaps we know
that stochastic but unfortunately we
don't have a model for W we don't have
the probability distribution so you can
either view this there are many
different ways to address the situation
one possibility is you may not know the
distribution but we may know some bounds
on it in that case you may adopt a not a
pessimistic viewpoint our worst case you
point and model it in this set in in
this set membership fashion okay you
don't know the distribution you can take
expectation but you know bounce so we
take this worst-case viewpoint and then
you fall into the minimax case that
would be one way to do
another way to do it is perhaps you have
the distribution maybe unknown but you
know that it has some form like for
example it may be a Gaussian but you may
not know the mean yes right a parametric
type of method and then what you need to
do as the system is operating you need
to estimate at the same time the
parameters now problems where you have
what the model has unknown parameters
are known as adaptive control problems
okay and adaptive control problems are
covered by this methodology however you
have to view them in a more general
setting to introduce special state value
addition of state variables which model
the unknown dynamics or the unknown
parameters in the system finally there's
another possibility that even though you
may not know W you may have you may not
know the distribution of W you don't
have a closed form
you don't know it's Poisson dance you
know it's dancing whatever however you
may have a simulator of W then you fall
into the model free case that I talked
about earlier and you may use the cue
learning ideas so there are all these
various possibilities but let me also
add but if you don't know your model is
generally a bad thing not a good thing
there are a few things you can do
however
okay so let's take a break and be back
in 10 mins exactly