I'm ready to go
so it's fine I'm very happy to see so
many of you here today to listen to
professor
for six days course on the posh man and
an improvement so before professor the
fact that starts at what cost
many briefly introduced so Dimitri
protectors studied mechanical and
electrical engineering at the National
Technical University of a 16-piece and
obtained his PhD in citizen science from
Massachusetts Institute of Technology he
has held faculty positions mystic
engineer economics district department
name standard and then the electrical
engineering department of the University
of Illinois in Urbana since 1970 he has
been teaching at the electrical
engineering and computer science
department of the MIT where he is
recovering in McAfee professor of
engineering his research spans several
years including commendation control
large-scale computation and data
communication networks and is close
offering activities we have written
numerous research papers and quality
assurance they say 15 books right now
several of which are used and test those
in my office
missing all the expansion program
started the business pieces and has
continued through the present with many
research papers and separate books and
research monographs professor those
habits was awarded with impulse binding
97 of prize for research excellence in
interface between operations research
and computer science for his book nearly
dynamic programming for all the way the
job degrees it was awarded the 2003
national award for operations research
then into a summit important American
control conference jamun target for the
leading educational work and the 200
alive impulse expository writing network
in 2001 he was in a kitchen a dining
space
[Music]
[Applause]
thank you very much Sam well it's my
pleasure to be here I'm concerned a
little bit with sound can you hear me in
the back now okay we're trying to get a
microphone okay so I'll try to do my
best to the sound and this is six
lecture course on approximate dynamic
program so somewhat advanced course it's
a research oriented course the subject
right at the forefront of research in
Tzfat subject with many applications and
interesting theory there are many books
now in on the subject however my
lectures are going to be based not
surprisingly on my books the first book
is the hero dynamic programming book
that I've written will charge the
checklist back in 1996
so I research monograph really and many
parts of it still remain relevant now I
have a textbook who the latest edition
was published two years ago and this is
more up to date and it's also more
accessible than the first book in last
year I wrote a research monograph called
abstract dynamic programming that has
some relevance to the course material we
are going to be posting the slides my
slides in a website which will be
announced however if you want to see a
full set of slides on dynamic
programming including approximate
dynamic programming you may find it here
there are several sets of slides the
latest being one or two years ago okay
so
let me give you a brief outline of what
we're going to be covering okay this is
our subject large-scale dynamic
programming based on approximations and
in part on simulation a research area of
great interest for the last 25 years and
it comes under various names
reinforcement learning that's the that's
the name that people in artificial
intelligence or learning use and neuro
dynamic programming or approximate
dynamic programming that I have been
using they have been two lines of
research which at some point converged
and predicted in a very productive and
fruitful way one and was from artificial
intelligence the reinforcement learning
line with its ideas on on feature based
representations of functions and
relations and also the idea of learning
by observation or simulation and the
other side of the the other line of
research came from optimization control
theory with his emphasis on formal
optimization methods and algorithms such
as policy duration value duration and so
on at some point people that worked over
here people who worked over here
realized that they were doing with the
same problem approaching from different
sides and the cross fertilization
between them was very productive
now our subject deals with control of
dynamic systems under uncertainty
okay if you could okay we are going to
be discussing control of dynamic systems
under stochastic uncertainty but the
material we are going to talk about has
extension some of which I'm going to
mention the cases where the uncertainty
is not stochastic it may be minimax
right one certainty set membership
uncertainty or or uncertainty produced
by the actions of an antagonistic
opponent as in games multistage games
but also it has it because dynamic
program is a very broadly applicable
subject it has applications way B here
on the control of dynamic systems such
as for example solving discrete
optimization problems combinatorial
optimization problems in the G program
it's an excellent support method for
solving such problems
dynamic programming has always been
recognized as having a very very broad
range of applications it was that the
algorithms were not sufficiently
powerful to deal with the applications
in the size of the applications but now
that we know how to deal with
large-scale problems there's a vast
horizon for applications in all kinds of
fields from control theory to operations
research to economics to attrition
intelligence finance and all kinds of
fields dynamic program is very general
and now that we are getting close to
being able to realize its full potential
we have a big Vista of potential payoff
regarding your methodology of the
subject it's it has a rich variety of
theory in math it also has an element of
art in it because we are dealing with
challenging problems it's important 22
to approach them in a creative way there
is also there are also issues relating
to
more abstract theoretical aspects of the
subject modeling issues how do you model
problems dynamic programming problems we
don't have time to cover all this so we
will focus primarily on algorithms okay
so here's what we will end with ever
limited the limited framework of six
lectures a state-of-the-art account of
some of the major topics at the graduate
level okay this is fairly advanced is
for graduate students primarily okay
it's a it's more over it's fast so if
you could make an effort to study this
type the slides ahead of time
read a little bit it would be good
because we are going to be going
somewhat fast and our aim is to show how
by approximation and simulation we can
address the dual process of dynamic
programming
now bellman the originator of dynamic
programming coined the term curse of
dimensionality meaning the difficulty of
addressing large dimensional problems
with the dynamic programming technique
he recognized this as a major limitation
of dynamic programming well we are going
to try to address this curse of dynamic
programming there's another curse of
dynamic programming if you want to apply
it in its exact form you need an exact
mathematical model of the system you
need equations for the system transition
probabilities and so on some systems do
not have an easily obtainable
mathematical model but instead you can
simulate them with a simulator I have a
real time simulator or computer
simulator and it turns out that we can
deal with problems like that without a
mathematical model a computer simulator
will suffice and that's part and parcel
of the nature of the techniques were
going to
gasps this here's what we're gonna cover
two lectures today and Wednesday on
exact diagnostic programming a review or
finite horizon problems but with an
emphasis on infinite horizon problems
control of a dynamic system over an
infinite number of stages and we are
going to talk about algorithms and
issues of large-scale computation with
election on Friday we are going to enter
the approximation in simulation
methodology we're going to discuss
general issues for large-scale problems
and then in the second week we are going
to discuss more specific approximate
dynamic programming techniques one
lecture an approximate policy Direction
based based on methods called temporal
differences galerkin approximation
various methods of this type one
election aggregation methods in one
lecture and q-learning and other methods
such as approximation policy space so
the first week is going to be
preparation for the second week that
doesn't mean that the first week is
going to be easy okay
just to warn you but the main research
content is going to come here in the
second week
okay so what are we going to do today
an introduction to dynamic programming
and approximate dynamic program first
focus on finite horizon problems
involving decisions in a finite number
of steps okay make a decision now then
make a decision tomorrow then again a
finite number of decisions in sequence
we're going to discuss the dynamic
programming algorithm for such finite
horizon problems the classical form of
the algorithm then we are going to turn
to infinite horizon problems and develop
some of the basic theory for the easiest
type of infinite horizon problem which
is discounted discounted problems this
kind of problems with bounded cost per
stage okay so let's get started
first of all where does dynamic
programming fit within the broad field
of optimization when I started doing
research in this field optimization was
really an exotic subject you know
something that was at the edges of
research now it has become very
fundamental all encompassing all
pervasive you can find optimization
elsewhere everywhere and this and this
there are so many different kinds of
optimization that one wants what the
what are the connections between all
these and a more abstract level there is
only one optimization problem
what you see here minimize a cost
function of a barrier would you you may
be a scaler a vector or something even
more complicated it must live within a
constrained set capital u and you want
to minimize this cost function overall
you that are admissible are in this
constraint set now depending on the
nature of G nu you have different names
the big divide is between discrete
problems will use a finite set or
continuous problems where u is not
finite and G as some continuity prop
this is differentiable for example and
so on discrete problems are the
combinatorial problems the computer
scientists like to address the integer
programming problems they have a
different character than this continuous
problems which are usually solved by
calculus type of methods or convex in
type of methods so that's one big divide
discrete and continues another big
divide is linear programming problems
and non linear programming problems
linear programming problems are the ones
linear nonlinear are continuous but in
linear G is linear and use a polyhedral
set and non when they are the ones that
are not linear linear are connected to
discrete and integer programming
problems but fundamentally they are
continuous so that's another
categorization of problems another major
categorization of problems is to divide
them between stochastic and
deterministic now stochastic problems
involve a stochastic parameter W a
random variable which is averaged in
some way by taking expectation and G the
cost function has this form here so for
a given you I have a function capital G
of U in some random variable W I average
this by taking the expected value over W
and for each you I get a number here
okay and now I minimize this number over
you so stochastic problems are really
the same as these but they involve a
stochastic element which very much
affects the type of methodology that you
need to solve them
now dynamic programming in tandem with
stochastic problems as well as
deterministic problems shall deal with
the street can deal with continuous
candy was linear and nonlinear but the
main characteristic that distinguishes
from all the others is that it is
multistage in other words I select not
just are you but are you over each one
of several stages I select a you now I
select a you tomorrow another you after
two days and so on and each time this w
this unknown random variable reveals
itself to us in the form of some
information so multiple stages following
receipt of new information okay that's a
characteristic of dynamic programming
that's unique the information about W is
rebuilding stages the decisions are also
made in stages and they make use of the
available information in other words we
have to wait to get me information in
order to make better decisions so
there's a feedback loop here between the
session and information which is
characteristic to dynamic programming
for this reasons methodology is
different kind of different people say
ask me often I have taken linear program
should I take dynamic programming is it
different what's fundamentally different
it uses different methods different
structure different mentality okay it's
it's nothing very little that you see
here in terms of methodology for these
problems resembles what you see in
dynamic programming another big
difference is that dynamic programming
focuses on global minima okay global of
globally optimal solution some of these
methods may get stuck into local minima
so so if you've taken any one of these
courses expect to hear something
different here today in this in this
course okay so if this is where it fits
and let me give you now a basic model
that we are going to be using throughout
this course we have a discrete time
dynamic system a system that evolves
over time K indexes the discrete time
and K ranges from time 0 to time n plus
minus 1 and terminates after X n is
generated okay what is this X K XK is
the state of the system what is the
state well it's hard to describe it but
in the candy some very strange things
but its main property is it summarizes
all the past information that's relevant
for future optimization in other words
the system evolves over time if we look
at its current state in order to make
future optimal decisions that's all I
need to know just the current state in
the data of the problem I don't need to
look at how the system came to this
state I don't need to look at the past
it's something that mathematically
speaking it separates the parts from the
future from the purposes of optimization
UK is the control or decision this is
what we are interested in we want to
know how to make popped in all decisions
while observing the current state W K is
a random parameter also can be viewed as
a noise in some some engineering systems
or we can call it a disturbance
depending on the context and n is what
we call horizon for the number of times
control is applied later we're going to
talk about infinite horizon problem
where n is infinity but let's focus
first at the case of a finite horizon
okay so we have a system starts at X 0
then controls applied some random W
occurs and x1 first then a new control
is applied uw2 occurs and u2 is applied
and then we'll go to x3 and so on
sequential application control it
sequential generation of states now with
every transition with each J there's a
certain cost that occurs at time K the
cost gk is the cost that is incurred
when we are at state xk applied control
UJ and also W occurs so at time 0
there's a g0 cost of the curse then a G
1 then Z 2 and all of this is added up
and at the terminal state there is
another terminal cost which we denote by
this function here these are scalar
functions real valued function these are
numbers here
however they are random numbers Y random
because no matter what what whatever you
that you put here W makes this number a
random number so the whole cost is
random even if you fix the use the
controls therefore in order to make this
meaningful criterion for optimization
you need to take expected value the
expected value here is with respect to
all the random values so if I apply some
use in here then I get a number and I
can ask the question what are the use
that make this cost minimum that's our
problem
okay now one way to describe dynamic
systems is by an equation like this this
is an alternative way but depending on
the context may be more convenient and
that is through a transition through
transition probabilities this p here is
a conditional probability that gives you
for the current value of x in the
current value of u the probability
distribution of the next state this is
an alternative but equivalent
description of a system because he come
back if I have a system like this I can
generate these transition probabilities
from this equation given the
distribution of wk I can get the
distribution of XK plus 1 alternatively
if I give you this and then you can
define a system of this form in a very
simple way consider this special
equation where XJ plus 1 is just the W
and give us distribution of W to be the
distribution of XK plus 1 this is not
going to be so important in our course
but if you see in the literature a
subject developed in terms of a model
with transition probabilities be aware
that's equivalent it can all the results
can be transformed into our forward
okay
now what I'd like to do is give you an
example of a system like this and that's
what we will do is develop the dynamic
programming algorithm for this problem
this is an inventory control problem a
warehouse where you store face and then
customers come and you sell them and
then you have to order more to replenish
and so on
[Music]
nobody ever calls me here
okay
okay so this is an inventory system okay
XJ is the stocker period J so let's say
this is a system call we store cards
exchange the number of cars at pancake
now had during this time period
K customers come and they demand a
certain wk quantity which has to be
subtracted from XK at the same time at
this period we order stock we order new
cars UK
okay that's UK and therefore the number
of the stock at period k plus one
evolves according to this equation what
we have what additional we get minus
what we give away XJ plus 1 it is an
equation of the form that I gave you a
discrete time equation at the same time
there's some cost to be paid for our
ordering decisions when I order UK then
I have to pay a certain amount C is the
price of that UK UK price per car that I
pay so I have to pay this cost and there
is also some additional cost at the end
of the period when I look at the
inventory
I want the inventory to be roughly 0
okay I don't want to have excess
inventory what I have shortage of
inventory so there is some costs
associated with having having too much
or too little at the end of the period
so that's a common formulation of the
problem minimize over any time periods
the total ordering costs plus the cost
associated with having too much or too
little inventory and my discrete time
system is this so this is an example G n
sub X n is the value of the leftover
inventory at the end okay it's it's a
problem that fits the classical form you
can take GN equals to 0 if you throw
away the final
Nitori so it's a classical example wki
random variable okay that's where the
stochastic nature of the problem comes
in UK has to obey some constraints you
cannot order negative inventory it has
to be zero or or poor positive okay
sometimes there might be constraints
that depend on the state if your
warehouse cannot hold more than a
hundred cars that you can't order more
than a hundred right but so here are
some additional assumptions in this
model the probability distribution of WK
does not depend on past values you
assume that demands are not correlated
but we may depend on XK and UK you don't
want dependence of the the uncertainty
on the past because if there was such
dependence then it would provide
information past past demands would
provide information about the current
demand and that could be exploited in in
the optimization so so to make the
formulation simpler we assumed that the
current w's do not depend on past seven
years okay now here's something that's
very important for a subject what do we
optimize over do we optimize over
sequences of orders of cars or do we
optimize over something more complex
indeed we optimize of over something
more complex called policies for
feedback control laws which are rules
that tell us how much to order given the
current value of inventory so we
optimize over functions functions of the
current state that tell us if you have a
hundred cars open or there's so much if
you have five cards or there's so much
clearly it is important to adapt our
decisions to the current information
to the current number that we have -
what has happened in the past it would
not be a good idea at the beginning of
the horizon to make all our orders all
our decisions about orders because it is
clearly useful to take advantage of
information whether we sell a lot or we
sell a little how much we have and so on
so that's a major distinction we
minimize over sequences of functions
mapping each one mapping inventory to
order so our search space is over
objects like this a function of the
initial inventory then at time one a
function of the inventory at that time
x1 all the way to the end not over
sequence of so control sequences of
workers so the search space is a lot
more complicated than this and that's
why a lot of these other techniques like
linear programming nonlinear programming
techniques do not really apply in their
entirety it's because we minimize over
feedback laws and clearly there's a lot
of benefit for doing that if we restrict
ourselves to optimize over sequences
would clearly we're not going to do as
well as if we exploit the information
okay so now we are going to go back to
the general case remember a general
problem involves a discrete-time system
state control disturbance an additive
cost function and now let's look at a
formal description we have a system of
this type we have control constraints at
each time we are restricted to choose
constraint from some set that depends on
the current state we are given the
probability distribution of W depending
on XK and UK the conditional
distribution we consider policies that
is sequence of functions each of this
news mapping state to control and these
functions must start satisfy this
control constraint and for any one of
these policies we formulate a cost that
depends on the initial state x0 and on
the policy and it is the cost incurred
if we use this policy in other words if
we plug in the control back we will use
at each one of these states then this
becomes a random number which is
averaged over all the W's and give us
this number
okay so this is the cost associated with
a policy starting at the initial state
x0 this is called the cost function of
the policy for every initial state is a
value okay so we're dealing with a
function and the dynamic programming
aims to compute the optimal cost
function given by this expression
so given this cost of policies minimize
over all policies to get J star that's
the optimal cost heart state Excel
starting from x0 it is a function of the
initial state x0 okay now here's
something interesting if you look at
this expression you would think that the
policy depends on X 0 there is no reason
superficially looking at this Y if you
plug in a different x0 here you would
use that you would use the same policy
it turns out however that because we're
dealing with functions there exists you
typically an optimal policy PI star
which satisfies this equation for all X
0 pi star the optimal policy is
independent of the initial state this
will come out as a consequence from the
dynamic programming algorithm
okay so this is a mathematical
description of a generic finite horizon
problem notice I've made no assumptions
about the spaces where this access use
and abuse live X may take values from a
Euclidean space like for example you
have a car on airplane moving in space
okay
typically the motion of this plane is
defined by six state values okay the
positions the three coordinates of the
position and the three coordinates of
the velocity so X is six numbers okay
for such a port for such a motion and X
lives in six dimensional space a
continuous space however there are other
problems where X lives in a much simpler
space like a discrete space a finite
space think for example of a queuing
system a queuing system where typically
the state is the number of customers
that are in the queue assuming that your
queue has a finite number of spaces for
customers then you have a finite number
of states a very different much simpler
space you could have a network of queues
which is more complicated multiple
queues and then the Cartesian product of
finite sets still a finite set the nice
thing about dynamic programming is that
it's spirit does not depend on where the
main barrier to live whether they live
in a continuous phase where a discrete
space the same reasoning the same
algorithms apply ok that's a big thing
because makes the techniques the
technique very general
similarly the control can be in a
Euclidean space can be in a finite set
like an on/off decision and the same
thing with W
okay there's something called principle
optimality people attribute to it
magical magical qualities lives indeed
at the heart of our dynamic programming
algorithm but it's also a trivial
statement a very very simple statements
and it it may surprise you that it is
the foundation on which just about all
of dynamic programming is is built what
is the principle of optimality the name
by the way is due to bellman principle
man's associate bellman he was the one
who who put it forth and showed that
underlies many different models and
algorithms dynamic programming type ok
what's the principle of optimality
remember that we are looking for an
optimal policy a Pollock's is a sequence
of functions suppose we have an optimal
sequence of functions which are called P
star PI star okay now let's our problem
starts at time 0 and goes all the way to
time and write a finite horizon suppose
that I look at a subproblem whereby I
have arrived at some intermediate state
X K at time K and I look at the tail
problem of how to go from XK to the end
optimally ok so I have an optimal policy
for the entire problem and I also have
formulated state sub problems which
involve the same system the same control
constraints and so on and we assume that
we are at X K at time K and we wish to
minimize the cost to go from here to the
end
what is this cost to go it is the sum of
the states course starting at time K to
the end and having also this terminal
cost so
the total cost and the tail sub-problems
costs and the principle of math is the
following rather obvious things think
the tail policy okay
this is the tail policy that starts from
XK to the end the tail portion of this
optimal policy is also optimal for the
tail sub problem in other words if I
find myself at XK using this optimal
policy and someone tells me forget about
the past
do optimally from here to the future
then I would continue to use the optimal
policy the tail portion of PI star is
optimal for this problem now the idea is
that dynamic program is solved
simultaneously all the tail sub problems
doesn't solve just the problem of going
optimally from here to here starting
from a given initial State but it also
solves all the tail subproblems no
matter what well you may end up at any
intermediate State XK find an optimal
policy for this tail sub problem so all
of them simultaneously and all of them
can be put together their optimal policy
into a single big policy how does it do
that
at the generic step it solves all the
tails are problems of given time length
using the solution of the tail
subproblems of shorter time lengths okay
very simple idea let me explain it we
start over here one step to the end we
solve this tail sub problem then we go
to two steps from the end and we solve
this state sub problem but the solution
simplifies because we have already
solved the shorter tails our problem
then we go to three three three steps
and using the solution for the two steps
and keep going backwards until we get to
the end that's the dynamic programming
algorithm is this principle or melody
here clear and any questions that you
might want to ask just to give one more
example suppose that I want to start
there I want to go by car from my home
which is in Massachusetts in the United
States I want to go to California the
opposite cause got Los Angeles and
suppose that I calculate the optimal
route the fastest route and it goes
through Chicago okay so I have this
route suppose now that I fly to Chicago
and I want to find the shortest route by
car from Chicago to Los Angeles what
would be the optimal route well it would
be the tail portion of the route that I
would have taken had I started from
Massachusetts shorter tail portions or
fruits are optimal of optimal overall
routes are optimal for the tail
subproblems
okay so now let's give the dynamic
programming algorithm
let us
let us call JK of XJ the optimal cost of
the tail subproblem that starts at xj
now we want to have an algorithm that
gives this JK and I start from this
initial condition at the very end the
last tails a problem where I'd landed at
XJ this is next and there's not nothing
to optimize this is the cost and now we
go backwards one step at a time having
computed JK plus one the optimal cost of
the tail subproblem starting at the next
state we add the cost of the additional
of the current stage and we minimize the
sum of the two so given all the JK plus
once I calculate all the JK's Nibin all
the xn I calculate J and minus one for
every possible value of the state then J
n minus 2 J n minus 3 all the way to 0
in other words the interpretation the
word interpretation of this equation is
to solve the tail subproblem at time J i
minimize the sum of the cave stage cost
plus the optimal cost of the next pain
problem starting from the next day at
time k plus 1 now this is an algorithm
that a computer can understand you give
it an initial function this GN and it
cracks out she has a black box that
tracks out functions into functions k
plus 1 functions to K and then UK minus
1 and so on
each time generating a function
okay now I see what happened I forgot an
extra slide in here okay
here we are here's the algorithm to
solve the ten subproblem at time k we do
this and then at time zero we have jay-z
rows of x0 generate the flag step and it
is equal to the optimal cost because the
last tail problem is the original
problem so J 0 sub X 0 as generated by
this algorithm is exactly J star also if
I record the minimum the you that
attains the minimum in each X at each X
K and K I will obtain a sequence of
functions of state where at XK new case
of XK minimizes in the right hand side
this equation so this algorithm
simultaneously gives me the solute the
optimal cost of the tail subproblems and
also an optimal policy by minimization
in the right hand side and actually the
proof of this is very simple just by
induction you assume that this is JK
plus 1 is the optimal possibly takes a
problem you prove the same property for
JK it's it's not going to go into the
proof of this but you may be able to
just on the base of attrition figure it
out yourselves it's also what you can
find in the sources
so that's the algorithms have any
questions here
yes some go forward okay the question is
whether you can execute this algorithm
going backwards going forward rather
than backward it turns out that you can
execute it going forward but only for a
special class of problems problems where
there is no uncertainty where
deterministic problems where the W's
take a single known value then we can
sort of reverse the direction of time
and developed of the same algorithm but
with fine reversed and so forward out
there however there is no forward
algorithm for stochastic problems it's
just not possible to do it
probably the variables we can optimize
the objective over functions
No
to find a perhaps you can you can
approximate this algorithm and do things
in a different world but to get the
optimal solution with no alternative
really to this yes okay you're taking me
five lectures forward what's the
difference between this algorithm and
q-learning to learning is is an
algorithm that uses sampling okay it
does not calculate expected values like
here instead it uses samples of W so
it's an algorithm that's that's more
complicated more general and I think it
ties in with us with a connection
between dynamic programming and
simulation we're going to get into this
in the fair amount of detail next week
so I'd rather wait until then yes
why is it white spiced are independent
well because you're solving all the
tails subproblems in this way and it
comes out to be what you get is
something that works for every initial
state it's the nature of the algorithm
that
it is for okay so this is optimal for
the entire thing is optimal for any
initial state and every pain portion is
also optimal for the tale problems okay
just because dynamic programming needs
to find the optimal policy of all the
tales have problems at the given stage
so at the end it also solves all that
the poldek all the original problems
from any initial state yes
that's why we live far away they can't
figure out it so I can't admit other
types of course function okay so the
question is that here we have a problem
defined as as with an expected cost
problem it's possible to have a
different kind of problem like a max the
maximum over some of over the W square W
is given by some kind of set description
what W may be chosen by an antagonistic
opponent there is a dynamic programming
algorithm for such problems as well and
the rationale is similar and I'm going
to touch upon it a little later but for
support for simplicity and specificity
in this course I'm going to focus on
expected values however they there are
there are generalizations certainly yes
which ended under so small Hey
and
define a problem or smaller for isin you
mean and consider that well we do that
basically right we look at all the
problems of smaller horizon in the
process okay J and minus 1 this pertain
here and so on
JK is obtained here so we solve all the
intermediate problems with this
algorithm ok I'd like to take a break
I think 2 hours is too much for for me
and I'm sure for Yuko and so what I'd
like to do is every 35 minutes or so
give or take 5-10 minutes take a break
for 10 minutes and then you have a
chance to digest correlate questions and
rest a little bit and I have to say so
let's break and get back in exactly 10
minutes please