okay can you hear me everything okay
okay good so I'd like to welcome you to
this second lecture second out of six on
approximate hoops approximate dynamic
programming last time we talked about
exact dynamic programming first finite
horizon problems over n stages and then
infinite horizon problems over an
infinite number of stages and we focused
on discounted problems and we are going
to review this discounted infinite
horizon formulation and I introduced
some shorthand notation also and then
after we do this review we're going to
focus on algorithms for exact discounted
DP value iteration various forms of
policy direction one particular type of
it of policy direction which I call
optimistic which is going to come up
again in the future
then I'm going to talk about Q factors
in Q learning and introduction to these
but we'll revisit them later as well
then we're going to talk about various
models other than discounted in this
short course we're going to focus almost
exclusively on discounted problems which
are the easiest class of problems they
give you the strongest results not other
models may not have a strong results but
we discounted problems provide a
benchmark of the best that you can
achieve and it's a good starting point
for us and we're going to follow that
but we are going to introduce some other
disk dynamic programming problems
including some that are continuous space
in continuous time then we are going to
close this overview of exact dynamic
programming with a couple of more
advanced topics the first has to do
the more abstract view of dynamic
programming that allow us to allows us
to develop the theory simultaneously in
a unified way for all these models not
just for discounted but for all of them
in look in a more fundamental way as to
whether as to why some results hold for
some models and not for others the last
topic I want to touch upon briefly is a
synchronous algorithms where you either
have a parallel computing system
executing value or policy duration or we
have a simulation driven algorithm where
not all states are treated at the same
time it's a certain a synchronous a
synchronous character to these
algorithms and it turns out that they
work both policy duration and value
iteration when appropriately implemented
they work in a synchronous format so
that's where we're going and we're going
to start with a review remember in
infinite horizon in an inner equation
setting we have a stationary system
which gives you the next state at time k
plus 1 given the current state the
control that you apply in the random
quantity which we call disturbance or
noise whatever you want to call it it
operates starting from 0 going to 1 2
and so on an infinite number of stages
at each stage there is a cost that is
incurred that depends on state control
in this disturbance now we are looking
at policies policies are sequences of
functions one function for each time
stage and this function Maps States into
controls so we observe the state and the
control function is a rule that tells us
what control to apply so we are looking
for sequences of such feedback control
functions this museum new one and so on
now once we plug in such a policy into
the cost function which by the way is
discounted by
alpha which is less than one in a
discounted problem then we get a random
number
all this discounted costs added up over
an infinite number of stages give you a
random number random because they depend
on this double use here we take the
expected value over this double use and
the limit as n goes to infinity and we
get a number which is the cost of policy
pi starting at the initial state x0 so
for one state I have one cost for
another state I have a different cost
and so on so this J pi is a function of
the state into the real numbers now one
assumption that's critical for these
discounted problems in addition to the
fact that alpha is less than 1 is that
the cost per stage is bounded in other
words there is a number M that provides
an upper bound to the absolute value of
the cost for any X U and W the effect of
this the mathematical effect of this is
that it makes this series here summable
summable to a real number ok
because G's bonded alpha K is
geometrically going to 0 and the whole
series is converging to a real number so
J pi is a real valued function ok
because there are some other
implications which I'm going to get into
that for this assumption of boundedness
but let me first remind you of the
shorthand notation that I introduced for
dynamic programming mappings now we are
dealing here with functions of state and
the dynamic programming algorithm both
for financialization and also it's
infinite horizon version takes functions
and produces other functions now these
other functions are denoted by T J so T
is a box some abstract box that takes a
function and produces another function
through this operation now let me review
this operation for you it involves
at state X the first-stage cost and the
cost from the next state onward as
measured by the function J that we are
operating on this expected value is a
number minimize over all you and that
gives you the value of TJ's of X it is
the optimal cost for a one-stage problem
involving this one stage cost plus a
cost to go a final cost at the end of
the stage okay now this is the mapping
this is dynamic programming dynamic
programming starts with some J produces
TJ t square J the square J is T applied
on TJ t cube J which is T applied on T
squared J and so on and so clearly it's
a very important operation and it turns
out to be very fundamental as well so
that's no notation and it's much better
to work with this expression than with
that expression can get pretty pretty
complicated okay now suppose that you
have a fixed policy new and let's say
the policy stationary stationary points
are very important here stationary
policies are pies for which mu does not
change the same new at time 0 sine U at
time 1 and so on so a stationary
policies new Miu Miu Miu ok and if you
plug it in here for a given J it gives
you another function team use of J this
is the one stage cost of applying mu at
the first stage and then getting a
terminal cost associated with J so these
two are similar but this is for a single
policy and this is for all policies the
minimum over all policies okay so this
is the shorthand notation and a nice
thing about the shorthand notation it
can give it it gives you the possibility
to describe the entire theory of this
in a couple of slides so this is the
shorthand theory Bellman's equation J
star the optimal cost function that
we're looking for satisfies this
equation J star is equal to t J star it
says that J star is a fixed point of the
mapping T more analytically it's this
equation here this equation is one
equation for each state okay so this is
a functional equation an equation
satisfied by the whole function J star
ok so so if you have if X takes a finite
number of values I'm sorry yeah if there
are only a finite number of states 1 up
to n there are n equations here J starts
of 1 J star of 2 and so on so this
becomes a vector equation but generally
it's a functional equation in this
equation is his for J star and there's
another equation for J mu and we showed
last time that J star is the unique
solution of this equation where is J mu
for any stationary mu is the unique
solution of this equation that's the
first fundamental result the second
result is that if I give you J star and
you minimize in this expression here and
get a policy in this way then this
policy is optimal
it's an optimality condition find J star
and then minimize in this expression or
equivalently find mu such that team U
and J star equals TJ star if you find
such a mutant is optimal conversely if
you have an optimal mu then it must
satisfy this equation this is an if and
only if condition
the third major result is about the
method of value iteration value
iteration starts with J any J that is
bounded generates TJ by applying this
mapping here with the T mapping then
generates this T squared J T cube J and
so on in the limit value iteration has
the property that it converges to the
optimal value function some major
algorithm for calculating J star and of
course we want to calculate J star
because this will also give us optimal
policies so we prove this convergence
last time or almost proved it and
there's a second major algorithm policy
direction which we described but we did
not show its validity last time in
policy direction instead of generating
cost functions JT JT squared J and so on
we generate policies we start with some
policy nu 0 and then generate another
policy new one another policy me 2 and
so on so here's the typically duration
of policy duration given a stationary
policy mu J we find the cost of that
policy and this cost is obtained as a
fixed point of the mapping team you this
is called policy evaluation so we solve
this functional equation here for MU for
a given u K find J nu K and then we find
new k plus 1 that satisfies this
equation
in other words attains the minimum in
this expression when J star is replaced
by J nu J this is called policy
improvement now policy duration value
duration is going to be very important
for us approximate versions of those are
the
and so on of approximate dynamic
programming so we're going to get back
to them quite frequently and but for the
moment we have been looking at V at the
exact versions we showed convergence of
this and a few slides were going to look
into this and show convergence of that
as well okay now what are the major
properties that make the theory work
what is at the foundations of all the
proofs and arguments and justifications
it turns out that the fundamental
properties are embedded in this mappings
T and T Mew the first major property is
that both T and T mu if I can take you
back here are monotone if I increase J
by a certain amount uniformly from J I
take it up by some amount then TJ is
also going to increase okay it's evident
because it's a plus sign here similarly
for Tim you it is monotone so that's
that's a property that's very very basic
and very important it's very simple but
still very important for any function J
and J Prime on the state space one
bigger than the other then if you apply
T to them to both of them being equality
is preserved and similarly 14 you now
just about all dynamic programming
models have this monotonicity property
it's it's part and parcel structure of
these problems however for discounted
problems there's another very important
property that is responsible for the
good nature good character of these
problems
what makes discounted problems be
relatively easy and having a strong
theory is that in addition to
monotonicity there is a contraction
property lurking in which we have
already discussed and it says that for
any bounded functions J and
prime then the distance between jet
between J and J prime as measured by
this expression here by the maximum
distance between the two this distance
is reduced when you apply T to these two
functions applying T to J into J Prime
brings them closer in this sense by a
factor alpha alpha remember is a
discount factor less than 1 similarly
there's another property similar for MU
of per team you square this and now if
you want to translate it in even more
compact notation introduce a norm
introduce a norm on the space of
functions J which is the maximum
magnitude okay so you have a function
take the maximum magnitude and that's
the norm of the function and what in
terms of this norm this properties here
translate are equivalent to in shorthand
to this that the norm between j TJ and
TJ prime is less than alpha times the
north between J and J Prime in
mathematical terms
this says that T is a contraction
mapping on the space of functions J and
similarly Tim use a contraction mapping
now contraction mappings have great
properties and that's why I discarded
problems also have great properties okay
all of this is review up to now and
let's go into the algorithms one is
value iteration we discussed that it
works for any starting function J in his
policy duration given mu K evaluate new
K in other words find its cost function
by solving the corresponding functional
equation the bellman equation
corresponding to new K in shorthand it
is like this
in longhand it is like this okay then
after you calculate this cost function
of mu J you improve muche by finding
another policy mu k plus 1 by minimizing
in this expression so notice you have
already calculated Jamie okay you plug
it in here and for every state X you do
this minimization and you obtain a
minimal a controller that is the minimum
and that's your new policy you can write
this expression in longhand or in
shorthand it's like this as you can
verify so that's policy direction and
now before we go into justifying this
policy direction let's make an
observation suppose that you have n
states okay not n dimensional system and
states 1 2 up to n so there n costs
associate will Jane you J nu is a vector
J nu 1 at state 1 2 and so on up to n so
this J Musa vector when you evaluate J
mu using this equation you need to solve
a linear system of equations there is
one equation here for each X so there
are n equations with n unknowns which
are the components of this J mu K and
this is a linear equation why is it
linear well this is a constant term here
and this is a term which involves this
expectation now expectation is a linear
operation right - right the expectation
of a random variable you just write the
product the weighted product of the
values of the random variable with the
prop corresponding probabilities so this
is a linear operation over here so you
have n linear equations with n unknowns
and you can write the system compactly
like so this is a vector equation
involving this constant vector involving
this matrix here
alpha P mu and P mu is the so-called
transition probability matrix associated
with mu let's not go into the details of
that it is the matrix that comes out
from this equation so you have a vector
J nu here which is the unknown another
vector which is the unknown and this is
a linear equation a matrix equation that
you can solve by inversion okay you
solve the code you invert the
corresponding matrix and you get the
solution in this way so mathematically
speaking this is a very simple operation
the policy evaluation is a very simple
operation in practice however it's not
so simple and the reason is that if you
have a large number of states let alone
if you have infinite number of states
even if you have a finite number of
states but if n is large and I'm talking
really large here zillions and trillions
and a huge number think of the hugest
number that she can think more than the
number of of molecules in the entire
universe a gigantic number then it is
impossible to solve this equation by
giving it to MATLAB okay you can't do
that the memory requirements are too big
the computational requirements are too
big so even though we are going to show
shortly that this policy duration
terminates in a finite number of steps
applying it is out of the question
applying it exactly you can't you can't
apply it in practice you have to do some
kind of an approximation now the type of
approximation that you we will use often
and I'm going to get into that later is
to solve this equation here iteratively
not exactly by matrix inversion but
iteratively by using value iteration use
value iteration to solve this equation
approximately with just a few iterations
okay so instead of solving exactly solve
it approximately in there are many many
kind of
approximations we can use including
solution by value iteration okay so now
what we would like to do is take a look
at why this policy Direction method
works it turns out that the most
important thing about it is that there
is policy improvement in other words you
have the current policy new K you have
its cost the cost function of the next
policy is better is smaller so it
uniformly decreases the cost function
with every iteration and the proof of
this is a few lines which I'll give you
here what we want to show is that with
every direction I get a cost function
that's less than what I had before a
better policy now I could get the two of
them to be equal but in that case I will
have an optimal policy so I will show
that either you have strict improvement
at every direction or you have optimal
'ti and here's the proof for a given
equation suppose we are at the direction
K then we know that we that but that
that the policy evaluation equation
holds J mu J satisfies this equation
when I minimize this expression here in
involved in key against J mu J I get
something that's smaller and by policy
improvement I have that this is equal to
that okay
so just from the definition of the
method I have that when you apply T mu K
+ 1 to j nu K it takes it down so you
start with general K applying P mu K + 1
I get something that smaller apply it
again and again get something smaller
and you get convergence to something so
that's due to the monotonicity property
J mu K is less than this here apply mu K
plus 1 again
and then again and you get a
monotonically decreasing sequence and in
the limit you get by value iteration you
get J mu k plus 1 so that's that genu K
is greater than J near k plus 1 it's two
lines proof okay now if the two are
equal then equality holds throughout
here which which among other shows that
J nu K sauce balance equations the T
equation because it's a teeth some pony
yeah have equality here therefore J mu K
is equal to J star so in the end I did
eration K I've every algorithm generates
a strictly improved policy strict
inequality in at least one state or else
it finds an optimal policy now this is
true for an arbitrary state space if you
have a finite spaces and D P or a finite
state MVP then the algorithm terminates
with an optimal policy why is that going
to put up for a finite space SMTP finite
number of states final number of
controls at each state
how many policies are there altogether
the finite number finite number of
policies at every direction I have
strict improvement or else optimality
therefore termination in a finite number
of steps with an optimal policy if you
have an infinite state space then you
can show convergence asymptotic in an
infinite number of iterations that's a
little trickier to show but it is true
okay so this policy duration method has
very solid properties for the discounted
problem
okay now there is we mentioned value
duration as one algorithm and then
policy direction and the fact that
sometimes it's better to use a few
directions of a few value iterations to
evaluate a policy rather than to
evaluate it exactly because we may have
a very large number of states this is
called optimistic policy iteration it is
policy duration where the policy
evaluation is done approximately with a
few directions with a few value
iterations so here it is optimistic
policy duration
this is policy duration where the policy
evaluation is done approximately the
finite number of valid directions so we
approximate J nu with a few it value
directions involving mu starting from
any J M can be one in which case we
turns out that we get value iteration
algorithm or it could be two three any
number M equals infinity is exact policy
direction so this optimistic is is this
optimistic method is intermediate
between the two extremes value and
policy duration and in practice it works
better than both and experimentally this
has been verified the some analysis that
indicates that and you can think of
extreme cases where it would be better
than either one it's not difficult to do
that there's a shorthand notation for
this for this method since I'm big on
shorthand notations I have it here and
you can see what it is this is the
policy improvement in aeration and this
is the policy evaluation direction
involving Mk number of value iterations
and for MK ungentle equal to one you can
verify that this exactly value duration
for MK infinity it becomes policy
direction you can show convergence for
both finite and infinite space
discounted problems
in the case of in both cases both in
fine and in play if you can shoot an
infinite number of directions you need
an infinite number of directions because
for the special case where M K is equal
to 1 it becomes very duration and value
iteration requires an infinite number of
iterations typically it works faster
than badly duration in Polish duration
particularly for large problems when we
are going to talk about approximations
later an approximate policy duration
it's always some kind of optimistic
method that you are using we never use
the two extremes what very seldom we use
the extreme of value duration and never
exact policy duration in approximate
dynamic programming ok let's say one
more thing about policy duration with an
eye to the future starting in the next
lecture we're going to be talking about
approximations and we're going to be
talking about approximate versions of
this policy duration algorithm so let's
have a preview of that and what's the
basis for that ok so well then we have
approximations they can be
approximations in two ways the policy
evaluation may be approximate in the
sense that instead of computing the cost
of a policy we compute some other
function JK which is uniformly within
Delta this is the maximum norm so the
maximum distance by value distance
between JK and J mu K is bound by Delta
so I have this J nu K that I want to
evaluate but instead I using something
that's within Delta uniformly from that
Delta is some number whatever it is okay
so this is approximate policy evaluation
and suppose also that the policy
improvements approximate so when I take
the minimum in in in in the minimization
operation corresponding to JK that I
have that
I don't find the exact minimum but
rather something that's within epsilon
of the minimum so policy improvement is
exact within Epsilon okay so both of
these approximations of course throw off
the convergence
you can't expect convergence to be exact
optimum but what you have is a bound the
bound says that the sequence of policies
generated by this approximate policy
duration method satisfies this
inequality so these policies do not
converge to anything that's optimal but
come to within this factor this number
this bound from the optimal okay so the
optimal is somewhere over here and I get
something that's higher than that but by
no more than this now epsilon is what
you'd be approximation involved in the
policy improvement Delta is the
approximation the error involved in the
policy evaluation and there is a factor
1 minus alpha squared in the denominator
alpha is the discount factor this factor
in the denominator worrisome because
alpha may be something like okay point
nine nine okay very close to one and
this denominator is going to cause this
bound to be very high it turns out that
you can find specialized examples where
this inequality is sharp okay however
typically in practice this bound is
conservative and what you get is you
start out typical behavior in practice
you start out with some initial policy
and you have some cost functions like
like that then you apply one step of
approximate policy direction you get
something that's lower and lower and
lower up until you get to within some
zone from the optimum
you get in there you sort of bounce back
okay
the method does not converge it just
oscillates within this zone here that's
the typical behavior in practice and
this zone is not as high it's not as big
as this bound suggests it is something
typically smaller there's another bound
that I want to mention if this sequence
of policies terminates at some policy mu
bar in other words you get to some point
and you keep generating the same policy
it's not going to be optimal it's going
to be optimal within some error bound
and this error bound is this here and it
is better by a factor of 1 minus alpha
than this other bound there are some
approximate policy duration methods for
which you can guarantee termination and
have this better error bound there are
some others where you cannot guarantee
termination you get oscillation
generically and then and then this is
this bound here that that is in effect
now you should not take this bounce too
seriously okay they are not quantitative
bounds that you can use you can't first
of all you cannot guarantee that you get
when you do approximate evaluation who
knows what this Delta is you can't get a
hold on on numerical value of Delta
similarly you cannot get a hold of you
numerical value of epsilon and less
epsilon is equal to zero okay and then
so since Delta is unknown you can't
really say much about that's
quantitative using this bounce all you
can say is that at least the method does
not explode does not go unstable its
stable within some bounds okay it's not
going to explode on you which is not
very much but it's something it's not
quite negligible okay because there are
methods that do approximations and then
they explode as
as the overtime okay so that's a good
point to take a little break
are there any questions about policy
direction we have done policy direction
so far and now we're going to go into Q
factors and we have closed the subject
for the moment of policy direction at
least exact and have any questions yes
yeah your question has to do with this
optimistic policy direction okay I'm
telling you that it's typically works
faster than value duration and policy
duration but can you prove it the answer
is that there are some partial results
that that that you can interpret them as
faster convergence the most convincing
evidence is really the practical
evidence there is the theoretical
results are not so definitive there are
some but they are not definitive it's
mostly based on practice but it is a
sure thing okay you can have no doubt
about it
yes
okay equals 1 MK is equal an integer 1
or greater yeah positive
I'm not sure I understand what you mean
should be positive okay okay no I don't
think you're right okay your question is
the following suppose that M K is equal
to infinity then I claim that this this
relation here
gives you this relation gives you J nu K
plus 1 okay because you do an infinite
number of it M K goes to infinity so
this the sequence converges to J mu K J
mu K I'm sorry J nu K so so this is
exact policy evaluation and therefore
when followed by policy improvement you
get the policy duration I think it's
correct as it is okay
in the last slide the last slide here
second equation it's you know it's G
second it's policy yes ah there's a typo
here and it should be m'kay
okay you're right here's M superscript K
yes you're right yeah it's a type of
I'll correct it as I as was mentioned
earlier this slides change up to five
minutes before the lecture so sometimes
there are some mistakes and even though
we are posting slides before the lecture
for you to take a look at at the end of
the lecture I make corrections to typos
and post them again okay so let's take a
break for ten minutes and then we'll
come back and continue