that inbox or you to the team is on time
sorry about the problems that we've been
having with equipment and let me welcome
you to this third lecture on this series
of six lectures on approximate dynamic
programming we spent the first two
lectures to to discuss exact dynamic
programming with an emphasis on
discounted cost problems which are the
easiest ones we are going to review
these problems to start this lecture and
then we are going to go into we are
going to go into approximate dynamic
programming today's lecture is the
purpose of today's lectures overview
I'll give you an overview the bigger
picture of the subject and then next
week we're going to pick up various
parts of this picture and we're going to
go into greater depth so today it's
going to be sometimes not quite very
detailed description
I just won't want to describe the whole
field to you and then I'll point out
what the major points are the major
areas where one needs to pay attention
what were to discuss our oxidation
architectures to to introduce
approximations you need to have some
parametric forms and that's what this
approximation architectures are then I'm
going to discuss the politics iteration
method which we saw earlier in the
previous lectures but with
approximations and also using simulation
and we are going to discuss why do we
need simulation why simulation so
important in this field we're going to
focus on methods of approximate policy
evaluation which is the first the first
part of a policy duration and then we're
going to talk about some issues of
policy improvement as well and close
with a few
discussion of a few general issues on
approximation methods so let's go with a
few slides slides of review we are
considering dynamic systems who state is
X K at time K we consider the systems
over an infinite horizon and now the
systems evolve according to an equation
a discrete time equation where the new
state is obtained from the current state
the control that you apply this UK and
some random quantity wk there are some
assumptions associated with that we
disturbed the VW cake which we call
disturbance or noise the probability
distribution of that depends only on XK
and UK and not on previous stuff the
Markov property that that we assume here
and and we are interested in policies
policies are functions of state to
control there are rules that tell us at
every state what control to apply so
once we have this new we know how to do
that and that's the objective to obtain
such a sequence of Meuse such that the
corresponding cost is minimized so if we
plug in one of these PI's the sequence
of control functions there is a cost
associated with each stage at stage K
because G depends on XK the control that
you apply and the random disturbance so
this is a random number the discount
factor alpha between 0 and 1 which keeps
this thing bounded and let's say future
costs here are discounted heavily so
that the future doesn't count as much as
the present mathematically this is good
because it allows us to define this as a
real number this causes a real number
now each one of these terms here is a
random the sum is also random and we
take the expected value of that over W
and becomes a number
and we take the limit of this series as
over over an infinite number of stages
and that gives us the cost of policy by
starting at state x0 so for one state we
have a course another state another
costs a whole function associate with
this policy and we want to make this
function of course as low as possible by
optimal choice of Pi ok now with the
double some shorthand notation associate
the first thing is this mapping that
takes functions into functions this
appears in the dynamic programming
algorithm is very basic so to a given J
it provides it will produce another
function T sub J and also there's a
corresponding mapping for a certain
policy stationary policy station reports
are important of course because in
infinite horizon problems optimal
policies can usually be found within
policies that do not change over time
and this is the mapping T mu associated
with a policy means given by this
expression okay now we have been talking
the nice thing about this formulation is
that it applies to very general systems
arbitrary state space arbitrary control
space arbitrary disturbance space
it's very general however most of the
work in approximate dynamic programming
and also within this course is going to
assume a simpler system a system that
has n states in other words a Markov
chain with a finite number of states N
and we are going to it's convenient to
switch to Markov chain notation so the
states can be either 1 2 up to n and I
will use the symbol I to denote the
state as opposed to X ok so if you see I
that means a discrete state finite
number of states if you see X that means
I have discrete or continuous or
whatever and instead of the system
equation I'm going to use also
transition probability notation which I
mentioned in last week that in the
earlier lectures that's an equivalent
way of representing a system so this P I
ki k plus 1 is the probability when you
are at state I K to go at the next state
at state i ka plus 1 under the influence
of control you change the transition
probabilities depend on UK and they are
a substitute to the system equation if
you're given a system equation like that
then you can obtain transition
probabilities through the problems
tribution of W the cost is going to be
denoted again with I notation as opposed
to X notation and so this is cost
associated with going from state I K to
study IJ plus 1 with control UK cost
functions now are functions of a finite
number of qualities there are only a
finite number of points where this
function is defined so a J is a vector
an N dimensional vector a vector in RN
with components J 1 up to J N and the
cost of a policy again is transcribed in
terms of the discrete notation and the
mappings can also be described like so
expected value over this one stage cost
plus cost to go is obtained by taking
the transition probabilities and adding
over those transition probabilities
similarly for team you so instead of
expectation I have waited summation with
the transition probabilities equivalent
notation for discrete systems discrete
state systems okay so the theory and
will go on to the throat one more time J
star is the optimal cost vector for an
end-state prop system it is an N
dimensional vector is the optimal cost
that's what we want to find and it
satisfies the system of equations it's
the unique solution of this bellman
equation the unknowns are J 1 up to
Julian it's n equations with n unknowns
nonlinear because this minimization over
you if you have a fixed policy then this
J news are a vector which is the unique
solution of this system of equations and
this system of equations is linear so if
you want to find J mu for a given policy
you have to solve this linear system of
equations and the optimality condition
is that the policy is optimal if and
only if the policy attains the minimum
in Bellman's equation with J star here
ok
that's an if and only if condition and
we can also we also have two fundamental
algorithms value direction and policy
direction and value iteration starts
from any vector in our end and applies
the T mapping to it
this dynamic programming operator again
and again and again and in the limit it
has the property that no matter where
you start you converge to J star so
that's one basic method for exact
dynamic programming and the second
method is policy direction given a
stationary policy new k and you start to
some arbitrary poles new 0 but given the
typical policy new k in the algorithm
you evaluate it by solving this system
of equations which is balanced equation
for the cost vector of that policy again
a linear system as I mentioned in
abstract notation is given like this in
longhand limitations given like this you
can solve it in any way that's
convenient and then you improve the
policy by finding a new policy that
attains the minimum in this expression
or in shorthand notation this it's this
expression here so start with mu 0
compute new one evaluate mu 0 compute me
1 that Wallis improvement new
then evaluate that new - and so on and
for a finite number of states we have
shown last time that that it converges
to an optimal policy in a finite number
of directions and some of the points
that are important here is that policy
evaluation is equivalent to solving a
linear system of equations however for
large end and these are the problems
that we are interested in large systems
with a large number of states you cannot
really solve this system of equations
exactly because it has two large
dimensions and the alternative perhaps
the only alternative is to use use some
value iteration for this system here
apply T nu repeatedly to what you have
as a valuation of chainu and then the
evaluation of genuine approximate but
still the method works this is the
optimistic policy Direction method where
the policy evaluation is done with a few
value iterations okay so now approximate
dynamic programming amounts to
introducing approximations and and
obtaining approximate versions of this
algorithms that I sort of make sense and
that's what it is for the most part okay
so now let me give you a broad
description or approximate dynamic
programming it dates to the late 80s and
it arose out of real need belmont coined
the term curse of dimensionality for
dynamic programming many problems could
be addressed in theory but in practice
they were too big for the computers of
the day or for any computers of the
present or for any computers of the
future in fact approximations became a
necessity in order to solve problems and
then real problems and then people
started looking more systematically
proclamations and there were several
strands of research that originated in
different parts of the scientific
scientific community in artificial
intelligence it the name of the field
this is reinforcement learning
enforcement learning is a natural
evolution of an old field people have
been talking about reinforcement
learning artificial intelligence in the
early days in the 50s and now this came
in as the idea of of adjusting policy as
a result of observation and reinforcing
the good actions relative to the bad
actions this is something that's
ingrained in the field of artificial
intelligence and so there is this name
there for smart learning and a lot of
interesting ideas came from that field
new dynamic program is the name of one
of your textbooks it's a name that I've
introduced with the joneses checklist in
our book and and it means just about the
same thing but we had a different
orientation we're not computer
scientists were not artificial
intelligence people we are control and
optimization operations research people
we have a more mathematical viewpoint
and and so it's a different direction to
some of the same problems but
substantially different attitude their
methodology came out from these two
sides of the field finally there's a
third third line of research called
unfortunately ADP also but it doesn't
mean approximate dynamic programming
it means adaptive dynamic programming
and came from came from the field of
adaptive control adaptive control has to
do with controlling systems for which
you don't know an exact model however
some unknown parameters like for example
a robot may move something from here to
here but the dynamics of the robot may
be unpredictable may depend for example
on the weight of the finger the carries
okay and so adaptive control tries to
find the control policies good control
policies that are independent of the
model but model free operation is also
part and parcel of this approximate
dynamic approximate dynamic programming
field so that's where the common points
where in adaptive operation and there
have been contributions from that side
of the field as well and there are
substantial groups working on this in
every part of the world including
including China okay we will focus on
end State discounted problems which is
the easiest case to address however you
got to think of a huge number of states
one possibility is to have a continued
state space which you discretize with
many points that's one way to get a few
state space I will show you other
examples of huge state space that arise
in other ways while we are going to
focus on finite state discounted
problems a lot of the ideas apply to
other kinds of dynamic programming cop
models continued space continues time
and discounted and extensions are
possible but there are they're a little
bit not quite as easy as for discounted
problems and we may discuss selectively
some of those later now for
approximations there are several
approaches one approach that is quite
useful at times is the following you
have a certain problem that's very
difficult very complicated complicated
dynamics large state space whatever and
then you construct an approximation of
that problem you neglect some of the
difficult dynamics you simplify some
things here some things there you obtain
a simpler problem related to the
original which you can solve
by an exact method if you can solve the
simpler problem by an exact method you
can use the cost function of that
problem as a substitute for the cost
function the optimal cost function of
the more difficult problem in balanced
equation and obtained and a policy that
sub optimal because it does not use the
true optimal cost but rather the
approximation obtained through this
simpler problem so that's called problem
approximation there are many many
applications of that kind and but we're
not going to go into that except in very
small ways we are going to focus
primarily on approaches that are based
on simulation and there are three major
types that use simulation one is a roll
out a simple and very effective
technique that I discussed in the
previous two lectures I'm not going to
say anything further about that the
other two approaches that we are going
to talk about our approximation in value
space where we approximate the j
function okay we try to find an
approximate version of that through
through a parameterization and the other
is to approximate directly an optimal
policy you introduce approximations into
the policy and you try to find the
parameters of the approximation that
give you a good policy we're going to
focus primarily in value space
approximation less than policy space but
I'm going to mention both of these in my
lecture today
okay now simulation is I've mentioned so
many times simulation why simulation
important for us we may have a perfectly
deterministic problem why do we want to
simulate it with Monte Carlo random
number generators and random
trajectories that seems a little strange
the idea is is simple and it's it's very
important
let me to understand it so why do we use
simulation
there are two reasons and the main
reason is that it helps the computation
large problems involve huge calculations
for example inner products the simpler
operation from linear algebra is to
compute an inner product of two vectors
to compute an inner product of two very
large vectors requires a very large
computation so can we simplify that it
turns out that simulation can simplify
this calculation and you may have heard
about methods for computing integrals
complicated integrals by Monte Carlo
integration it's the same idea so let me
describe this we want to compute
efficiently sums or expected values
involving a very large number of terms
one per state let's say well any sum of
this form let's take a generic sum
involving summation of n numbers a 1 up
to a n then I can write this as an
expected value like this I introduce a
probability distribution so I want side
2 and so on up to size the vector
components I want up to say n it could
be a uniform distribution like 1 over N
probability for every I what it could be
it does not have to be uniform it can be
any kind of probability distribution I
can write the Sun like so ok multiply
and divide with sy and this becomes the
expected value of the ratio AI of XII
with respect to the distribution of the
Y vector so any summation can be written
as computing an expected value in
computing an expected value can be done
either by adding the terms or by
flipping coins in doing simulation now
if the number of terms is gigantic it
may be better to flip coins fewer number
of times
and get an approximation which however
may be adequate for practical purposes
this is a method that's used very widely
in all sorts of fields and it's an idea
that's important in our context and here
it is again the expected value or the
sum can be approximated by generating
many samples change samples from 1 up to
M and according to this distribution
site and doing Monte Carlo averaging in
other words approximate this son with a
Monte Carlo average corresponding to the
samples that you have generated
potentially it's a lot fewer
computations if n again is very very
large so that's one reason doing linear
algebra operations in a product's matrix
vector multiplies involving gigantic
matrices and gigantic vectors there's a
second reason why simulation is also
convenient I mentioned model free
operation if I don't have a mathematical
model of the system and I have instead a
computer model of the system I can use
simulation to carry out values of the
algorithms that that we are interested
in like valuing policy narration these
are the two main reasons lack of an
analytical model and instead having
simple access to simulation and
computing large sums a complexity a
computational complexity issue
okay I think questions before we go into
more specifics okay let's discuss in
some generality approximation in value
and policy space first of all
approximation and value space what this
amounts to is replacing J star or J mu
from some other using some other
function from a parametric class in
other words this J till the eyes of R is
a vector one with one component for
every state but depending on a parameter
vector R okay so R is a parameter vector
and this is some functional form that I
haven't told you anything about yet how
you how you pick it but that's the idea
of using some parametric approximation
to J star or genu and then we can use
them right in various theoretical
expressions or in values algorithms and
so on okay now what is the role of this
parameter this J tilde is a function
okay a function of state if you choose
one value of parameter it may be
something like this another value of
parameter it's different something like
that for each value of the parameter we
get different functions now you have
something that you want to approximate
and you want to adjust the parameters so
that you get a good fit between the two
that's the idea
that's the role of the parameter we can
change the shape of J tilde so that it's
close to J star or J nu so how are the
issues here the first one is to select
the parametric class which is also
called the approximation architecture do
you want this J tilde to be linear in R
you want it to be quadratic do you want
it to be polynomial do you want it to
have a more complicated expression this
choice is very important because that
becomes your new search space within
which you're going to
do your approximation the second field
is after you have selected the
approximation architecture find a good
method for for obtaining the parameters
this is called training the architecture
you may have heard of training neural
networks training neural networks neural
networks is an approximation
architecture that depends on certain
parameters training the neural network
means adjusting the parameters based on
data to achieve a certain objective so
choice of approximation architecture and
then training the architecture by using
some kind of algorithm and these are the
two key issues success depends very
strongly on how these two issues are
handled and of course it's important to
have insight about the problem in order
to make good choices here now the
training may be done using a simulator
if you have or may be done using the
real system and but if there is no
mathematical model and we are going to
focus on the case of simulation but
there are many other possibilities that
I'm not going to get into also we may
use parametric approximation for J star
or J nu but yet there is also an
alternative of approximating two factors
or cost function differences in the
previous two lectures I mentioned that
there is this possibility of using two
factors which are associated with
statement repairs we may want to
approximate those or cost function
differences that may be another idea of
using approximation to get something
close to those
okay how about approximation
architectures well they are divided in
linear and nonlinear linear dependence
of J tilde on R or nonlinear dependence
linear architectures are easier to train
easier to deal with they have more
algorithms and with better performance
guarantees on relative to nonlinear
architectures but there are some
nonlinear architectures which are very
useful in practice neural networks is
one possibility I don't know if you if
you know about how much you know about
neural networks I do not have time to
explain but what I can tell you is that
they involve a sequence of mappings that
are nonlinear nonlinear and depend on
parameter R on the parameter vector R so
so they given I they give you a J tilde
sub I of R where R is whatever parameter
happens to be in the network now
neuronal would have their own culture
and their own algorithms by which you
train them and there are very rich class
of of
of architectures but we're not going to
look at those we're gonna focus
primarily on linear architectures now
linear architecture quite rich as well
and I'll explain why okay here's a
here's an example of an architecture
from computer chess computer chess has
made great strides now computer chess
programs can be to do routinely with the
world champion okay they start from very
low but over a period of time then
improved a great deal thanks also to
great advances in computing hardware
what does chest' have to do with
approximation architectures well at each
point in again there's a board position
the current board position think of this
board position as the state of the game
and think of all the moves that you can
make at the
position has controls or decisions so
you have you have the state and you have
also all these possible decisions and
you want to calculate the score for each
move that's like a Q factor okay state
control pair you want to evaluate a
number that tells you how good this move
is now the way chess programs do is they
involve a feature extraction mapping
first of all they project several moves
forward okay and then at the end of the
search they look at that at a position
and they extract some features from it
now the features are things that chess
play is recognized as being important
like for example the material balance do
I have more material than my opponent
okay that's good do I have more mobility
in the sense that I can move my pieces
to more squares than my opponent that's
also a good feature safety of my King
strategic features open files and so on
they're like 30 40 50 features that just
players take into account and these are
weighted with various weighting factors
and all of this is put into this
complicated position evaluator and
outcomes the score which is the Q factor
associated with the starting position
with your current position and the move
that you are considering so you get a
score for this move for that move for
that move for that move and you pick the
move that gives you the highest score
and that's the way the computer chess
programs work generally speaking there
are very few features in this mapping
involves a few unknowns actually the the
the number of features is like I said 30
40 50 so there are only a few parameter
40-50 parameters to select in this box
the number of possible chess positions
of course is astronomical get your
search space
involves against your position evaluator
involves only a few numbers and it's
quite remarkable that it worked so well
now in computer chess the weights of
various features have been selected
empirically over time over a period of
50 years okay people have found that
this they look at the performance of the
chess program and they decide to maybe
increase the weight of subcreature
relative to another feature and and that
and through trial and error good
position evaluators have developed in
our field we want to do this more
systematically so let's look first at
linear approximation architectures the
function that we want to approximate may
be very very complicated however if we
have good features that encode a lot of
the non-linearity a lot of the
complexity of the cost function then if
we can use such features then we can do
simple weighting between them like
linear waiting so if you have if the
non-linearity inheriting the cost
function is encoded in the features then
the approximation may be quite accurate
without a complicated architecture XT
after an extreme example the ideal
feature is the true function you want to
evaluate if you had that then that would
be great you need anything else if you
have something that's approximately that
then that's a good feature and then you
can use simple waiting for being for the
architecture so with one chosen features
we can use a linear architecture okay a
linear architecture is described by
these three terms which are called the
features of state I now for each state I
these are all vector of features prime
denotes transposition R is a vector
weights
and this gives you a number the inner
product between the feature vector of
the state and the weights that you are
considering the cost associated with the
overall cost function that's associated
with R is a linear combination of the
columns of a certain matrix this is a
Miss fee matrix is a matrix that has a
row dimension equal to the state number
of states and column dimension equal to
the number of features sophie is a
gigantic matrix in the long direction
and a short matrix in the horizontal
direction its columns are this Phi of
Phi I capital they can be viewed as
basis functions for a subspace
approximation in particular J tilde is
some function within a lower dimensional
space spanned by the columns of the
matrix field and once you have a certain
vector R a certain vector weights you
have you can take any state extract the
features associated with that state
extract the feature vector Phi I and
then wait linearly with r and you obtain
the approximation associated with state
I this J tilde eyes are of course what's
important here is to find good features
that characterize well being the state
so for example this so for example if
the optimal cost function
you know that's approximately quadratic
well you might use as features a
polynomial a quadratic polynomial this
face here each row is involves a
constant a linear for
a constant I I squared and so on
okay there are many examples of feature
types polynomial approximation radial
basis functions is a very very extensive
literature in methodology a societal
approximation and I'm going to give you
some examples the first and simplest is
polynomial approximation for example a
quadratic approximation function suppose
that the state is I from and the same I
has two dimensions let's say you're
considering two dimensional space
approximation so there are two
components I 1 and I 2 three dimensional
and so on these are not States the
desired dimensions the components of the
state vector so you may consider a
quadratic approximation involving for
each I which is of this form a linear
weighting of these components plus a
quadratic weighting of these components
so this is in two dimensions a quadratic
kind of function and the coefficients
are this is the constant coefficient a
coefficient that multiplies the linear
terms and a coefficient that multiplies
the quadratic terms so the R vector has
all of these components here so that's a
quadratic fit it could you could have a
quad linear a linear feed or cubic fit
to be to be function that you want to
approximate another possibility is
interpolation you have this function
that you want to approximate it you take
some selected points and you calculate
the dysfunction and then you make a
piecewise constant approximation now the
values are the selected points are
exactly your features also you do not
need to have you you do not need to have
a a piecewise constant approximation you
may have a piecewise linear approximate
or a piecewise quadratic approximation
all of this fits into the interpolation
category so let me read here you select
a subset I of special representative
states and the parameter vector has one
component R I press state and then the
approximating function is exactly RI at
the selected points and some
interpolation for the intermediate
points using the values at I could be a
linear interpolation quadratic
interpolation spline or whatever many
possibilities okay so this is standard
stuff people in numerical analysis do
this sort of thing all the time they
approximate the solutions of partial
differential equations with piecewise
constant functions splines linear and
wavelets
many different ways now here's another
example which is sort of more problem
specific you look at your problem and
you try to figure out what are the
features that are important for this
problem and then you construct an
architecture based on that I don't know
if you know this game I know that video
games are popular in China and this is
one of the first video games Tetris to
visit this is it known in in China in
Tetris you have you have you have a
certain matrix of possessions and and
then objects fall from the top and then
you try to fit them onto the top of the
wall and then you can move them
horizontally or rotate them and there
are several different types of objects
and they come in and each time you
complete a row solid row you gain a
point you eliminate that row and then
the wall goes down by one and the
objective is to play for as long as
possible
earn as many points as possible before
the war
rises up all the way to the top at which
time the game stops okay so this is a
problem that can be viewed as a dynamic
programming problem the starting state
is the empty board the the the state at
any point is the the board position you
know the zeros and ones where in this
matrix there is an object or there is
it's filled or it's empty there's a
gigantic number of states for a standard
ten by twenty board the number of state
is created by two to the 200 now I don't
know if you have a you can think of how
big to to the 200 is but it's more than
the number of molecules in the entire
universe okay it's it's a gigantic
number now why is this a control problem
well at every state there is and given
any object that falls I have a different
set of different options I can move it
horizontally and I can rotate it okay so
this is my decision the number of
controls here are in the order of of
let's say 30 or something like that
okay the number of states is gigantic
the control space is relatively small
there is randomness here
while there is randomness because the
object that comes out is random it can
take one of several shapes so there is
randomness and there is there are
decisions this cost or reward every time
you eliminate that row you get one point
okay so you want to maximize number of
oh let's minimize number of negative
role negative number of rows that you
have and what is J star J star sub I is
the optimal score starting from position
I so from the starting position this J
starts off of the empty board and for
any possible board position there is a
corresponding optimal score that you can
get if you are an optimal player if you
are the world champion
we were the absolute optimal because
nobody now has to have to play optimally
and and nobody can calculate this
j-stars of I there is such a vector but
it has dimension greater than two to the
200 and we will never calculate it what
we can do instead is culturally an
approximation of that using some kind of
algorithm likely involved in simulation
and use the J tilde in place of J star
in choosing a move now this problem has
been started quite a bit has a history
of more than twenty twenty years I think
it was at MIT I was involved also when
it got started and and and even though
the problem is so gigantic with just
twenty two features we have been able to
get a reasonably good tested Tetris
players using policy direction in other
words you start from a certain bad that
display a very primitive player and then
that's your initial policy in a policy
duration scheme then you train using
this twenty two features the
corresponding architecture to obtain
well you use simulation to calculate the
score that this the average score that
this player can achieve then you obtain
a better player by using policy
improvement and so on and starting from
players that would achieve like an
average of thirty points per game we got
up to like three thousand points four
thousand points five thousand points for
various variations and we were very
happy than we thought that this is just
great and indeed for a forum for a
number of years for like maybe ten
fifteen years this was the best that
could be achieved eventually people
started using other methods
and it turned out that with other
methods not policy duration methods we
the schools that were achieved were in
the order of seven hundred thousand nine
hundred thousand so we thought that
we're doing well but we have no way of
telling of course because we did not
know the optimal scores and yet was not
possible to get with a small number of
features either twenty-two features or
some other additional features very very
high scores so an interesting probably
has been used as a testbed in
competitions okay like they have
competitions but finding a good soccer
player about finding you know a good
chess player and they have a competition
for for tetris players now let me tell
you also quite a bit 22 features the
approximation architecture used here is
a linear weighting of 22 numbers 22
numbers that when you look at a certain
position you extract these 22 numbers
from the position and you weigh them
with corresponding weights
what are these features well if you are
a Tetris player you sort of recognize
these features an important feature is
how high the world is okay and in
particular how high the different
columns are so that's ten features right
there for a if there are ten columns the
height of each column gives you ten
features what's also important is the
difference between the heights of
successive columns if you have a at the
top you have a lot of jaggedness
a lot of differences between heights
that's a bad thing so by taking
differences of heights you get another
nine features the number of holes in the
wall is an important feature we the
there was a constant that was viewed as
a feature and there was one more that I
can't remember but there are features of
this study the only 22 numbers that's
the important thing
even though you have as a cost vector
that is gigantic it is only at a low
dimensional 2222 dimensional subspace
over which you approximate it and yet
you get a very very good very very good
performance so we have standard
approximation architectures and we have
also the main specific approximation
architectures like in chess and Tetris
and now let's see how these architects
are used with policy duration we can use
simulation to approximate the cost of
the current policy and then generate an
improved policy by minimizing in the
approximate bellman equation so here is
approximate policy direction for costs
you start with a certain policy you
evaluate this policy approximately by
using an approximation architecture in
finding J tilde sub nu essentially
finding are the corresponding vector
associate with the sponsor then given
that you go into balance equation and
find an improved policy nu bar and then
you go back evaluate that and so on so
it's the same policy direction that you
have for exact points evaluation except
that you use an approximate an
approximation architecture in between so
in the context of Tetris you start with
a certain policy for playing Tetris you
play a lot of games and you evaluate the
score of that policy from be
approximated by find corresponding
vector of parameters then using that you
generate a new Tetris player you can
calculate the decisions online using
this function here for nu bar and then
evaluate
and so on alternatively you could use
you could approximate the cue factors of
MU where you start with a certain
initial policy evaluate approximate few
factors involving a parameter vector R
and then generate an improved policy by
just minimizing the new policy is
obtained by minimizing and finding the
optimal Q factor at any minimize no
value and frankly a problem that the
optimal Q factor at point I I'm sorry
that this letters are a little bit small
I don't know how well you can read them
have any questions
okay now we use approximation in the
context of policy in aeration to
approximate the cost or the two factors
of policies an alternative is to try to
approximate directly J star or Q star Q
learning is an algorithm for finding the
optimal few factors the optimal two
factors as you recall are given by this
expression they are the sum of the one
stage costs associated with I in here
plus the expected cost to go using an
optimal policy and if you know the Q
factors Q star you can't calculate the
optimal costs by by means of by
minimization so that's one possibility
this Q learning algorithm that aims at
finding directly Q star in jstor there's
also another method called the bellman
equation error approach remember bellman
equations J equals TJ so if you so if
you form a least squares objective where
you minimize over all functions J this
error in satisfying the equation then
the optimal solutions is J star and and
so however if you look over an
approximation architecture what you try
to do here is minimize the errors in
satisfying Bellman's equation using J
tilde and you minimize over all possible
parameter vectors so this is a generic
approach for solving approximately
equations you within a certain within a
certain class of approximations you try
to find one that minimizes the error in
satisfying this equation the expected
value here is taken with respect to some
distribution over the state so this is a
number and this involves this is Lee
squares but non linear least squares
because T is a nonlinear mapping
there's another method called
approximately I programming but let's
not discuss it here you can find in the
literature where is pure learning in its
standard form finds exact values of Q
star and J star it can be used also with
approximations although not very
rigorously we'll get into that later
also you can use both Q learning and the
bellman error approach in the context of
approximating of a policy evaluation as
opposed to calculating we exact exactly
optimal functions so you can either
approximate the cost of policies or the
Q factors of policies or the optimal
things and now all of this had to do
with approximation in value space let me
just spend one slide on approximation in
policy space we want to find an optimal
policy we want to find a new in the
control action for every R suppose that
we parameterize the set of policies
using some parameter vector we use some
parametric form of policies for example
we may look at linear policies that are
of this form without this quadratic term
or you may look at quadratic policies
with this r1 r2 and r3 being weights
and/or you may want to look at a linear
feature based kind of approximation
where the parameterization of policy is
is done through feature functions of the
state with corresponding weights are so
once you define approximation
architecture your search space becomes a
limited subset of the set of all
policies and then you may minimize over
all of this this limited search space so
each value of art defines a stationary
policy with with cost at state ID noted
by J tilde isin R then you try to find
our that minimizes a certain objective
that involve some weighting of the
states so our parameter Isis policies
you plug those policies in they give you
some kind of cost for each state then
you weigh this by probabilities and then
you minimize that and it's possible to
to to have methods to minimize
objectives like that involving gradient
methods random search other kinds of
methods these are its variety of
possibilities this is very different
than approximation in value space there
is no policy duration policy improvement
this is more direct search parameterize
the objects of interest and then do some
kind of a search to find an optimal
object within this class it's also
possible to make a connection with
parametric architectures for course for
example if you introduce a cost
approximation architecture J hat which
depends on R then you can obtain a
parametric class of policies that's
obtained by minimization in bellman
equation so this is sort of indirect
parameterization of policies through
parameterization of the cost function
okay I'm going to have a few things to
say about proximation policy space in
the in the in in the last lecture
however let me just mention that the
Tetra success that I mentioned earlier
the fact that policy duration type of
algorithms gave you scores like 5,000
points and then there were some other
methods that gave you many years later
we tried many League years later and
they gave you scores of
the hundreds of thousands five hundred
thousand seven hundred thousand and
million points out on the con the
average per game the methods were of
this type okay there were a random
search type of methods in the space of
policies so these methods have to show
some impressive successes as well even
though they have a little bit less of a
over solid theoretical foundation behind
them okay I think it's a good time to
break here have any questions we have
been discussing these this these broad
issues for approximation in particular
approximation architectures and
Proclamation value space and policy
space all of this is done very quickly
we're going to come back to it in next
week in more details at least parts of
them but are any questions now yeah
okay so the question is okay given this
approximate policy direction you have a
policy and when you evaluate it how do
you do you update are at the same time
as we update the policy well you do
because our defines the approximation so
our depends on mu you find forgiven you
you find R that gives you a good
approximation to the cost of that new
cost function of that new so this should
be ours of mu okay it's cool
so you're different so actually the
policies you never you never see them
they are too big to be eyeballed okay
they are gigantic they have gigantic
number of components what you have is in
fact a vector of parameters R which is a
much smaller quantity so you move from
one hour to an hour R to another R but
implicitly you evaluate these policies
and you do increase the policy
improvement
I'm sorry how to how to calculate our
okay so that's a major issue
how do okay how do you calculate our
here to do this Li squared is this
fitting between J nu and J tilde the
initial policy how do you choose the
initial policy okay
in principle it can be anything it can
be any policy in practice you may have
some good policy some reasonable policy
that you may be able to implement and
calculate the corresponding R
[Music]
in optimal control ok nocturnal control
you mean how do we get started not know
control how do we find an initial policy
not know control ok by optimal control I
think you mean a continuous time system
described by differential equations in
how do you find a feedback function to
start with that's what that's what I
thought nope that's what the policy is
right so ordinarily enough no control
the most important thing is to have a
stable policy a policy that stabilized
the system and gives you a stable
differential equation that converges to
some equilibrium in some way good or bad
slow or fast but at least it converges
and does not explode it's not unstable
so you got to have to apply policy
direction the context of control of this
type you need to have an initial stable
policy
yes now the nice thing is here is we
start with a stable policy policy
duration ordinarily we'll give you
another stable policy we'll give you a
sequence of stable policies that's a
consequence of the policy improvement
property that each policy is better than
the previous one this is true of course
in in exact dynamic programming if you
introduce approximations it is possible
that you may start with a stable policy
okay I think what your ass is how do we
find good features and how do we know
that we have good features what happens
if we missed some good features well if
you miss some good features then you're
going to get something worse than what
when what we might have that whether the
better features you have the better
performance you will get and the more
features you have the better performance
you'll get at least in principle the
however how do you get good features how
do you get good features is mostly an
art to a great extent it is an art and
also a question of insight into your
problem like for example if you ask a
person who has never played Tetris to
select good features for the tetris game
he will not be very successful it's
through some experience with a
particular type of problem that you get
insight about what are good features and
what are not
there are also some automatic methods
for choosing features
based on the performance of certain
features you add some more features
which is okay it's it's something that
is a methodology that's still in the
experimental phase and has not been
fully established as far as I know if
you okay so what you're asking is if you
have a certain set of features and
you're not sure if this is an ideal set
okay you're looking for some more
features if you add some more then we'll
things get better is it possible the
bacon get worse it's not very likely it
will get worse the reason is the
following if you have more features that
means that you are expanding the
subspace over which you're doing an
approximation with fewer features you
get only a subset of that subspace so if
your approximation method is good
getting giving yourself more options to
approximate from should help you but of
course this is under ideal circumstances
and this there's no guarantee so it's
principle it's it's possible in
principle that you take a method you add
more features and you're not doing
better now it's possible that you that
that the new features that you add are
not very good you think they might be
good but they are not very good also but
it's also possible that so there is so
how do you find good features it's
really not a question that doesn't have
a clear answer and as an example let me
mention to you this Tetris
problem the initial features chosen for
this tetris problem gave a score of
about fifty an average of 50 points but
per game when the features were
increased to 22 we got into the
thousands
now people added some more features and
were able to get even higher with 22
some more and some more they want to get
a lot higher and we don't know if there
are some hidden features that nobody has
ever discovered yet but if you add them
in you might not go into the hundreds of
millions of score okay we just don't
know that unless you have J star the
optimal cost factor which is
unattainable usually there's no way of
telling how good your approximation is
and whether you're using good features
you need fixed point so we get the
optimal just our given function goes
high and means we get our feature
selected not equally not yes also so
that'll narrow function because Metin is
known in your neck yeah I think you're
making good points what you're saying is
that one way to tell whether we have a
reasonably good approach in a reasonably
some reasonably good features is to look
at the error that we're making in
satisfying Bellman's equation if we had
the ideal features that error would be
identically zero however if we get an
error that's large okay how can you tell
it's large well maybe you can tell maybe
not if that looks large than that that
gives you the thought that you should be
searching for some better features
we can dynamically add some filtering
system with coffee yes some people also
have looked at approaches like that
dynamically
sparsity yeah
okay again you're making very good
points the you're saying that in machine
learning there's a lot of interest in
learning good features and identifying
good features and perhaps some of this
could be applied here I suspect that it
can but it but it hasn't been done yet
and you mentioned the methodology of
compressed sensing where you you want to
you have you have a certain parametric
model that has a lot of weights and you
know that some of them are 0 should be 0
and you're looking for a metric
parameterization that has only few
nonzero weights and relatively few
features and compressed sensing allows
you to do that by adding to the bellmen
error function little squares from
objective if you are beyond 1 norm yes
you're right if you add the l1 known
here then you will get compressed
sensing type of effect you'd get sparse
solutions to my knowledge nobody has
tried that look at Belmont error methods
with with l1 norm has not been done it
it should be doable but has not been
done to it as far as right now maybe
someone can do a thesis on it certainly
a worthwhile topic because it allows you
to not to worry too much about the
correct features but just put many
features in there and then the the
algorithm will figure out which ones are
important and which are not
any other questions
I am I'm afraid that the the clarity is
not very good though that of the type
and I don't know what to do about maybe
maybe in the next lecture we'll improve
it but I'm having a hard time reading it
and I'm standing in front of the first
Rojo okay maybe we can fix it while we
take a break let's take a break for ten
minutes and we'll be back okay